<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nist.govs on </title>
    <link>/nist.gov/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nist.govs on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	<atom:link href="/nist.gov/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/nist.gov/sp800-53/readme/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/nist.gov/sp800-53/readme/</guid>
      <description>NIST produced OSCAL content for NIST Special Publication 800-53 NIST is maintining OSCAL content for multiple revisions of the NIST Special Publication (SP) 800-53.
OSCAL XML-, JSON-, and YAML-based content is provided for the following revisions:
 NIST SP 800-53 Revision 4 OSCAL catalog and baseline profiles content. NIST SP 800-53 Revision 5 Final Public Draft (FPD) OSCAL catalog content.
Note: In the SP 800-53 Revision 5 FPD, the control catalog and control baselines are separated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/nist.gov/sp800-53/rev4/readme/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/nist.gov/sp800-53/rev4/readme/</guid>
      <description>NIST SP 800-53 Examples This subdirectory contains provisional stable, best effort versions of OSCAL catalogs and profiles related to NIST SP800-53. While not authoritative, as examples these are useful as demonstrations (as can be established by comparing them with their originals). The files have been produced by a combination of automated and semi-automated (editorial) processes.
Note that in many ordinary working scenarios, users of OSCAL will not be writing or creating catalogs or low-level baselines (profiles) such as these, but only referencing them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/nist.gov/sp800-53/rev5/xml/nist_sp-800-53_rev5-fpd_catalog-preview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/nist.gov/sp800-53/rev5/xml/nist_sp-800-53_rev5-fpd_catalog-preview/</guid>
      <description>NIST Special Publication 800-53: Security and Privacy Controls for Federal Information Systems and Organizations, Revision 5 Final Public Draft .tag { color: green; font-family: sans-serif; font-size: 80%; font-weight: bold } .UNKNOWN { color: red; font-family: sans-serif; font-size: 80%; font-weight: bold } .UNKNOWN .tag { color: darkred } .lbl { background-color: midnightblue; color: white; font-size: 80%; font-weight: bold; font-family: sans-serif; padding: 0.2em 0.5em; margin: 0em 0.5em 0em 0em } .lbl2 { background-color: white; color: black; border: thin solid black; font-size: 80%; font-weight: bold; font-family: sans-serif; padding: 0.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>