<control class="SP800-53" id="ac-1">
  <title>Access Control Policy and Procedures</title>
  <param id="ac-1_prm_1">
    <label>organization-defined personnel or roles</label>
  </param>
  <param id="ac-1_prm_2">
    <label>organization-defined frequency</label>
  </param>
  <param id="ac-1_prm_3">
    <label>organization-defined frequency</label>
  </param>
  <prop class="label">AC-1</prop>
  <part class="statement" id="ac-1_smt">
    <p>The organization:</p>
    <part class="item" id="ac-1_smt.a">
      <prop class="label">a.</prop>
      <p>Develops, documents, and disseminates to <insert param-id="ac-1_prm_1"/>:</p>
      <part class="item" id="ac-1_smt.a.1">
        <prop class="label">1.</prop>
        <p>An access control policy that addresses purpose, scope, roles, responsibilities, management commitment, coordination among organizational entities, and compliance; and</p>
      </part>
      <part class="item" id="ac-1_smt.a.2">
        <prop class="label">2.</prop>
        <p>Procedures to facilitate the implementation of the access control policy and associated access controls; and</p>
      </part>
    </part>
    <part class="item" id="ac-1_smt.b">
      <prop class="label">b.</prop>
      <p>Reviews and updates the current:</p>
      <part class="item" id="ac-1_smt.b.1">
        <prop class="label">1.</prop>
        <p>Access control policy <insert param-id="ac-1_prm_2"/>; and</p>
      </part>
      <part class="item" id="ac-1_smt.b.2">
        <prop class="label">2.</prop>
        <p>Access control procedures <insert param-id="ac-1_prm_3"/>.</p>
      </part>
    </part>
  </part>
  <part class="guidance" id="ac-1_gdn">
    <p>This control addresses the establishment of policy and procedures for the effective implementation of selected security controls and control enhancements in the AC family. Policy and procedures reflect applicable federal laws, Executive Orders, directives, regulations, policies, standards, and guidance. Security program policies and procedures at the organization level may make the need for system-specific policies and procedures unnecessary. The policy can be included as part of the general information security policy for organizations or conversely, can be represented by multiple policies reflecting the complex nature of certain organizations. The procedures can be established for the security program in general and for particular information systems, if needed. The organizational risk management strategy is a key factor in establishing policy and procedures.</p>
    <link rel="related" href="#pm-9">PM-9</link>
  </part>
  <references>
    <link href="#ref050" rel="reference">NIST Special Publication 800-12</link>
    <link href="#ref044" rel="reference">NIST Special Publication 800-100</link>
  </references>
</control>