<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<catalog xmlns="http://scap.nist.gov/schema/catalog"
    xmlns:xh11d="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/datatypes/"
    xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"    
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xPCI="http://oscal.nist.gov/schema/extension-PCI"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://oscal.nist.gov/schema/core
    	file://../xsd/OSCAL-core.xsd
        http://oscal.nist.gov/schema/extension-PCI
    	file://../xsd/OSCAL-extension-catalog-PCI.xsd">

    <!--
         xmlns:x80053="http://oscal.nist.gov/schema/extension-catalog-800-53"
    xsi:schemaLocation="
        http://oscal.nist.gov/schema/core file://../xsd/OSCAL-core.xsd
        http://oscal.nist.gov/schema/extension-catalog-800-53 file://../xsd/OSCAL-extension-800-53.xsd"
        -->
        
    <id>PCIv3_2ver01a_req1</id>
    <name>Build and Maintain a Secure Network</name>
    <version>1</version>
    <summary>TBD</summary>
    <meta>
        <property name="requirement" type="xsd:string"/>
        <item>
            <property name="requirement" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1" />
            <property name="parameter" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded" />
        </item>
    </meta>
    
    <items>
        <item>
            <type>requirement</type>
            <id>1</id>
            <title>Install and maintain a firewall configuration to protect cardholder data</title>
        	<statement>
        		<description>Firewalls are devices that control computer traffic allowed between an entity’s networks (internal) and untrusted networks (external), as well as
traffic into and out of more sensitive areas within an entity’s internal trusted networks. The cardholder data environment is an example of a more sensitive area within an entity’s trusted network.
A firewall examines all network traffic and blocks those transmissions that do not meet the specified security criteria.
All systems must be protected from unauthorized access from untrusted networks, whether entering the system via the Internet as e-commerce, employee Internet access through desktop browsers, employee e-mail access, dedicated connections such as business-to-business connections, via wireless networks, or via other sources. Often, seemingly insignificant paths to and from untrusted networks can provide unprotected pathways into key systems. Firewalls are a key protection mechanism for any computer network.
Other system components may provide firewall functionality, as long as they meet the minimum requirements for firewalls as defined in Requirement 1. Where other system components are used within the cardholder data environment to provide firewall functionality, these devices must be included within the scope and assessment of Requirement 1.</description>
            </statement>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control</type>
            <id>1.1</id>
            <statement>
            	<description>Establish and implement firewall and router configuration standards that include the following:</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href='#1' />
            <properties>
                <!-- These properties validated under schema extension for 800-53 catalog -->
                    <xPCI:guidance>
                        <xPCI:description>Firewalls and routers are key components of the architecture that controls entry to and exit from the network. These devices are software or hardware devices that block unwanted access and manage authorized access into and out of the network.
Configuration standards and procedures will help to ensure that the organization’s first line of defense in the protection of its data remains strong.
                        </xPCI:description>
                    </xPCI:guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control</type>
            <id>1.1.1</id>
            <statement>
                <description>A formal process for approving and testing all network connections and changes to the firewall and router configurations</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#1.1"/>
            <properties>
                <!-- These properties validated under schema extension for 800-53 catalog -->
                    <xPCI:guidance>
                        <xPCI:description>A documented and implemented process for approving and testing all connections and changes to the firewalls and routers will help prevent security problems caused by misconfiguration of the network, router, or firewall.
Without formal approval and testing of changes, records of the changes might not be updated, which could lead to inconsistencies between network documentation and the actual configuration.
                        </xPCI:description>
                    </xPCI:guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control</type>
            <id>1.1.2</id>
            <statement>
                <description>Current network diagram that identifies all connections between the cardholder data environment and other networks, including any wireless networks</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#1.1"/>
            <properties>
                <!-- These properties validated under schema extension for 800-53 catalog -->
                    <xPCI:guidance>
                        <xPCI:description>Network diagrams describe how networks are configured, and identify the location of all network devices.
Without current network diagrams, devices could be overlooked and be unknowingly left out of the security controls implemented for PCI DSS and thus be vulnerable to compromise.
                        </xPCI:description>
                    </xPCI:guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control</type>
            <id>1.1.3</id>
            <statement>
                <description>Current diagram that shows all cardholder data flows across systems and networks</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#1.1"/>
            <properties>
                <!-- These properties validated under schema extension for 800-53 catalog -->
                    <xPCI:guidance>
                        <xPCI:description>Cardholder data-flow diagrams identify the location of all cardholder data that is stored, processed, or transmitted within the network.
Network and cardholder data-flow diagrams help an organization to understand and keep track of the scope of their environment, by showing how cardholder data flows across networks and between individual systems and devices.
                        </xPCI:description>
                    </xPCI:guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
    </items>
</catalog>
