<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Contribute on OSCAL</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/contribute/</link><description>Recent content in Contribute on OSCAL</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/contribute/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Contact Us</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/contribute/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/contribute/contact/</guid><description>GitHub.com Repository Please visit our GitHub repository for more information, schemas, and examples.
Chat with Us You can chat with us directly on the OSCAL Gitter.
Contact by Email Please email the OSCAL team with any questions you have about this project or if you are interested in getting involved.
We also offer a couple of mailing lists.
oscal-dev@nist.gov for communication among parties interested in contributing to the development of OSCAL or exchanging ideas.</description></item><item><title>Lunch with the Devs</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/contribute/devlunch/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/contribute/devlunch/</guid><description>To increase communication with the OSCAL community, the NIST OSCAL team is hosting a one-hour teleconference every two weeks starting on Thursday, December 5th 2019 @ noon EST.
Global
Note: (1/10/2020) The Bluejeans info below has changed.
Meeting Link Bluejeans Details
Call-in Numbers :
https://nist.bluejeans.com/ Meeting ID: 187 858 571 Participant Passcode: 0183
Phone Dial-in
+1.408.317.9254 (US (San Jose)) +1.408.740.7256 (US (San Jose)) Global Numbers
Who Can Attend Open to All Members of the Public</description></item><item><title>OSCAL Development Roadmap</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/contribute/roadmap/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/contribute/roadmap/</guid><description>OSCAL is a community-driven, NIST-led project, with an open invitation to the community to participate in the framing and development of OSCAL. Feature requests can be created and submitted directly into the project&amp;rsquo;s GitHub repository. Feedback in the form of bug reports are also encouraged and appreciated. If appropriate, we ask you add a comment to an existing relevant issue, and only create a new issue when no relevant issue exists.</description></item></channel></rss>