<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../oscal-working.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../CSS/oscal.css" title="Straight" alternate="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../CSS/oscal-ui.css" title="Formal" alternate="yes"?>
<?xml-model href="oscal-docs.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<catalog xmlns="http://scap.nist.gov/schema/oscal">
  <title>OSCAL: the Open Security Controls Assessment Language</title>
  <!--<declarations>
    <property context="element-description" class="tag">
          <required/>
      <identifier/>
          <regex>\i\c*</regex>
      <!-\- An XML name -\->
        </property>
    <property context="element-description" class="full_name"/>
    <feature context="element-description general-constraint" class="description">
      <required/>
    </feature>
    <part context="element-description" class="remarks"/>
    <property context="term-definition" class="term"/>
    <part context="term-definition" class="definition"/>
  </declarations>-->
  <section>
    <title>OSCAL namespace</title>
    <p>Determine the element population of an OSCAL document (set) bmo XPath
        <code>distinct-values(//*/node-name())</code></p>
    <p>Valid OSCAL documents will not contain elements not described in this specification. While
      OSCAL may be mixed with other tag sets, or extended, neither of these applications is
      addressed in any way by this document. This document provides only bare-bones information
      about the OSCAL <q>core</q>.</p>
    <p>For its XML names, OSCAL uses the namespace <a>XXX http://scap.nist.gov/schema/oscal XXX</a>.
      Commonly, this will be assigned to (unprefixed) names in an OSCAL document by default, and in
      this document, OSCAL elements (and attributes, presumed to be in no-namespace) are referenced
      without a prefix, <code>oscal:</code> or any other.</p>
  </section>
  <group>
    <title>OSCAL terminology</title>
    <control class="term-definition">
      <prop class="term">Control object</prop>
      <part class="definition">
        <p>OSCAL catalogs are comprised of control objects, typically arranged in groups. The
          top-level control object is <code>control</code>. Other control objects are subcontrols
            (<code>subcontrol</code>) and features (<code>feat</code>). Subcontrols may only appear
          (directly) within controls. Features may appear within controls or subcontrols, or may be
          nested (to any depth) within features.</p>
        <p>Control objects in OSCAL may be characterized as consistent data structures, whose
          contents are appropriate to their type and application. The type of a control object is
          labelled by means of its <code>@class</code>. Control objects may validated for
          consistency between and among objects of the same type, by means of constraining values
          assigned to the control components (qv) appearing within them.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="term-definition">
      <prop class="term">Control component</prop>
      <part class="definition">
        <p>Control components are information objects that constitute particular controls. They
          include properties (<code>prop</code>), statements (<code>stmt</code>), features
            (<code>feat</code>), and parameters (<code>param</code>).</p>
        <p>Note that features (feat) are both control components (only appearing inside control
          objects) and themselves control objects (which may contain their own properties,
          statements, and features). As such they are <q>transitional</q> objects. Indeed they may
          be used for control components below the level of subcontrols. Typically, however, they
          will be more fragmentary, not providing useful information outside the context of the
          containing control object.</p>
        <p>The appearance (whether required or optional), cardinality, and values (of any control
          component) and/or components (of features) may be constrained and validated by means of
          the OSCAL declarations model. This enables catalogs and catalog types to enforce
          consistency of components across controls of identified and labeled types.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
  </group>
  <group>
    <title>Controls and control components</title>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">catalog</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Catalog</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Top-level element for a (canonical) control catalog</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">collection</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Collection</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Top-level element for a set of controls, not considered to be a catalog</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>Most often, a collection element will be used for a set of controls derived from one or
          more control catalogs (such as a profile, baseline or overlay), which do not themselves
          serve as a catalog.</p>
        <p>However, collections may contain everything that catalogs may contain, and OSCAL does not
          prohibit their use as (source or interim) catalogs for profiling. (Although an application
          might).</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">control</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Control</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>A structured information object representing a security control</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">subcontrol</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Control enhancement</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Within a control, a control object appearing as a component</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>This is a control object, just like a control, only related to a particular control by
          virtue of containment in the OSCAL instance. Control enhancements (subcontrols) may
          contain their own enhancements as well as control components (properties, statements
          etc.).</p>
        <p>Because either <code>control</code> or <code>subcontrol</code> may be grouped, the schema
          does not absolutely constrain that <code>subcontrol</code> appear only within
            <code>control</code> and never the reverse: this enforcement is left to a
          Schematron.</p>
        <p>Albeit not absolutely forbidden by the schema, the rule is that while both controls and
          subcontrols may contain subcontrols, neither may contain controls. That is, in any
          catalog, a control is only the <q>top level</q> of control object (even if gathered in
          groups) – all else is subcontrols (control enhancements) or control contents.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">prop</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Property</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>A value with a name, attributed to the containing control, subcontrol, feature or
          group</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>Like statements (<code>stmt</code>), features (<code>feat</code>) and parameters
            (<code>param</code>), properties are <q>named things</q> that appear within controls,
          subcontrols or features.</p>
        <p>Properties do not contain structured content, only values, albeit sometimes containing
          inline markup (<q>rich text</q>). Inasmuch as properties are often used as selectors or
          identifiers for OSCAL operations, their values can be expected frequently to be flattened
          (markup stripped) and normalized (e.g., with respect to whitespace) in use.</p>
        <p>When singletons (that is, the only element among siblings with its <code>@class</code>),
          properties are especially useful as proxies (unique identifiers) for their controls, such
          that controls may be returned one for one on queries for properties (name and value). The
          robustness of such queries can be ensured by appropriate property declarations (as
          singletons and as identifiers); cf <code>property</code> in the declarations model (which
          also supports other constraints over property values).</p>
        <p>Properties are the <q>bread and butter</q> of OSCAL; they enable the deployment and
          management of arbitrary controlled values, with and among control objects (controls and
          their formal enhancements), for any purpose useful to an application or implementation of
          those controls. Typically and routinely, properties will be used to sort, select, order
          and arrange controls or relate them to one another or to class hierarchies, taxonomies or
          external authorities.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">part</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Part</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>A component of a control, subcontrol or part</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>Like properties (<code>prop</code>) and parameters (<code>param</code>), parts can
          be distinguished from other elements within their controls by their assigned
            <code>@class</code>, such that they may be subjected to <q>declarations logic</q> using
          these values as bindings (and thereby getting open-ended extensibility).
            <code>@class</code> is however optional on <code>stmt</code></p>
        <p>An assigned class will typically also provide for a header in display, such that
            <code>stmt[@class='objectives']</code> is displayed under a header <em>Objectives</em>,
          etc. This is useful, since unlike controls, subcontrols, groups or even features
            (<code>feat</code>), statements may not have titles.</p>
        <p>Like anything in OSCAL, this element may be formally valid, without its contents or
          representations being correct, complete, veracious or even intelligible.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">link</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Link</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>A line or paragraph with a hypertext link</p>
      </part>
      
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">param</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Parameter</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>A parameter setting, to be propagated to points of injection</p>
      </part>
      
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">desc</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Parameter description</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Indicates and explains the purpose and use of a parameter</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    
  </group>
  <group>
    <title>Functional elements</title>
    <p>Functional elements appear inside control content to provide <q>hooks</q> to OSCAL processors
      for dynamic injection.</p>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">withdrawn</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Withdrawn</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Indicates that a containing control or subcontrol is no longer applicable</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>Used to mark a control or subcontrol included in a catalog as a placeholder, </p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">inject</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Parameter injection</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>A reference to a parameter for dynamic content transclusion</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">select</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Selection</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>A selection requiring designation via parameter</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">choice</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Choice</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>A choice of values, to be designated via parameter</p>
      </part>
    </control>
  </group>
  <group>
    <title>Declarations elements</title>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">declarations</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Declarations</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>For extra-schema validation of control components within controls</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>The OSCAL validation model supports not only validation against a formal schema
          (describing elements, attributes, and their permitted contents, described generally and
          generically), but also against a set of declarations provided specifically for the catalog
          or catalog type within which they appear. Constraints described in these declarations, and
          bound via assignments of <code>@class</code> (for control components) and
            <code>@context</code> (indicating control, subcontrol or features wherein the components
          may appear), enable automated checking for consistency of controls, subcontrols and
          features, specific to the types or kinds of control items that appear within a particular
          catalog or control collection.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">declare-property</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Property declaration</prop>
      <part class="description">
      <p>Constraints applicable to a class or classes of <code>p</code> elements within a control
        object</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">declare-p</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Paragraph declaration</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Indicates constraints to be enforced on paragraphs in context</p>
      </part>
      
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">declare-part</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Part declaration</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Indicates constraints to be imposed on parts in context</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">declare-link</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Link declaration</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Indicates constraints to be imposed on links in context</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">singleton</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Singleton constraint</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>The declared component may occur only once in its context</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>When this element is present in the declaration of an OSCAL control component, the
          component (<code>prop</code>, <code>param</code>, <code>stmt</code> or <code>feat</code>)
          must be the only component of that class given in its context. i.e., no other element
          child of the same parent may have the same <code>@class</code> value (at the level of
          syntax), or be bound to the same component type (at the semantic level).</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">required</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Requirement constraint</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>The declared component is required in its context</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>When this element is present in the declaration of an OSCAL control component, the
          component (<code>prop</code>, <code>param</code>, <code>stmt</code> or <code>feat</code>)
          is required to appear, at least once, in its context.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">identifier</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Identifier constraint</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>The declared component has a value unique within the document, among components of the
          same type</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>This constraint is generally only used for properties to be used as identifiers for their
          control object (control, subcontrol or feature). Guaranteeing their uniqueness means that
          these values can be used to effect one-to-one retrieval or reference to the objects to
          which they are assigned.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">regex</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Regular expression constraint</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Indicates that the value of a property (<code>prop)</code> or parameter
            (<code>param</code>) must match the given regular expression</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>Matching against a regular expression is conducted on the normalized lexical value of the
          given parameter or property: that is, with leading and trailing whitespace stripped,
          interim whitespace (space, tab or line feed) normalized to single spaces, and inline
          markup stripped.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">value</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Value constraint</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Indicates a permissible value for a parameter or property</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>Typically, <code>value</code> will be given in groups, indicating a set of enumerated
          permissible values.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">autonum</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Autonumbered (generated) value</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Generates a formatted numeric value based on the position of a control object among its
          siblings, the text contents providing a template for the numbering format (arabic,
          alphabetic, roman etc)</p>
      </part>
      
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">inherit</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Inherited value constraint</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Indicates that a value or part of a value will be inherited from a property on a
          containing control object</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p><code>inherit</code> is typically used to enforce hierarchical numbering within control
          objects. When given in a <code>value</code> in a declaration, <code>inherit</code>
          indicates that the value of a property, or a segment of its value, must be the same as a
          property (<code>prop</code>) higher in the containment hierarchy of a control object. That
          is, if a property with <code>@class='number'</code> is constrained with
            <code>value/inherit</code>, it must be the same as is assigned on the closest ancestor
          (feature, subcontrol, control or group) with the given property.</p>
        <p>Usually, <code>inherit</code> is used in conjunction with <code>autonum</code> (qv).
          Using the two elements in combination, for example, the number (property) assigned to a
          subcontrol appearing inside a control numbered <q>A1</q> may be constrained to be
            <q>A1-a</q>, <q>A1-b</q> etc., depending on the position of the subcontrol within the
          control.</p>
        <p>If a value must inherit from a property of a different class from the containing control
          object, <code>inherit/@from</code> can be used to indicate the applicable property (by its
          class). By default, <code>inherit</code> indicates a property value should match an
          ancestor's property with the same <code>@class</code> (the most usual case).</p>
      </part>
    </control>
  </group>
  <group>
    <title>Structural elements</title>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">section</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Division</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>A chapter, section or subsection partitioning a catalog, collection or section
          therein</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>Echoes HTML5 <code>section</code>.</p>
        <p>Like groups, sections (<code>section</code>)</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">group</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Group</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Related controls or groups (of controls or groups)</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>In addition to controls or groups, groups may be titled and may have their own
          properties, statements, parameter settings and references, subject to declaration. In this
          respect they are like control objects (control, subcontrol and feature), albeit their
          properties apply to the entire group – and must be acquired in processing via
          inheritance.</p>
        <p>Unlike sections (<code>section</code> elements), groups may not contain arbitrary prose
          (paragraphs and lists). They may however contain statements (stmt), which may be untyped
          (no @class) and therefore unconstrained by declarations.</p>
      </part>
      
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">title</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Title</prop>
      <part class="description"/>
      
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">references</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">References</prop>
      <part class="description"/>
      
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">ref</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Reference</prop>
      <part class="description"/>
      
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">std</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Standard</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Citation of a formal published standard</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>Echoes the NISO JATS (and NISO STS) <code>std</code> element</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">citation</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Citation</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Citation of a resource</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>Echoes the NISO JATS (and NISO STS) <code>mixed-citation</code> element.</p>
        <p>For references to standards, <code>std</code> (qv) may be preferred.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
  </group>
  <group>
    <title>Prose</title>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">p</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Paragraph</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Or paragraph fragment</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>This element echoes HTML <code>p</code>; like its forebear, it is not limited to
          indicating complete or discrete (compositional or logical) paragraphs, but can be used for
          any text set off on its own line.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">pre</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Preformatted text</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Retains whitespace in display</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>Echoes HTML <code>pre</code>.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">ol</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Ordered List</prop>
      <part class="description"/>
      
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">li</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">List item</prop>
      <part class="description"/>
      
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">ul</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Unordered list</prop>
      <part class="description"/>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>As in HTML, <q>unordered</q> does not indicate that the order of contained list items is
          not respected, only that they are not displayed with any notation indicating their order:
          that is, bullets, not numbers.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">em</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Emphasis</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Rhetorical emphasis as indicated typically by a font shift</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>In display, this element can be expected to <q>toggle</q>, i.e. provide for italics when
          appearing within roman text, but roman when appearing within italic text.</p>
        <p>Particular semantics (indicating types of emphasis for finer resolution in display or
          retrieval) may be provided via <code>@class</code>.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">i</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Italics</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Typographical shift to italics</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>An implementation may toggle, i.e. display contents using a roman face when the
          surrounding text is already italic.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">b</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Bold</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Typographical shift to bold</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>In display, when surrounding text is already bold, an implementation may indicate
            <q>bold</q> by means of double-bold or some other typographical distinction.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">a</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Anchor</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>An HTML-style anchor (inline linking element)</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>As in HTML, the link target is indicated by <code>@href</code>, with a '#' prefix for an
          internal cross-reference matching an <code>@id</code> elsewhere in the document.</p>
        <p>Anchors without <code>@href</code> are not invalid to the OSCAL schema (base validation),
          but may be reported by a Schematron. In use, an application may promote the contents of a
            <code>a</code> element, when a valid URI, to serve as the link target, if
            <code>@href</code> is missing or not a URI.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">q</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Quoted text</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>An inline segment to appear within quotation marks</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>For practical purposes, this is a cosmetic element with no special semantics other than
          to provide quotation marks in display.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">code</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Code</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Inline code</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>Strictly, this element should identify formal code or code fragments.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">sup</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Superscript</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Superscripted text</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">sub</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Subscript</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Subscripted text</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>Strictly, this element should identify formal code or code fragments.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
    <control class="element-description">
      <prop class="tag">span</prop>
      <prop class="full_name">Span</prop>
      <part class="description">
        <p>Generic inline container</p>
      </part>
      <part class="remarks">
        <p>As in HTML, an escape hatch for arbitrary (inline) semantic (or other) tagging.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
  </group>
  <group>
    <title>Structural constraints</title>
    <part>
      <p>Over and above what is validable with a grammar (in Level 0), there is a small set of
        constraints governing usage. Validations enforcing them can be implemented via Schematron or
        another process capable of static analysis of the data.</p>
    </part>
    <control class="general-constraint">
      <title>Within a control, properties, statements and parameters may occur in any order.</title>
      <part class="description">
        <p>This specification does not govern how or whether an implementation may respect the order
          of properties and statements given within a control type. Among properties, statements and
          parameters (that is, named things) within a control, cardinality constraints (where
          enforced) can help ensure a canonical order. An order may be imposed locally (for example,
          by a schema that requires all properties to appear before all statements), but this is for
          its convenience not because an order is mandated.</p>
      </part>
    </control>
  </group>
  <section>
    <title>Customization layers</title>
    <p>Like many tag languages and machine-readable syntaxes, OSCAL is intended to be extended and
      customized. Unlike most other formats, however, OSCAL's extension mechanism includes a set of
      features, supported natively in the language, for extension by the simplest possible
      mechanism, without requiring modification of any schemas, using a simple, native set of
      declarations for controls.</p>
    <p>OSCAL's validation model consists of several layers. At base is schema validation, which
      ensures that all tags in use are recognized as OSCAL tagging and that their arrangement in the
      document (with regard to both structure, and certain <q>semantic</q> relations) is consistent
      with regular usage of OSCAL. In a second layer, other relationships can be tested and rules
      enforced, over and above what a schema imposes. Implemented in Schematron or any technology
      with analogous capabilities, such as second layer is more flexible and configurable than the
      base layer.</p>
    <p>In a third layer, an OSCAL document is validated to constraints it declares for itself, that
      is locally in its own declarations. (Call this a <q>consistency check</q> rather than
      validation, for clarity.) Such a validation may be useful to an OSCAL implementation, which
      can take advantage of contracts implicit in such validation to provide functionalities; OSCAL
      itself does not provide such functionality, but only the hooks – and the mechanism by which
      users and developers can easily create and manage new control types.</p>
  </section>
</catalog>