<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>OSCAL Stakeholders on OSCAL</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/stakeholders/</link><description>Recent content in OSCAL Stakeholders on OSCAL</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2019 17:41:35 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/stakeholders/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>For Assessors</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/stakeholders/assessors/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 20:12:36 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/stakeholders/assessors/</guid><description>Audit and assessment personnel who validate the accuracy of security plans and assess the implementation of security controls within information systems. OSCAL standardizes the format for documentation of security controls, while establishing a framework for the automated assessment of information systems to be evaluated based the state of the security controls being addressed.
How Does OSCAL Help Me? Reduces the amount of manual labor need to assess the implementation of controls.</description></item><item><title>For Baseline Authors</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/stakeholders/contentcreators/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 20:12:36 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/stakeholders/contentcreators/</guid><description>Systems security policy professionals who set requirements for security programs, both across and within organizations and agencies OSCAL provides a standardized solution for building security baselines, through the use of OSCAL profiles, that set the expectations for control implementation within one or more programs and associated information systems.
How Does OSCAL Help Me? Ensures consistency of control implementation across the enterprise. Improves the transparency of policy implementation by automating reviews of security control implementation and assessments.</description></item><item><title>For Security Professionals</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/stakeholders/securitypros/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 20:12:36 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/stakeholders/securitypros/</guid><description>Security professionals who document or implement security controls within information systems. OSCAL provides a standardized format for documenting security and privacy controls that maps across multiple compliance frameworks (i.e. NIST, PCI, etc.) and a method for attesting to the implementation of the controls within information systems
How Does OSCAL Help Me? Enables continuous maintenance of control documentation within a framework designed for that purpose. Reduces the amount of paperwork required to implement multiple compliance frameworks.</description></item><item><title>For Tool Developers</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/stakeholders/tooldevelopers/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 20:12:36 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/stakeholders/tooldevelopers/</guid><description>Tool developers who build security compliance systems (Electronic Governance Risk and Compliance [eGRC] systems), or who provide secure infrastructure/software solutions to the Federal Government or to highly regulated industries OSCAL provides standardized formats for consuming control, catalog, profile, and implementation information to visualize and automate security compliance processes. OSCAL provides a standardized means for the automated assessment of infrastructure and software solutions to verify the ongoing effectiveness of the system's security control implementation.</description></item></channel></rss>