<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<catalog xmlns="http://oscal.nist.gov/schema/core"
    xmlns:xh11d="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/datatypes/"
    xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"    
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xHIPAA="http://oscal.nist.gov/schema/extension-catalog-HIPAA"
    xsi:schemaLocation="
        http://oscal.nist.gov/schema/core file://../xsd/OSCAL-core.xsd
        http://oscal.nist.gov/schema/extension-catalog-HIPAA file://../xsd/OSCAL-extension-HIPAA.xsd">
    <id>HIPAA</id>
    <name>HIPAA Rev 1</name>
    <version>1</version>
    <summary>HIPAA security controls derived from NIST SP 800-66, rev 1</summary>
    <items>
        <item>
            <type>control</type>
            <id>164.308(a)(8)</id>
            <title>Evaluation</title>
            <statement>
                <description>HIPAA Standard: Perform a periodic technical and nontechnical evaluation, based initially upon the standards implemented under this rule and subsequently, in response to environmental or operational changes affecting the security of electronic protected health information, which establishes the extent to which an entity’s security policies and procedures meet the requirements of this subpart.
                </description>
            </statement> 
            <!-- <link>parent</link>  -->
            
            <!-- crosswalk map to NIST documents here -->           
            <link rel="reference" xml:lang="en-US" href="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#800-12">NIST Special Publication 800-12</link>
            <link rel="reference" xml:lang="en-US" href="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#800-14">NIST Special Publication 800-14</link>
            <link rel="reference" xml:lang="en-US" href="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#800-37">NIST Special Publication 800-37</link>
            <link rel="reference" xml:lang="en-US" href="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#800-42">NIST Special Publication 800-42</link>
            <link rel="reference" xml:lang="en-US" href="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#800-53A">NIST Special Publication 800-53A</link>
            <link rel="reference" xml:lang="en-US" href="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#800-55">NIST Special Publication 800-55</link>
            <link rel="reference" xml:lang="en-US" href="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#800-84">NIST Special Publication 800-84</link>
            <link rel="reference" xml:lang="en-US" href="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#800-115">NIST Special Publication 800-115</link>
           
            <!-- map HIPAA controls to NIST controls here -->
            <link rel="map-to" href="nist800-53#CA-1"/>
            <link rel="map-to" href="nist800-53#CA-2"/>
            <link rel="map-to" href="nist800-53#CA-4"/>
            <link rel="map-to" href="nist800-53#CA-6"/>
            <link rel="map-to" href="nist800-53#CA-7"/>
                        
            <properties>
                <!--
                #########
                Reference external schema for extension properties only available for the HIPAA catalog
                #########
                -->
                <!-- The following will be validated -->
                <xHIPAA:security-rule-standard>
					Evaluation: Perform a periodic technical and nontechnical evaluation, based initially upon the standards implemented under this rule and subsequently, in response to environmental or operational changes affecting the security of electronic protected health information that establishes the extent to which an entity’s security policies and procedures meet the requirements of this subpart.
				</xHIPAA:security-rule-standard>
				<xHIPAA:implementation-specification></xHIPAA:implementation-specification>
                <xHIPAA:footnote>
                Note: See also Section 4.10, HIPAA Standard: Facility Access Controls and Section 4.14, HIPAA Standard: Access Controls.
                </xHIPAA:footnote>   
                <xHIPAA:key-activity>
                	<xHIPAA:number>1</xHIPAA:number>
                	<xHIPAA:key-activity-overview>Determine Whether Internal or External Evaluation Is Most Appropriate</xHIPAA:key-activity-overview>
                	<xHIPAA:description>
                	• Decide whether the evaluation will be conducted with internal staff resources or external consultants.
                	• Engage external expertise to assist the internal evaluation team where additional skills and expertise is determined to be reasonable and appropriate.
                	• Use internal resources to supplement an external source of help, because these internal resources can provide the best institutional knowledge and history of internal policies and practices.
                	</xHIPAA:description>
                	<xHIPAA:sample-questions>
					• Which staff has the technical experience and expertise to evaluate the systems?
					• How much training will staff need on security-related technical and nontechnical issues?
					• If an outside vendor is used, what factors should be considered when selecting the vendor, such as credentials and experience?
					• What is the budget for internal resources to assist with an evaluation?
					• What is the budget for external services to assist with an evaluation?
					</xHIPAA:sample-questions>
					<xHIPAA:footnote>Organizations may wish to review and employ, where reasonable and appropriate, security control assessment procedures found in NIST SP 800-53A, Guide for Assessing the
Security Controls in Federal Information Systems.</xHIPAA:footnote>
                </xHIPAA:key-activity>
                <xHIPAA:key-activity>
                	<xHIPAA:number>2</xHIPAA:number>
                	<xHIPAA:key-activity-overview>Develop Standards and Measurements for Reviewing All Standards and Implementation Specifications of the Security Rule
                	</xHIPAA:key-activity-overview>
                	<xHIPAA:description>
                	• Use an evaluation strategy and tool that considers all elements of the HIPAA Security Rule and can be tracked, such as a questionnaire or checklist.
                	• Implement tools that can provide reports on the level of compliance, integration, or maturity of a particular security safeguard deployed to protect EPHI.
                	• If available, consider engaging corporate, legal, or regulatory compliance staff when conducting the analysis.
                	• Leverage any existing reports or documentation that may already be prepared by the organization addressing compliance, integration, or maturity of a particular security safeguard deployed to protect EPHI.
                	</xHIPAA:description>
                	<xHIPAA:sample-questions>
                	• Have management, operational, and technical issues been considered?
                	• Do the elements of each evaluation procedure (questions, statements, or other components) address individual, measurable security safeguards for EPHI?
                	• Has the organization determined that the procedure must be tested in a few areas or systems?
					</xHIPAA:sample-questions>
                </xHIPAA:key-activity>
            </properties>
        </item>
   
        <!-- add the rest of the HIPAA controls...-->
    </items>
</catalog>