<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>General Topics on OSCAL</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/</link><description>Recent content in General Topics on OSCAL</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Creating and Using Metadata</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/metadata/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/metadata/</guid><description>This tutorial provides a walkthrough for creating the metadata section of an OSCAL document, which appears in all OSCAL documents.
Before reading this tutorial you should:
Have some familiarity with the XML, JSON, or YAML formats. Have a basic understanding of the OSCAL models and their overall structure. Document metadata in OSCAL appears in two locations:
The document's universally unique identifier (UUID). The document's metadata section. This tutorial explores both of these topics.</description></item><item><title>Extending OSCAL Models</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/extension/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/extension/</guid><description>This tutorial describes the mechanisms for extending basic OSCAL models. Before reading this tutorial, you should:
Have some familiarity with the XML, JSON, or YAML formats. Review the OSCAL Layers and Models documentation. Review the latest OSCAL Reference. What are the OSCAL Extension Mechanisms? OSCAL is designed with the goal of simultaneously supporting multiple cybersecurity frameworks. The core OSCAL syntax achieves this goal by focusing on properties that are universal or have applicability across various frameworks.</description></item></channel></rss>