<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>OSCAL General Tutorials on OSCAL</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/</link><description>Recent content in OSCAL General Tutorials on OSCAL</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2022 15:55:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Creating and Using Metadata</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/metadata/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2022 15:55:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/metadata/</guid><description>This tutorial provides a walkthrough for creating the metadata section of an OSCAL document, which appears in all OSCAL documents.
Before reading this tutorial you should:
Have some familiarity with the XML, JSON, or YAML formats. Have a basic understanding of the OSCAL models and their overall structure. Document metadata in OSCAL appears in two locations:
The document's universally unique identifier (UUID). The document's metadata section. This tutorial explores both of these topics.</description></item><item><title>Extending OSCAL Models</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/extension/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2022 15:55:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/extension/</guid><description>This tutorial describes the mechanisms for extending basic OSCAL models. Before reading this tutorial, you should:
Have some familiarity with the XML, JSON, or YAML formats. Review the OSCAL Layers and Models documentation. Review the latest OSCAL Reference. What are the OSCAL Extension Mechanisms? OSCAL is designed with the goal of simultaneously supporting multiple cybersecurity frameworks. The core OSCAL syntax achieves this goal by focusing on properties that are universal or have applicability across various frameworks.</description></item><item><title>Testing New Releases</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/releases/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2023 13:03:08 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/learn/tutorials/general/releases/</guid><description>This tutorial provides common ways community members can test a new release.
Before reading this tutorial, you should have a basic familiarity with:
The OSCAL models and their overall structure. XML, JSON, or YAML formats. The basics of version control with Git and GitHub. The OSCAL release model OSCAL releases roughly follow a semantic versioning convention of MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH (for more details, see the document detailing OSCAL's branch and version structure).</description></item></channel></rss>