<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>More about OSCAL on OSCAL</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/</link><description>Recent content in More about OSCAL on OSCAL</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Challenges Addressed by OSCAL</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/challenges/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/challenges/</guid><description>OSCAL addresses a number of challenges around security controls and security control assessment.
Control Information Lacks Standardization The core challenge, and one of the primary reasons for creating OSCAL, is that concepts like security controls and profiles are represented today largely in proprietary ways. In many cases they are written in prose documents that are imprecise, lead to differences in interpretation, and are not machine-readable; meaning that the prose instructions require someone to manually implement the control in information systems in order for the tool to use the information.</description></item><item><title>Project Goals and Design Principles</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/goals/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/goals/</guid><description>Goals of the OSCAL Project The OSCAL project is working to address the following goals:
Decrease Paperwork Drive a large decrease in the paperwork burden for both information security professionals and vendors.
Normalize the representation of security control catalogs, regulatory frameworks, and system information using precise, machine readable formats. Allow the sharing of control implementation information across communities. Improve System Security Assessments Improve the efficiency, accuracy, and consistency of system security assessments.</description></item><item><title>News</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/news/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/about/news/</guid><description>OSCAL 1.0.0 Release Candidate 2 (RC2) Released - April 12, 2021 OSCAL 1.0.0 Release Candidate 1 (RC1) Released - December 21, 2020 NIST ready to test approach to make FedRAMP faster, less burdensome - October 8, 2020 OSCAL 1.0.0 Milestone 3 Released - June 3, 2020 OSCAL 1.0.0 Milestone 2 Released - October 1, 2019 OSCAL 1.0.0 Milestone 1 Released - June 15, 2019 What's Next for FedRAMP? Automation, new authorizations later this year - June 25, 2018 FedRAMP Looks to NIST for Security Control Refinements - June 14, 2018 Automating Compliance for Highly Regulated Industries with Docker Enterprise Edition and OSCAL - May 3, 2018 You're Nuts!</description></item></channel></rss>