<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Model Development Snapshot Reference on OSCAL</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/</link><description>Recent content in Model Development Snapshot Reference on OSCAL</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>OSCAL Complete Development Snapshot JSON Format Outline</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/json-outline/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/json-outline/</guid><description>The following outline is a representation of the JSON format for the combination of all OSCAL models. For each property, the name links to the corresponding entry in the JSON Format Reference. The cardinality and data type are also provided for each property where appropriate.
catalog [1]: {… }, uuid [1]: uuid,
metadata [1]: {… }, title [1]: markup-line,
published [0 or 1]: dateTime-with-timezone,
last-modified [1]: dateTime-with-timezone,</description></item><item><title>OSCAL Complete Development Snapshot JSON Format Reference</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/json-reference/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/json-reference/</guid><description>The following is the JSON format reference for the combination of all OSCAL models, which is organized hierarchically. Each entry represents the corresponding JSON property in the model's JSON format, and provides details about the semantics and use of the property. The JSON Format Outline provides a streamlined, hierarchical representation of this model's JSON format which can be used along with this reference to better understand the JSON representation of this model.</description></item><item><title>OSCAL Complete Development Snapshot JSON Format Index</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/json-index/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/json-index/</guid><description>The following is an index of each JSON property used in the JSON format, which represents the combination of all OSCAL models. Each entry in the index lists all uses of the given property in the format, which is linked to the corresponding entry in the JSON Format Reference. Each entry also lists the formal name for the definition which is linked to the corresponding JSON definition in the JSON Format Metaschema Reference.</description></item><item><title>OSCAL Complete Development Snapshot JSON Format Metaschema Reference</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/json-definitions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/json-definitions/</guid><description>The following is a reference for the JSON object definitions derived from this model's metaschema, which imports the metaschemas for all of the OSCAL models.
Short name oscal-complete
JSON Base URI http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0
Remarks This format represents a combination of all of the OSCAL models.
action assemblySwitch to XML Action
description An action applied by a role within a given party to the content.
Constraints (4) index has key for responsible-partythis value must correspond to a listing in the index index-metadata-role-id using a key constructed of key field(s) @role-id</description></item><item><title>OSCAL Complete Development Snapshot XML Format Outline</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/xml-outline/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/xml-outline/</guid><description>The following outline is a representation of the XML format for the combination of all OSCAL models. For each element or attribute, the name links to the corresponding entry in the XML Format Reference. The cardinality and data type are also provided for each element or attribute where appropriate.
&amp;lt;catalog uuid="uuid"&amp;gt;… &amp;lt;/catalog&amp;gt;[1] &amp;lt;metadata&amp;gt;… &amp;lt;/metadata&amp;gt;[1] &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;markup-line&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;[1] a markup-line value
Text and inline markup including &amp;lt;insert&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;code&amp;gt;. &amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;published&amp;gt;datetime-with-timezone&amp;lt;/published&amp;gt;[0 or 1] a datetime-with-timezone value</description></item><item><title>OSCAL Complete Development Snapshot XML Format Reference</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/xml-reference/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/xml-reference/</guid><description>The following is the XML format reference for the combination of all OSCAL models, which is organized hierarchically. Each entry represents the corresponding XML element or attribute in the model's XML format, and provides details about the semantics and use of the element or attribute. The XML Format Outline provides a streamlined, hierarchical representation of this model's XML format which can be used along with this reference to better understand the XML representation of this model.</description></item><item><title>OSCAL Complete Development Snapshot XML Format Index</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/xml-index/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/xml-index/</guid><description>The following is an index of each XML element and attribute used in the XML format for this model. Each entry in the index lists all uses of the given element or attribute in the format, which is linked to the corresponding entry in the XML Format Reference. Each entry also lists the formal name for the given element or attribute which is linked to the corresponding XML type in the XML Format Metaschema Reference.</description></item><item><title>OSCAL Complete Development Snapshot XML Format Metaschema Reference</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/xml-definitions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/reference/develop/complete/xml-definitions/</guid><description>The following is a reference for the XML element and attribute types derived from this model's metaschema.
Short name oscal-complete
XML namespace http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0
Remarks This format represents a combination of all of the OSCAL models.
action assemblySwitch to JSON Action
description An action applied by a role within a given party to the content.
Constraints (4) index has key for responsible-partythis value must correspond to a listing in the index index-metadata-role-id using a key constructed of key field(s) @role-id</description></item></channel></rss>