<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="specml.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!--<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="specml-html-xslt1.xsl"?>-->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="specml.css"?>
<?xml-model href="spec-checkup.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<SPECIFICATION xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/specml">
  <head>Profile Resolution</head>
  <p>These specifications describe how to render an OSCAL profile document in
    the form of an OSCAL catalog. We call this <term>profile resolution</term>.</p>
  <section id="top">
    <head>Reading these specifications</head>
    <section id="terminology">
      <head>Terminology</head>
      <p>These DRAFT specifications take the form of a tag set mapping between the OSCAL
          <term>profile</term> and OSCAL <term>catalog</term> XML document models. The same mapping
        (transformation from source to target) can be effected using other expressions of the OSCAL
        model such as JSON or YAML object serializations. In these specifications, XML terminology
        is used, with reference to XML constructs such as <q>element</q> and <q>attribute</q>, with
        examples given using XML syntax: these however are for illustrative purposes only and
        normative only with respect to the semantic mapping, not the syntax as such. The XML
        orientation of the specification of this mapping is an expediency; in the longer term we
        plan specifications that are format-agnostic.<revisit> Let us know if you have an interest
          in helping to recast the specs / metaschema terminology?</revisit></p>
      <p>In these specifications there are references to <term>source</term>, <term>target</term>
        and <term>result</term>. <term>Source</term> refers sometimes to profile documents as a type
        (abstractly), and sometimes to instance profiles in operation, or elements within profiles
        (particular kinds of sources). <term>Target</term> refers to the intended output of the
        transformation, that is the catalog model generally (as a document type) or, for particular
        source instances or elements, particular targets.</p>
      <p>Elements in the source format are marked in these specifications to appear distinctively as
          <src>source-element</src> (for an element named <q>source-element</q>).</p>
      <p>Elements in the target format are marked in these specifications to appear distinctively as
          <tgt>target-element</tgt> (for an element named <q>target-element</q>).</p>
      <p>The term <term>result</term> refers to the actual results of transformation, as opposed to
        the intended or expected results. Conformance to these specifications requires that a
        processor's result corresponds to the target as described here, given a particular
        source.</p>
      <p>The term <term>directive</term> is used in these specifications to refer to an element or
        combination of elements in source data, which is designed to effect a particular outcome in
        the target catalog. For the most part, directives are in the source profile document – for
        example, a <src>set</src> element in a profile is a directive to set a parameter value in
        the target catalog.</p>
      <p>In contrast to profiles, catalogs do not contain directives but instead, representations of
        security controls and their parts, optionally gathered in groups, on which directives are
        assumed to operate. There is one exception: the <src>insert</src> element in control
        catalogs can be considered a directive that a parameter value be inserted into a particular
        location in running text (data content), when a catalog is rendered. Since these semantics
        respect catalog rendering, however, not profile resolution, they are out of scope for this
        document. For purposes of profile resolution, catalogs may be considered to be passive
        resources from which contents are replicated (copied): the operation of the profile, in
        contrast - its <q>OSCAL semantics</q> as opposed to the domain-specific semantics of the
        information it handles – requires that it express what is to be done and how.</p>
      <p><term>Original order</term> refers to the order of elements and objects as given in the
        source. <term>Canonical order</term> refers to the <q>correct</q> order of elements or
        objects as defined by an OSCAL format such as the catalog or profile models. That is, the
        respective schemas of these models enforce order to the extent it is meaningful; where it is
        not (for example, in the ordering of properties on objects in JSON), a metaschema can
        nevertheless be referenced to provide an order.</p>
      <p>So for example, on a JSON object, a <src>links</src> object and a <src>parts</src> object
        may be given as properties on an OSCAL <src>control</src> object. Each of these collects a
        sequence of one or more objects of the appropriate type (links or parts). As properties in
        JSON, these collections are not ordered with respect to one another. However, for the sake
        of a complete definition in another of OSCAL's operational contexts (namely XML), the OSCAL
        catalog model stipulates that all links come before all parts. This has two consequences.
        First, lossless conversion between formats is possible, even when one or both is defective
        in some respect (as in this case, JSON's object model does not capture the order of object
        properties): the metaschema can provide the difference, enabling a compliant OSCAL processor
        to know how deterministically to emit valid XML (with respect to ordering) even from a
        property set (intrinsically unordered) JSON source. Second, it ensures that the relative
        ordering of links to parts will never be significant in the data: while the order of links
        within <tgt>links</tgt> and the order of parts within <tgt>parts</tgt> may be significant
        and can hence be preserved across representations, the order <q>first links, then parts</q>,
        being defined by the model, becomes invariant across instances and thus insignificant.</p>
      <p>Canonical order is important since there are occasions when, in order to produce valid
        outputs in XML, a profile resolver must resequence items. This may happen any place where
        the natural or intrinsic order resulting from splicing sequences in original order is not
        correct.</p>
      <p>Finally, this specification describes not only (source) profiles and (target or result)
        catalogs, but <term>control selections</term> as well. The conceptual model of profile
        resolution takes a profile through several steps, in which controls are collected from
        source catalogs, combined, and potentially modified. As described by this specification,
        control selections are produced during this process, as temporary collections of controls in
        a transitional state. In the last phase of processing, the discrete selections are combined
        into the single catalog, the target.</p>
      <p>For illustrative purposes, these control selections are, like source and target formats,
        also represented by tagging in examples given here, and described as intermediate targets,
        even though no OSCAL processor is obliged to produce or recognize such XML at any point, as
        long as it produces the same results (final outputs) from the same inputs.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <head>RFC 2119 Keywords</head>
      <p><revisit>When complete, this specification will conform to IETF RFC 2119 in its use of
          keywords such as <q>must</q>
          <q>required</q> and <q>shall</q>. At present (time of writing) an editorial pass to ensure
          this consistency has <em>not</em> been conducted.</revisit></p>
    </section>
    <section id="use-of-xpath">
      <head>Use of XPath</head>
      <p>Additionally, in these specifications XPath notation is used to identify elements and
        attributes in the XML. A summary of some lightweight XPath syntax:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p><xpath>element</xpath> (unpunctuated) indicates an element named
            <xpath>element</xpath></p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p><xpath>@attribute</xpath> (punctuated <q>@</q>) indicates an attribute named
              <xpath>attribute</xpath></p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p><xpath>elem/@attr</xpath> indicates an attribute named <xpath>attr</xpath> on an
            element named <xpath>elem</xpath></p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p><xpath>elmn[@att='val']</xpath> indicates an element <xpath>elmn</xpath> that has an
            attribute <xpath>@att</xpath> with value <code>val</code>. </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="variable-content">
      <head>Variable contents in XML examples</head>
      <p>Examples given to illustrate targets for particular source (example) inputs are given, like
        the source, in XML notation. Sometimes, however, the expected outputs are not fully defined
        by the inputs given. In these cases, a description of the dynamic (variable) contents in
        curly braces <term>{ }</term>.</p>
      <p>So for example where a property is added to target <tgt>metadata</tgt>, an example could
        show</p>
      <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;last-modified><hi>{ timestamp }</hi>&lt;/last-modified></tagging>
      <p>This indicates the <tgt>last-modified</tgt> element should be produced with contents
        generated appropriately, namely with an actual time stamp in this case, and not the string
          <q>{ timestamp }</q>. In display, these values should also be shown with special
        formatting as shown here.</p>
      <p>Examples also indicate unspecified content using a simple <q> … </q> (elision) character,
        typically for more verbose chunks of target data whose production is specified elsewhere in
        the document.</p>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="operational-context">
    <head>Operational context</head>
    <section id="processing-context">
      <head>Processing context and scope</head>
      <p>A <term>profile</term> in OSCAL represents a selection and configuration of a set of
          <term>controls</term>. In the normal case, the set of controls available to a profile is
        provided by a catalog. For example, the three NIST SP 800-53 profiles representing the
        impact baselines HIGH, MODERATE and LOW: each of these calls on a catalog representing the
        families, controls and control enhancements described in SP 800-53/53A. In a data processing
        system, this dependency can be modeled in the form of separate documents or data instances -
        the (nominal) <q>catalog</q> and its <q>profile</q>, the latter being a selection,
        adaptation and organization of controls, as distinct from the catalog from which those
        controls are derived.</p>
      <p>However, profiles may also select controls from profiles, thus deriving them from
        underlying catalogs as modified by those profiles. This feature enables an organization that
        wishes to promulgate guidelines or requirements to do so by publishing a set of
        customizations to an existing catalog, rather than create a catalog from scratch. Profiles
        can also arrange combinations of controls from more than one catalog or profile origin,
        making it possible to use them to support the creation of hybrid catalogs. </p>
      <p>In the general case OSCAL must support sourcing more than one catalog at once, in order to
        aggregate and organize controls from disparate sources. For example, it should be routine
        for a profile to acquire its controls from an authoritative standard catalog, plus a local
        supplement.  But multiple catalog inputs, especially when they are produced and sourced
        independently of one another, may not combine without issues. In order to provide sensible
        and transparent results even for incoherent inputs, this specification defines these
        processes such that legible and testable results are produced even when they are formally
        invalid to constraints governing the outputs. Such downstream processing errors including
        validation errors are expected to be detectable and remediable. This especially applies to
        situations where multiple catalogs are sourced, or where the same catalog is sourced more
        than once, directly or indirectly.</p>
      <p>In order to support these semantics – because whatever data set is sourced by a profile, it
        must <q>look like a catalog</q> – the results of resolving a single profile must be in the
        form of a single catalog. Two different OSCAL processors that promise profile resolution,
        must deliver, for the same input, the same catalog with regard to its contents: which
        controls are included; their ordering (insofar as the target format represents ordering);
        and the structure (groups) in which they are embedded. This specification is designed to
        make this possible, by defining outputs with sufficient rigor that <q>the same</q> is
        meaningful and testable in this context.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="why-a-catalog">
      <head>Why resolve a profile as a catalog</head>
      <p>A profile is a representation of a delta, a <q>here to there</q>. As such, a profile might
        be conceived of as a recipe or instruction set – a sequence of steps or procedures – whereby
        to create an OSCAL catalog (set of controls describing security requirements) from an OSCAL
        catalog (set of controls describing security requirements). The primary use case for this is
        when we need to make a new catalog to apply to a system or set of systems, starting from a
        canonical, received, mandated or standard catalog with a more general scope.</p>
      <p>This is because although catalogs - for example, the controls described in NIST SP 800-53 -
        are published, available for use, and even standardized, they can never be used exactly in
        the form in which they are acquired. They must be taken from the packaging and placed into
        operational context before they mean anything. This typically requires that a few operations
        over <q>raw catalogs</q> be supported by a profiling mechanism. We must be able to select
        controls; we must be able to arrange them in order (or not); and we must be able to qualify
        or condition them by setting parameters defined for them and making adjustments to them. </p>
      <p>By representing the steps by which a base catalog can be sliced, sifted, amended and
        edited, into a (nominally) finished or ready set of control requirements, a profile makes it
        easier to codify and preserve even very incidental or temporary local revisions of a control
        catalog. Once expressed as a profile in OSCAL format, a set of emendations to a catalog can
        be managed entirely separately and independently from the catalog. Because a conformant
        processor can always create the customized catalog by resolving the profile against its
        sources (executing the transformation described in this document), the profile can also be
        examined and used as a proxy for that catalog for other purposes. The customized catalog can
        be made available wherever and for whatever purposes it is needed, while its revision and
        maintenance can be focused on the profile.</p>
      <p>This separation of concerns - between the originating catalog authors, who describe policy
        in only general terms, and the authors of the <q>user manual</q> catalog, who must describe
        policy in very particular and local terms - is a necessary factor in supporting sustainable
        processes with the potential for automation and process improvement. An OSCAL profile
        bridges the gap between a set of general guidelines, and actionable rules. Only by examining
        the system in the context of the actual intentions appropriate to that system, can we
        properly assess its security. Profiles make this possible.</p>
      <p>In order for this to work however we need a process that can perform the necessary
        operations, to apply the delta to an unmodified catalog, to produce the local view of the
        catalog as modified. This is profile resolution.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="valid-endpoints">
      <head>Formal validation of source and result</head>
      <p>In an XML context, document validation is available as a means of determining whether an
        arbitrary XML document entity conforms to structural and naming constraints such as must be
        assumed by processors respecting application semantics. These specifications assume that XML
        inputs for profile resolution will be <em>schema-valid</em> with respect to the OSCAL
          <term>profile</term> model, and hence will be tagged in the namespace
          <code>http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0</code>.</p>
      <p>Similarly, the definition of the output format or results, is constrained by the OSCAL
          <term>catalog</term> model as defined by its schema.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <head>Order of objects in serialization</head>
      <p>As described above, <term>original order</term> refers to the order of elements and objects
        as given in the source, whereas <term>canonical order</term> refers to the <q>correct</q>
        order of elements or objects as defined by an OSCAL format such as the catalog or profile
        models. That is, the respective schemas of these models enforce order to the extent it is
        meaningful; where it is not (for example, in the ordering of properties on objects in JSON),
        a metaschema can nevertheless be referenced to restore an order.</p>
      <p>So for example, on a JSON object, a <src>links</src> object and a <src>parts</src> object
        may be given as properties on a <src>control</src> object. As properties, they are not
        ordered with respect to one another. However, for the sake of a complete definition in
        another of OSCAL's operational contexts (namely XML), the catalog model stipulates that all
        links come before all parts: in an XML representation, <tgt>link</tgt> elements come before
          <tgt>part</tgt> elements. This restriction ensures that the relative ordering of links to
        parts will never be significant in the data: while the order of links within
          <tgt>links</tgt> and the order of parts within <tgt>parts</tgt> may be significant and can
        hence be preserved across representations, the order <q>first links, then parts</q> is
        defined by the model, with the consequence that it can be represented as such even when an
        underlying representation (such as a compiled JSON object) does not encode that relationship
        natively.</p>
      <p>There are occasions especially when control contents are altered or amended, when a
        straightforward representation of elements in their original order, or in two sequences
        spliced together (say, the parts of a control, followed by new properties for the same
        control, added by the profile), would be invalid, which is to say not conformant with
        canonical order. In general the rule in these cases is, in resolution, to reorder the
        elements. <revisit>Example</revisit></p>
      <p>For any given element (defined as an assembly in the metaschema), the canonical order is
        given by its model. So for example the canonical order for contents of a catalog is
          <tgt>metadata</tgt>, <tgt>param</tgt>, <tgt>control</tgt>, <tgt>group</tgt>,
          <tgt>back-matter</tgt>. Within this sequence, members may be missing, as for example not
        all catalogs will have parameters or groups. Any members that are present, however, must be
        given in this order.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="id-uniqueness">
      <head>ID uniqueness constraint</head>
      <p>In addition to those described and enforced by the respective schemas, there are additional
        constraints over the data that this process relies on. The most important of these is
        ID-distinctiveness. Every <src>id</src> flag (in XML, represented by <xpath>@id</xpath>
        attributes) on an element in the model, whether it be attached to a control, group or an
        element within a control, must be distinct and unique, within the defined processing scope,
        inasmuch as this value will be used in processing as a proxy for <term>element
          identity</term> and especially (in the case of controls) for <term>control
        identity</term>. That is, it is on the basis of their IDs that controls are selected and
        referenced, and clashes are detected and recognized between competing representations of
        controls.</p>
      <p>In this context, <q>defined processing scope</q> includes a profile along with all profiles
        and all catalogs it imports, directly and indirectly. Many arrangements are possible in
        which a single catalog provides controls to more than a single branch on the import tree. In
        profiles where this occurs, distinct imports must identify discrete, non-intersecting, sets
        of controls, or clashes occur. Additionally, clashes may naturally occur through implicit
        copying of parameters from multiple imports.</p>
      <p>OSCAL profiles provide three different modes for handling clashing controls or replicas in
        general, where <term>replica</term> refers to any element represented more than once. Each
        of these modes is indicated by different directives given on <src>merge/@combine</src>,
        namely <q>keep</q> (also the default), <q>use-first</q> and <q>merge</q>.</p>
      <p><revisit>Because ID distinctiveness within the scope of processing, is critical, OSCAL
          users should take care that different catalogs have distinct sets of IDs. This applies to
          all structures within the catalogs, not only controls but also groups, parameters,
          citations and resources.</revisit></p>
    </section>
    <section id="control-identity">
      <head><propose>Defining control identity</propose></head>
      <p>A central problem in profile resolution is determining when two controls are both
        representations of <q>the same</q> control, even when those representations have dissimilar
        contents or come to a profile through different import pathways.</p>
      <p>For purposes of profile resolution, control identity (or parameter, group identity etc.)
        can be determined by any of several ways, depending on the <term>identity designation
          mode</term>:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>strict - control ID only - ordinary mode for well-controlled inputs</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>diagnostic - control ID + provenance identifier</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>maintenance - control ID + provenance + class (version etc)</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>none - no identification (each input control is distinct) - for tracing</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p><revisit>Dev team member suggests we provide a resolution/disambiguation/debugging mode that
          produces valid OSCAL by producing new IDs for everything, thereby disambiguating by brute
          force. This is not a bad idea. This proposal offers that feature as 'no identity
          designation', i.e. nothing is found to be identical with anything.</revisit></p>
    </section>
    <section id="detecting-issues">
      <head>Detecting issues in profiles</head>
      <p>It is frequently possible by static analysis to detect many conditions even in schema-valid
        profile documents, that will result in problematic catalogs in resolution. The most common
        issue will be clashing controls, that is more than one control in underlying catalogs with a
        given identifier (ID), making references to such controls ambiguous. The <term>identity
          designation mode</term> is intended to give profile developers some control over this
        handling, for purposes of development or diagnosis; but the quality of the results can only
        be guaranteed determinatively by the quality of the inputs, and full analysis in support of
        profile development and diagnostics – to produce correct inputs that accurately reflect the
        intent – is outside the scope of these specifications.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="comments-in-result">
      <head>Comments in result documents</head>
      <p>In an XML-based profile resolution, XML comments are one straightforward way for a
        processor to record events or conditions without affecting the output's nominal semantics.
        To support this, while two processors are obliged to return the same catalog XML for the
        same profile XML inputs, they are not required to match one another's comments, whitespace
        usage, attribute order, or processing instructions, only each other's elements, attributes
        and data content.</p>
      <p>One consequence of this is that processes intended to compare two profile resolutions may
        have to accommodate differences in comments, considering them as insignificant along with
        other differences in serialization.</p>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="target-structure">
    <head>Target catalog structure</head>
    <p>Inasmuch as the target of profile resolution is a catalog, the resulting document is expected
      to be a catalog document as specified by OSCAL, conforming to the applicable schema, XSD in
      the case of OSCAL XML or JSON Schema for OSCAL object serialization formats.</p>
    <p>These two approaches to validation do not constrain their respective data models – although
      OSCAL-equivalent – in exactly the same way. In particular, element structures in the XML may
      be represented in JSON by either objects, or arrays of objects, depending on the respective object's
      OSCAL definition; and where objects appear outside arrays, ordering semantics cannot be respected (whereas in XML, order among nodes is
      always an intrinsic property of the graph).</p>
    <p>Consequently, where these specifications dictate that targets appear in order, it must be
      understood that what is described is <em>both</em> (a) the order in XML, and (b) the
        <term>canonical order</term> in OSCAL, which while it is not exposed in a JSON object
      serialization, will always available to an OSCAL processor by reference to the appropriate
      metaschema (in this case, the Metaschema instance that defines the catalog model). <xref
        rid="terminology"/></p>
    <section id="form-of-result">
      <head>Form and organization of resolution target</head>
      <p>The output of a profile resolution should take the form of a catalog. Catalog results (the
        output of a conformant profile resolution) will be valid to the OSCAL catalog schema.</p>
      <p> At its base, an OSCAL <src>profile</src> source produces a <tgt>catalog</tgt>:</p>
      <mapping unit-test="base-test_profile.xml">
        <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile id="profile-identifier">...&lt;/profile></tagging>
        <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;catalog id="<hi>{ new-catalog-identifier }</hi>">
  &lt;metadata>[Required metadata, as described below]&lt;/metadata>
  <hi>{ controls or control groups, as described below }</hi>
  &lt;back-matter><hi>{ back matter as described below }</hi>&lt;/back-matter>
&lt;/catalog></tagging>
      </mapping>
      <p>A valid catalog must have <tgt>metadata</tgt> in addition to controls and control groups.
        Additionally it may have <tgt>back-matter</tgt>. How to produce and populate the
          <tgt>metadata</tgt> and <tgt>back-matter</tgt> is described below 
        <revisit>link me</revisit>, as is the construction
        of the <tgt>catalog/@id</tgt> in the target.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="validation-of-result">
      <head>Validation of resolution result</head>
      <p>Although the target of profile resolution takes the form of a catalog, it may not be valid
        to all constraints that define the OSCAL catalog format, whether enforced by its schema or
        by other means such as Schematron. Specifically, while a correctly implemented profile
        resolution may produce a result catalog that is structurally valid, there is a mode of
        operation, namely the <tgt>keep-all combination rule</tgt>, which can permit replication of
        controls or control contents, when the control imports are redundant or contain redundant
          <src>call</src> or <src>match</src> directives. Such replication can result in violations
        of ID uniqueness constraints, in particular. <xref rid="valid-endpoints"/></p>
      <p>If the merge behavior is set to <src>combine[@method='keep']</src>, or not given (as this
        setting is the default), a profile with multiple calls on controls will result in multiple
        copies of controls with clashing IDs. These should raise validation errors in the results,
        since IDs must be unique on elements in document scope. Accordingly, this is an appropriate
        combination rule to use in development when any potential collisions should be detected and
        removed; it is also an appropriate rule to apply when a profile has been tested and found to
        be free of any such collisions. Other combination rules (<src>method='use-first'</src> or
          <src>method='merge'</src>)  are provided for special exigencies or to permit certain kinds
        of optimization.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="top-level-id">
      <head>top-level @id</head>
      <p>Because document IDs are sometimes used to distinguish data points in processing context, a
        resolved profile may not present the same ID as any of the catalogs it is importing, or the
        same ID as its source profile.</p>
      <p>It is permitted to produce the profile’s ID in resolution via a static mapping from the ID
        of the source. For example, the resolution of profile with ID <code>profile-X</code> might
        have ID <code>profile-X-RESOLVED</code>.</p>
      <p><revisit>BR feels this is underspecified and I agree. He also thinks that resolutions
          should always have a (generated) unique IDs, since upstream catalogs can change between
          resolutions.</revisit></p>
    </section>
    <section id="metadata-in-result">
      <head>Instance metadata</head>
      <p>Metadata in the target is derived directly from the source metadata, with modifications.
        All elements inside <src>metadata</src> in the source profile are copied in their original
        order into the catalog. Additionally, new elements are introduced as described here.</p>
      <p>Because of options in producing metadata and especially the requirement for a timestamp,
        developers and users should note that two different resolutions of the same profile will
        not, ordinarily, be identical inside <tgt>metadata</tgt>.</p>
      <p><revisit>This has been worked, with changes suggested by DW, since BR's
        review</revisit></p>
      <section id="metadata-timestamp">
        <head>Metadata resolution timestamp</head>
        <mapping>
          <p>A <tgt>prop</tgt> element with <tgt>name</tgt>
            <q>resolution-timestamp</q> is added to the resolution target metadata with a valid
            timestamp indicating the time of the resolution runtime. Conforming with canonical order
            of <tgt>metadata</tgt> in the target, It must be placed into metadata structure after
            any <tgt>title</tgt>, <tgt>published</tgt>, <tgt>last-modified</tgt>,
            <tgt>version</tgt>, <tgt>oscal-version</tgt>, or <tgt>doc-id</tgt> elements, and before
            any <tgt>prop</tgt><tgt>, link</tgt>, <tgt>role</tgt>, <tgt>party</tgt>, or
              <tgt>responsible-party</tgt> elements. The target is schema valid, and the new
              <tgt>prop</tgt> is given before copies of <src>prop</src> elements already
            present.</p>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;metadata>
  &lt;title>Example Profile&lt;/title>
  &lt;last-modified>2019-06-30T10:54:16.372-05:00&lt;/last-modified>
  &lt;prop name="status">NEW&lt;/prop>
&lt;/metadata></tagging>
          <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;metadata>
  &lt;title>Example Profile&lt;/title>
  &lt;last-modified>2019-06-30T10:54:16.372-05:00&lt;/last-modified>
  &lt;prop name="resolution-timestamp"><hi>{ timestamp of profile resolution runtime }</hi>&lt;/last-modified>
  &lt;prop name="status">NEW&lt;/prop>
&lt;/metadata></tagging>
          <p>The presence of this property with a valid timestamp may be taken as an indicator that
            an OSCAL <src>catalog</src> has been produced by resolution of a <src>profile</src>.</p>
        </mapping>
        <p>Note that due to this provision, two different resolutions of the same profile produced
          at different times will not be bit-equivalent, since their timestamps will be
          different.</p>
        <p><revisit>Any provision for systems that cannot provide a valid timestamp?</revisit></p>
      </section>
      <section id="metadata-link">
        <head>Metadata link to source profile</head>
        <mapping>
          <p><revisit>Optionally</revisit>, a processor may add a link to the result<tgt>
              metadata</tgt>. Conforming with canonical order of <tgt>metadata</tgt> in the target,
            It must be placed into metadata structure after any <tgt>title</tgt>,
              <tgt>published</tgt>, <tgt>last-modified</tgt>, <tgt>version</tgt>,
              <tgt>oscal-version</tgt>, <tgt>doc-id</tgt> or <tgt>prop</tgt> elements, and before
              any<tgt> link</tgt>, <tgt>role</tgt>, <tgt>party</tgt>, or
              <tgt>responsible-party</tgt> elements. The target is schema valid, and the new
              <tgt>link</tgt> is given before copies of <src>link</src> elements already present</p>
          <p>The new link should have two flags (attributes):</p>
          <ul>
            <li>
              <p><tgt>@rel</tgt> has the value <q>resolution-source</q></p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p><tgt>@href</tgt> provides a URL or URI address for the source profile</p>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;metadata>
  &lt;title>Test profile&lt;/title>
  &lt;last-modified>2019-12-03T11:36:32.284-05:00&lt;/last-modified>
  &lt;version>1.0&lt;/version>
  &lt;oscal-version>1.0-MR2&lt;/oscal-version>
  &lt;party>
    &lt;org>
      &lt;org-name>Standing Committee&lt;/org-name>
    &lt;/org>
  &lt;/party>
&lt;/metadata></tagging>
          <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;metadata>
  &lt;title>Test profile - RESOLUTION RESULT&lt;/title>
  &lt;last-modified>2019-12-03T11:36:32.284-05:00&lt;/last-modified>
  &lt;version>1.0&lt;/version>
  &lt;oscal-version>1.0-MR2&lt;/oscal-version>
  &lt;prop name="resolution-timestamp"><hi>{ timestamp of profile resolution runtime }</hi>&lt;/last-modified>
  &lt;link rel="resolution-source" href="<hi>{ URI to resolution source data instance }</hi>">Test profile&lt;/link>
  &lt;party>
    &lt;org>
      &lt;org-name>Standing Committee&lt;/org-name>
    &lt;/org>
  &lt;/party>
&lt;/metadata></tagging>
        </mapping>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="body-of-result">
      <head>Body of the target</head>
      <p>The construction of the body of the target catalog is described in the next section. <xref rid="full-mapping"/></p>
      <p>The body of the target <tgt>catalog</tgt>, after its <term>metadata</term>, is structured
        as follows, depending on its merge directive. (Details on merging are given below <xref rid="merge-phase"/>.)</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>If no <src>merge</src> was given, or if <src>merge</src> is given without
              <src>custom</src> or <src>as-is</src>, controls are flat (unstructured) in the target
            catalog. This mode of processing is referred to as <q>no merge</q>. Note that the same
              <src>merge</src> element in the source is also the location for the combination
            directive, expressed as <src>merge/combine/@method</src>. The combination method and the
            merge rule are two distinct concepts in profile resolution; and any merge rule (<q>no
              merge</q>, <q>as is</q> or <q>custom</q>) can work with any combination method
              (<q>keep</q>, <q>use-first</q> or <q>merge</q>).</p>
          <p>Conforming with canonical order, the target catalog has a content model as follows
              <revisit>(DTD/RNC notatation)</revisit>: <code>(metadata, param*, control*,
              back-matter?)</code></p>
          <p><revisit>BR: note we have Issue #523 about permitting param to appear at the
              top.</revisit></p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>If <src>merge/as-is</src> is used, the structure of the target will reflect the
            structure(s) of the source catalog(s).</p>
          <p>Conforming with canonical order, the target catalog has the content model
              <code>(metadata, param*, control*, group*, back-matter?)</code> where
              <code>group</code> has the model <code>(title?, prop*, part*, param*, control*,
              group*)</code>.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>If <src>merge/custom</src> is used, see above. The content model of the target catalog
            is the same as that for <src>merge/as-is</src>.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Unless it be for special purposes in a debugging or tracing mode, profile results may not
        show any groups or structures in the form of elements not described here. Depending on the
        merge directive, all groups will be given either by the catalog source(s)
          (<src>merge/as-is</src>) or the profile (<src>merge/custom</src>), or there will be no
        groups at all (no merge directive).</p>
    </section>
    <section id="target-back-matter">
      <head>Back matter</head>
      <p>The back matter in target catalogs is assembled from the back matter of their source
        profiles in combination with the back matter of source catalogs. In both catalogs and
        profiles, <src>back-matter</src> is comprised of (multiple uses of either)
          <src>citation</src> or <src>resource</src>. Either of these elements may be
        cross-referenced from any location in their source documents by means of a URI fragment
        identifier on an <src>href</src> flag, for example <code>&lt;resource id="document-X</code>>
        may be referenced from inside its containing document by <code>&lt;link
          href="#document-X"></code> appearing elsewhere. Whether an element inside back matter must
        be included in the target, depends on whether such a cross-reference has also been included
        in the same target.</p>
      <p>Specifically, any <src>citation</src> or <src>resource</src> inside <src>back-matter</src>
        either in the profile, or in any imported catalog, is considered eligible for propagation
        into the target if either of two conditions obtains:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>The element (<src>citation</src> or <src>resource</src>) is referenced by any element
            inside the profile metadata.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The element is referenced from a link or anchor (<src>link</src> or <src>a</src>
            element) inside controls, parameters, or any contents (for example, paragraphs inside
              <tgt>group/part</tgt>) included in the resolved profile. The link takes the form of a
            URI fragment identifier <code>#id</code>, where <code>id</code> is the value of the
              <src>@id</src> attribute of the <src>citation</src> or <src>resource</src>.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>The assembly of the target <tgt>back-matter</tgt> occurs by including copies of all
        eligible <src>citation</src> elements followed by all eligible <src>resource</src> elements,
        in the same order as given in their sources.</p>
      <p>Additionally, combination rules (see next section) will affect whether and how duplicate or
        competing <src>citation</src> or <src>resource</src> elements are handled, to remove or
        combine multiple occurrences of the same referenced object.</p>
    </section>
  </section>
    <section id="full-mapping">
    <head>Phases of profile resolution</head>
    <p>Considered as a <q>document</q> or integrated data set (object), a profile has three
      sections, each of which corresponds to a conceptual step in resolution. To resolve a catalog
      fully is to perform all these steps.</p>
    <p>While the steps are described in this specification as occurring in sequence, a profile
      processor is not obliged to perform them in the order described. Conformance to these
      specifications is determined by whether the results of processing (<term>resolution</term>)
      appear as described, not on whether the means to produce those results work in exactly the
      manner described here.</p>
    <p>The three steps are <src>import</src> (control <term>selection</term>); <src>merge</src>; and
        <src>modify</src>. In brief:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p><src>import</src> identifies one or more control sources (catalogs or profiles) and the
          controls within them to be included in this (resolved) profile;</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><src>merge</src> designates the rules for how controls will be organized and merged (or
          not) in the result catalog;</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><src>modify</src> indicates how parameters in the underlying catalog may be modified or
          set, and how control contents may be amended or modified.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>The <term>selection</term> phase provides the basis for a customized catalog by designating
      controls to be included in it; a profile that designates no controls, produces no catalog. The
      selection phase is controlled by <src>profile/import</src> directives in the source
      profile.</p>
    <p>The <term>merge</term> phase addresses two questions: what a processor should produce in
      cases of (accidental or intentional) ambiguities in control identification in the selection
      phase; and how to structure the outputs, whether in a hierarchy (copied or created) or flat
      (without grouping). These two aspects of resolution are addressed by the <term>combination
        rule</term> (or <term>combination method</term>) and the <term>merge rule</term> (which
      includes a <q>no merge option</q>). In source data (a valid profile document), a
        <src>profile/merge</src> directive is optional; when it or its child directives are absent,
      default combination and merge rules apply.</p>
    <p>The <term>modification</term> phase is an opportunity for a profile to amend, alter or edit
      controls, and to set parameter values or constrain or qualify parameters as represented in the
      target. A profile can be valid and useful without making any modifications, only selections,
      so the <src>profile/modify</src> element (node) is optional in the profile model.</p>
    <p>As described in the previous section, when resolved, an OSCAL profile takes the form of an
      OSCAL catalog. The merge semantics described below will produce outputs conforming to this
      organization.</p>
    <section id="import-selections">
      <head>Selection phase </head>
      <p>A profile begins by importing catalogs, all of whose controls are made available. The
        catalogs it references may be available as static resources, or they may be produced
        dynamically on request; accordingly a profile may also import profiles, to be resolved as
        catalogs, instead of or in addition to catalogs as such. Imports are given in sequence after
        the metadata:</p>
      <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile>
  &lt;metadata><hi>{ Profile metadata }</hi>&lt;/metadata>
  &lt;import href="#catalog"><hi>{ … selection of controls … }</hi>&lt;/import>
  &lt;import href="#catalog-supplemental"><hi>{ … selection of controls … }</hi>&lt;/import>
&lt;/profile>
</tagging>
      <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;profile>
  &lt;metadata><hi>{ Profile metadata }</hi>&lt;/metadata>
  &lt;selection href="#catalog" catalog-id="<hi>{ catalog-identifier }</hi>"><hi>{ … selection of controls … }</hi>&lt;/selection>
  &lt;selection href="#catalog-supplemental" catalog-id="<hi>{ catalog-identifier }</hi>"><hi>{ … selection of controls … }</hi>&lt;/selection>
&lt;/profile>
</tagging>
      <p>The resource indicated can be either an OSCAL catalog or an OSCAL profile. A catalog
        provides controls in their native form. An imported profile is resolved on import, using the
        same rules for profile resolution, so a catalog is presented to the importing profile.</p>
      <p>(The result of importing other endpoints or resources besides valid OSCAL catalogs and
        profiles is not defined by this specification.)</p>
      <p>No profile may import itself either directly or indirectly. An import directive that
        indicates either the profile itself, or a profile into which it is being (currently)
        imported, must be ignored. Optionally, a processor may issue a warning.</p>
      <p>In an import directive, the reference to the resource to be imported appears on an
          <src>@href</src> flag. It takes either of two forms, external or internal:</p>
      <section id="import-via-uri">
        <head>External - import via URI</head>
        <p>An external reference appears as an absolute or relative URL</p>
        <p>Indicating a file available via <revisit>[prototol?]</revisit></p>
        <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;import href="../../nist.gov/SP800-53/rev4/xml/NIST_SP-800-53_rev4_catalog.xml">
  &lt;include>
    &lt;call control-id="ac-1"/>
  &lt;/include>
&lt;/import>
</tagging>
      </section>
      <section id="import-via-resource">
        <head>Internal - import via resource</head>
        <p>A catalog or profile to be imported can also be indicated using an internal link via a
          URI fragment identifier (starting with <code>#</code>). If an import href resolves to a
            <code>resource</code> elsewhere in the profile (typically in back matter), that resource
          can be retrieved to provide the source catalog.</p>
        <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;import href="#nist-sp800-53_catalog">
  &lt;include>
    &lt;call control-id="ac-1"/>
  &lt;/include>
&lt;/import>

  ...
  
&lt;back-matter>
  &lt;resource id="nist-sp800-53_catalog">
    &lt;desc>SP 800-53 catalog (OSCAL format) on Github&lt;/desc>
    &lt;rlink href="https://github.com/usnistgov/oscal-content/tree/master/nist.gov/SP800-53/rev4/xml/NIST_SP-800-53_rev4_catalog.xml"/>
  &lt;/resource>
&lt;/back-matter>
</tagging>
        <p>A reference from an import to a resource that does not reference a catalog or profile, or
          a cross-reference to something other than a resource, is inoperative for purposes of
          importing. It may be signaled as an error [or warning] by a processor. <revisit>Allow
            processors to import other stuff as they like?</revisit></p>
        
      </section>
      <section id="stateless-URIs">
        <head>Availability of documents returned by given URIs</head>
        <p>The rules of XSLT <code>document()</code> apply to the traversal of any URI: that is, it
          is assumed that all calls to a given (resolved) URI reference, will return the same
          result.</p>
        <p>If documents called for import are determined to be unavailable, the processor may drop
          them along with a warning, both or either out of band (e.g. through <code>STDERR</code>)
          or in the catalog results.</p>
        <p>URIs are used as a widely supported, global address with broad utility. A processor is
          not obliged, when requested for a resource, to use the given URI in an http request to
          produce it. Processors may offer fallback behaviors for URI requests that fail; conversely
          a processor may be able to avoid a URI request in favor of a better way to provide
          resources identified by URI.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <head>Missing imports</head>
        <p>An import that does not reference either an OSCAL catalog, or an OSCAL profile that can
          be resolved as a catalog, is dropped.</p>
        <mapping unit-test="profile-resolution-examples/broken_profile.xml">
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile id="broken_profile">
  &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
  &lt;import href="missing_profile.xml">
     &lt;include>
        &lt;call control-id="ac-1"/>
     &lt;/include>
  &lt;/import>
&lt;/profile>
</tagging>
          <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;profile id="home_profile_RESOLVED">
  &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
&lt;/profile>
</tagging>
          <p>Optionally, a processor may produce a comment indicating the lapse:</p>
          <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;profile id="home_profile_RESOLVED">
  &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
  &lt;!-- referenced resource 'missing_profile.xml' cannot be resolved -->
&lt;/profile>
</tagging>
        </mapping>
        <p>In this context, an OSCAL profile that makes direct or indirect reference (via its own
          imports) to the importing catalog, is also dropped as unavailable. See below under
            <q>Circular Imports</q>.</p>
      </section>
      <section id="circular-imports">
        <head>Circular imports</head>
        <p>When a profile imports a profile, the subordinate profile is resolved into a catalog
          using the same rules. This presents a possibility of circular imports, when a profile is
          directed to import itself either directly or indirectly.</p>
        <p>A <term>circular import</term> is defined as a directive to import a resource, which has
          already been called higher in the import hierarchy. For example, if Profile A imports
          Profile B, and Profile B imports Profile A, the second import is circular. (An import at
          the top can only be circular if a profile tries to import itself.) If A imports B, B
          imports C and C imports A, C’s import is circular.</p>
        <p>Note that an import can only be circular within the context of processing a particular
          profile. In the last example, C’s import would not be circular if invoked in the context
          of resolving B by itself (without being imported by A), or of resolving some other profile
          that did not import A. (D importing B importing C importing A would not be a problem.)</p>
        <p>Circular imports are inoperative, and may be reported as an error <revisit>or
            warning</revisit>.<revisit>BR wants this to be more draconian but I am not sure every
            situation warrants it. It seems like the same sort of thing as a missing import to me,
            except it's missing by definition.</revisit></p>
        <p>An import that is not circular (refers to a document not already imported) results in a
          control selection, subject to merging with other control selections in the merge
          phase.</p>
        <mapping unit-test="profile-resolution-examples/home_profile.xml">
          <p>A profile identified as <code>home_profile.xml</code> imports another one identified as
              <code>circular_profile.xml</code>:</p>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile id="home_profile">
  &lt;metadata>...&lt;/metadata>
  &lt;import href="circular_profile.xml">
     &lt;include>
        &lt;call control-id="ac-1"/>
     &lt;/include>
  &lt;/import>
&lt;/profile>
</tagging>
          <p>In turn this file invokes <code>home_profile.xml</code>:</p>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile id="circular_profile">
  &lt;metadata>...&lt;/metadata>
  &lt;import href="home_profile.xml">
     &lt;include>
        &lt;call control-id="ac-1"/>
     &lt;/include>
  &lt;/import>
&lt;/profile>
</tagging>
          <p>No control selection is produced for the circular import:</p>
          <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;profile id="home_profile_RESOLVED">
  &lt;metadata>...&lt;/metadata>
&lt;/profile>
</tagging>
          <p>Optionally, a processor may produce a comment indicating the lapse:</p>
          <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;profile id="home_profile_RESOLVED">
  &lt;metadata>...&lt;/metadata>
  &lt;!-- referenced resource 'home_profile.xml' cannot be resolved from resource 'circular_profile': circular dependency -->
&lt;/profile>
</tagging>
        </mapping>
      </section>
      <section>
        <head>Multiple imports</head>
        <p>In the selection phase, each import directive is processed to produce a set of controls
          and (when they are referenced) parameters. These controls and parameters are represented
          in the form of a control selection. Note that this occurs in the selection phase even if
          the same catalog (resource) is imported multiple times: each distinct import collects
          controls into a <tgt>selection</tgt>:</p>
        <mapping unit-test="profile-resolution-examples/import-twice_profile.xml">
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile id="import-twice_profile">
    &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
    &lt;import href="#catalog">
        &lt;include> … select controls …  &lt;/include>
    &lt;/import>
    &lt;import href="#catalog">
        &lt;include> … select controls …  &lt;/include>
    &lt;/import>
    &lt;back-matter> … &lt;/back-matter>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
          <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;profile id="import-twice_profile_RESOLVED">
  &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
  &lt;selection id="catalog-id"> … selected controls … &lt;/selection>
  &lt;selection id="catalog-id"> … selected controls … &lt;/selection>
  &lt;back-matter> … &lt;/back-matter>
&lt;/profile>
</tagging>
        </mapping>
        <p>The control selections are combined and collapsed in the next phase of processing,
            <term>merge</term> (see below) .</p>
        <p>Multiple imports may result in outputs with clashing controls (see below). Typically this
          will be because a control has been selected twice (in selection or in the selections of
          underlying profiles), and no merge behavior has been indicated to resolve the clash.</p>
        <p>Typical cases of multiple imports of the same (underlying) resource will be when a
          profile A imports another profile B, which calls catalog Z, and then profile A calls
          catalog Z again to acquire other controls not included in profile B, or in an original
          form unmodified by profile B.</p>
      </section>
      <section id="select-phase">
        <head>Selecting controls</head>
        <p>Imports can specify controls by inclusion and exclusion, either or both in
          combination.</p>
        <section id="include-directive">
          <head>Including controls</head>
          <p>Using inclusion, all or some controls may be selected from a catalog.</p>
          <section id="include-by-id">
            <head>Selecting by ID</head>
            <p>Select individual controls or controls by groups using <src>control-id</src>
              selectors corresponding to their IDs.</p>
            
            <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;include>
  &lt;call control-id="ac-1"/>
&lt;/include>
</tagging>
          </section>
          <section id="include-by-match">
            <head>Matching IDs to select groups of related controls</head>
            <p>Controls may also be selected using match patterns against their IDs. This is useful
              because related controls (either in a hierarchy, or together in a group) frequently
              have related IDs as well.</p>
            
            <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;include>
  &lt;match pattern="^ac"/>&lt;!-- matches any control whose ID matches regex '^ac' -->
&lt;/include>
</tagging>
            <p><revisit>The match pattern is evaluated as a regular expression using XPath regular
                expression syntax. [XXXX]</revisit></p>
          </section>
          <section id="include-all">
            <head>Selecting all controls</head>
            <p>Select all controls from a catalog by using an <src>include/all</src> rule:</p>
            
            <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;include>
  &lt;all/>
&lt;/include>
</tagging>
          </section>
          <section id="include-child-controls">
            <head>Including child controls</head>
            <p>In OSCAL, controls may contain controls. For example, in SP 800-53 many controls are
              supplemented with control enhancements; in OSCAL these are represented as child
              controls within parent controls. So parent AC-2 has children AC-2(1) through AC-2(13),
              for example.</p>
            <p>Child controls can be included by the same mechanism as controls, i.e. by means of an
              ID call. Alternatively a match can frequently be applied (at least given most ID
              assignment schemes) to match controls and child controls together.</p>
            <p>Additionally, a <src>@with-child-controls</src> directive on a <src>call</src> or
                <src>match</src> can indicate that child controls (that is, direct children not all
              descendants) should be included with the applicable call(s) or match(es).</p>
            <p>Furthermore, <src>all[@with-child-controls='no']</src> may select all controls placed
              directly within a group, excluding all controls appearing inside other controls.</p>
            
          </section>
          <section id="redundant-calls">
            <head>Redundant calls</head>
            <p>Calls and matches may be combined in a single import. Their effect is cumulative; any
              control that is selected by both calling and matching from a given <src>include</src>
              directive, or by matching more than one pattern, is included once (unless it is also
              marked for exclusion, see <xref rid="exclude-directive"/>).</p>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section id="exclude-directive">
          <head>Excluding controls</head>
          <p>Exclusions work the same way as inclusions, except with the opposite effect - the
            indicated control(s) do not appear in the target catalog.</p>
          <p>Additionally, there is no such thing as <src>exclude/all</src>, which is invalid and
            should be considered inoperable.</p>
          <p>Any control designated to be both included and excluded, is excluded. This holds
            irrespective of the specificity of the selection for inclusion or exclusion. For
            example, if AC-1 is included by id <code>ac-1</code> and excluded by matching
              <code>ac.*</code>, it is excluded. Selection for exclusion prevails.</p>
          <p><propose>One possible exception: what about when a control is excluded, but it has
              descendant controls that are included? Under <src>include/all</src>, the descendants
              maybe would be excluded. If the subcontrol is included by <src>call</src> or
                <src>match</src> perhaps the 'shells' of its ancestors should be included despite
              their nominal exclusion. See section on "implicit inclusions under as-is",
              below.</propose></p>
        </section>
        <section id="implicit-all">
          <head>Implicit <src>all</src></head>
          <p>An empty import statement should be considered the same as an import with an
              <src>include/all</src>. An empy <src>import</src> directive</p>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;import href="#nist-catalog"/>
</tagging>
          <p>is functionally equivalent to this:</p>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;import href="#nist-catalog">
  &lt;include>
    &lt;all/>
  &lt;/include>
&lt;/import>
</tagging>
          
          <p>The same thing occurs if an <src>exclude</src> directive is given without an
              <src>include</src> directive.</p>
          <p>Example:</p>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;import href="#nist-catalog">
  &lt;exclude>
    &lt;call control-id="ac-1"/>
  &lt;/exclude>
&lt;/import>
</tagging>
          <p>is the same as this:</p>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;import href="#nist-catalog">
  &lt;include>
    &lt;all/>
  &lt;/include>
  &lt;exclude>
    &lt;call control-id="ac-1"/>
  &lt;/exclude>
&lt;/import>
</tagging>
          <p>Target: all controls from the catalog are included <em>except</em> AC-1.</p>
          
        </section>
        <section id="controls-order">
          <head>Order of controls returned in selection</head>
          <p>Because controls may be organized in the subsequence merge phase, order of controls
            returned in the selection step is unimportant in most circumstances. If no merge
            directive is applied, however, or the <q>no merge</q> combination rule is used (see
            below), controls are returned for an import in the order of their appearance in their
            catalog of origin.</p>
          <p><revisit>BR suggests we revisit as an alternative would be to sort in call order. I
              think the given proposal is simplier given cases of match and "all".</revisit></p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <head>Copying parameters</head>
        <p>Unlike controls, parameters are copied implicitly. Whether a parameter in the source
          catalog is copied into the target depends on two factors: its location, and whether it is
          referenced by an <tgt>insert</tgt> directive in the target catalog.</p>
        <p><src>insert</src> directives may occur anywhere in a catalog's data content including not
          only in controls, but in other parameters. Thus a parameter may have to be included by
          virtue of an <src>insert</src> directive, making reference to it, that occurs in another
          parameter, included by virtue of a different <src>insert</src> directive found in an
          included control.</p>
        <section id="params-in-controls">
          <head>Parameters given in controls</head>
          <p>Any parameter (<src>param</src> element) that appears in a control being selected,
            appears in the target, unless the parameter element was indicated by a remove directive
            (see below <xref rid="remove-directive"/>).</p>
          <p><revisit>BR thinks such nonsense should be prevented somehow perhaps warnings or
              errors. My feeling is, that's what validation is all about.</revisit></p>
          <mapping>
            <tagging whose="source_catalog">&lt;control id="a1">
    &lt;title>Control A1&lt;/title>
    &lt;param id="param-a1.a">
        &lt;label>a1.a parameter&lt;/label>
        &lt;value>a1.a value&lt;/value>
    &lt;/param>
    &lt;prop name="status">alive&lt;/prop>
    &lt;part name="statement" id="a1-stmt">
        &lt;p>A1 aaaaa aaaaaaaaaa&lt;/p>
    &lt;/part>
&lt;/control></tagging>
          </mapping>
          
        </section>
        <section id="loose-params">
          <head>Loose parameters</head>
          <p>There are two situations where parameters must be considered separately from controls,
            in which case they are considered to be <q>loose</q>, appearing in the target directly
            inside <tgt>catalog</tgt> or <tgt>group</tgt>. The first is when they have no control
            parent in the source catalog (or rendered profile): they are <q>inherently loose</q>.
            The second is when they <q>become loose</q> because the control in which they appear, is
            not selected, but they are needed in the target, due to being referenced for insertion
            elsewhere. <revisit>(Examples)</revisit></p>
          <p>The same parameter, however, cannot be both loose and anchored. If it is invoked from
            inside its parent control, it is considered as anchored, even if it would also be called
            (as loose) by virtue of insertions made outside the parent control, were the parent
            control not included. That is, a <tgt>param</tgt> only appears loose in the resolution
            target, if it is also loose in its source catalog, or if its parent control in the
            source catalog is not included in the profile.</p>
          <p>In general, loose parameters (parameter declarations, <src>param</src>) are permitted
            to support flexibility for referencing, especially making multiple references to a
            parameter. It may be convenient to represent a parameter that is referenced from inside
            two different controls, outside both of them, or to group parameters separately from
            controls for simpler management. <revisit>(This does not occur in the SP800-53
              catalog.)</revisit></p>
          <p>Loose parameters (that is, with <tgt>catalog</tgt> or <tgt>group</tgt> parents, not
            controls) appear in the target if (only if) elsewhere in the target, some content is
            also propagated, which after modification contains an <src>insert</src> directive
            referencing this parameter. (The <src>param/@id</src> appears on an
              <src>insert/@param-id</src> elsewhere in the target document.) In the target, the
              <tgt>param</tgt> appears in the location corresponding to its location in the source,
            albeit ungrouped if no <src>merge/as-is</src> is given, and sorted with respect to
              <tgt>control</tgt> elements at the same level: all <tgt>param</tgt> elements first,
            followed by all <tgt>control</tgt> elements, conforming to canonical order for the
              <tgt>catalog</tgt> or <tgt>group</tgt> container. <revisit>this is a case where the
              XML and JSON requirements are different.</revisit></p>
          <p>When a catalog is organized by a <src>merge/custom</src> directive, loose parameters
            are copied into the resulting grouping structure directly preceding the first control
            appearing that contains an <src>insert</src> directive referencing that parameter.</p>
          <p>Parameters that are not referenced by an <src>insert</src> elsewhere in the target, do not appear
            in the target. While it is not formally invalid to include unreferenced (unused) parameters,
          profile resolution requires that none be included except as a special option.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="merge-phase">
      <head>Merge phase</head>
      <section id="merge-combine">
        <head><src>merge/combine</src> - handling control collisions</head>
        <p><term>Colliding controls</term> (or <term>clashing</term>) describes the condition that
          occurs when multiple invocations of controls with the same ID are given, and so a profile
          resolution will result in duplicative and/or contradictory information. Even given a rule
          against multiple imports of the same resource, it may frequently occur that in profiles
          (especially profiles under development), multiple copies – and with variations – may be
          invoked from different sources. For example, if a profile tailors another profile which
          includes a control with amendments, and then (the top-level profile) includes the same
          control directly from its original catalog, a collision will occur between these two
          variants.</p>
        <p>Generally such a collision is readily detectable as long as IDs have not been modified;
          in other words, constraints over uniqueness (within document scope) of IDs will be
          violated in resolved instances where two (perhaps different) representations of the same
          control appear. Careful profile authors will be able to detect and prevent these resulting
          problems.</p>
        <p>Apart from handling problems and exceptions, however, for different purposes different
          profiles might wish to apply different rules. OSCAL offers three such rules: the
          directives for each are given as a value on the <src>@method</src> attribute of a profile
            <src>merge/combine</src> element.</p>
        <section id="no-merge-explicit">
          <head>No <src>merge/combine</src> given</head>
          <p>If no <src>merge</src> directive is given in the profile, or if a <src>merge</src> is
            given without a <src>combine</src>, control or parameter clashes are treated as if
              <src>merge/combine[@method='keep']</src> were given. A profile with no
              <src>merge</src> directive:</p>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile>
  &lt;import href="#catalog1"/>
  &lt;import href="#catalog2"/>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
          <p>is the same as</p>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile>
  &lt;import href="#catalog1"/>
  &lt;import href="#catalog2"/>
  &lt;merge>
    &lt;combine method="keep"/>
  &lt;/merge>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
          <mapping unit-test="profile-resolution-examples/merge-implicit-keep_profile.xml"/>
        </section>
        <section id="no-merge-combination-rule">
          <head><q>No merge</q> combination rule</head>
          <p>When a merge is indicated by <src>merge/combine[@method='keep']</src>, or not given,
            the <q>no merge</q> combination rule is used. Clashing controls or parameters are not
            merged. (They are kept.) Their groups are merged only if another <src>merge</src>
            directive such as <src>as-is</src> is given. (The combination rules affect only the
            handling of colliding controls, not their grouping in the target.)</p>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;merge>
  &lt;combine method="keep"/>
&lt;/merge>
</tagging>
          <p>Under this directive, colliding controls will result in invalid results, as they will
            both appear in the results with the same ID. Accordingly, this setting may be useful in
            ensuring integrity of references to controls as given in the profile: if any included
            control is called only once, clashing controls will not be produced and validation will
            succeed.</p>
          <mapping unit-test="profile-resolution-examples/merge-keep_profile.xml">
            <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0 ../../../../xml/schema/oscal_profile_schema.xsd"
    id="merge-keep_profile">
    &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
    &lt;import href="abc-simple_catalog.xml">
        &lt;include>
            &lt;call control-id="a1"/>
            &lt;call control-id="b1"/>
        &lt;/include>
    &lt;/import>
    &lt;import href="abc-simple_catalog.xml">
        &lt;include>
            &lt;call control-id="a1"/>
            &lt;call control-id="b1"/>
        &lt;/include>
    &lt;/import>
    &lt;merge>
        &lt;combine method="keep"/>
    &lt;/merge>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
            <p>In the target (showing control selections):</p>
            <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;profile xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0"
    id="merge-keep_profile">
    &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
    &lt;selection id="…">
      &lt;control id="a1"> … &lt;/control>
      &lt;control id="b1"> … &lt;/control>
    &lt;/selection>
    &lt;selection id="…">
      &lt;control id="a1"> … &lt;/control>
      &lt;control id="b1"> … &lt;/control>
    &lt;/selection>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
          </mapping>
          <p>In this case, downstream errors should be expected: the two <code>a1</code> controls
            clash with each other, as do the two <code>b1</code> controls. To remove the duplicates,
            either repair the source catalog to avoid the redundant invocations (usually a better
            solution) or (when that is unavoidable) use a different merge combination rule.</p>
          <p>Processors may optionally produce warnings when clashing controls are produced due to
            redundant invocations.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="use-first-combination-rule">
          <head><q>Use first</q> merge combination rule</head>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;merge>
  &lt;combine="use-first"/>
&lt;/merge>
</tagging>
          <p>When the <q>use first</q> combination rule is applied, the first reference to a given
            control, with respect to the document order of the source data, prevails over later
            references. <q>First</q> is determined in reference to a top-down, depth-first traversal
            of the profile import hierarchy. So if a profile is imported before a catalog, and the
            imported profile presents a representation of a control also given in the catalog
            import, the profile’s representation (perhaps modified) is taken. However, if the import
            directive targeting the catalog appears first, the catalog's (unmodified) representation
            of the control is included.</p>
          <p>The same logic applies to parameters in the source catalogs, as modified by parameter
              <src>set</src> directives.</p>
          <mapping unit-test="profile-resolution-examples/merge-keep_profile.xml">
            <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0 ../../../../xml/schema/oscal_profile_schema.xsd"
    id="merge-keep_profile">
    &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
    &lt;import href="abc-simple_catalog.xml">
        &lt;include>
            &lt;call control-id="a1"/>
            &lt;call control-id="c1"/>
        &lt;/include>
    &lt;/import>
    &lt;import href="abc-simple_catalog.xml">
        &lt;include>
            &lt;call control-id="a1"/>
            &lt;call control-id="b1"/>
        &lt;/include>
    &lt;/import>
    &lt;merge>
        &lt;combine method="use-first"/>
    &lt;/merge>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
            <p>In the target (showing control selections):</p>
            <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;profile xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0"
    id="merge-keep_profile">
    &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
    &lt;selection id="…">
      &lt;control id="a1"> … &lt;/control>
      &lt;control id="c1"> … &lt;/control>
    &lt;/selection>
    &lt;selection id="…">
      &lt;control id="b1"> … &lt;/control>
    &lt;/selection>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
          </mapping>
          <p><revisit>The <q>use first</q> combination rule also affects back matter,
            q.v.</revisit></p>
        </section>
        <section id="merge-combination-rule">
          <head><q>Merge controls</q> merge combination rule</head>
          <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;merge>
  &lt;combine="merge"/>
&lt;/merge>
</tagging>
          <p>When the <term>merge controls</term> merge combination rule is applied, the processor
            will merge all representations of a given control, as distinguished by ID, into a single
            unified representation.</p>
          <p>The single unified representation is assembled by aggregating all the contents of all
            the (clashing) control instances and discarding replicated branches, so that only a
            single instance of each distinctive element appears in the result. The order of the
            copied contents will be their original order within their controls, given in the
            original order of the controls in their source catalog, then sorted into canonical order
            for control contents. </p>
          <p>Example:</p>
          <tagging whose="source_catalog">&lt;control id="a1">
  &lt;title>Control A1&lt;/title>
  &lt;prop name="label">A-1&lt;/prop>
  &lt;prop name="status">pending&lt;/prop>
&lt;/control>
</tagging>
          <p>merging with</p>
          <tagging whose="source_catalog">&lt;control id="a1">
  &lt;title>Control A1&lt;/title>
  &lt;prop name="label">A-1&lt;/prop>
  &lt;prop name="status">ready&lt;/prop>
&lt;/control>
</tagging>
          <p>produces</p>
          <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;control id="a1">
  &lt;title>Control A1&lt;/title>
  &lt;prop name="label">A-1&lt;/prop>
  &lt;prop name="status">pending&lt;/prop>
  &lt;prop name="status">ready&lt;/prop>
&lt;/control>
</tagging>
          <p>Note that groups are not merged by this rule; for that purpose, <src>merge/as-is</src>
            or <src>merge/custom</src> should be used (in addition to the combine directive).</p>
          <p>Since the effect of this merge rule is to drop data silently (when it is considered to
            be redundant or duplicative), it should only be used on well-understood, well-controlled
            catalog and profile inputs, whose potential clashes or collisions are known in
            advance.</p>
          <p><revisit>BR wants SP800-53 examples and points out prop[@name='status'] is not in it.
              But this is not a guide to SP800-53 it is a spec for any profile
            resolution.</revisit></p>
        </section>
        <section id="combining-back-matter">
          <head>Effects of combination rules on back matter</head>
          <p>When profiles import from more than one resource (catalog or profile), not only is
            there a potential for clashing controls, but also citation and resource elements
            appearing in the back matter, may clash with other citations and resources, yielding
            validation errors in the result when an ID appears more than once.</p>
          <p>This situation is not remedied by the <q>no merge</q> combination rule. Under this
            rule, any citation or resource that is referenced from an imported catalog or profile,
            is included in the resolution target. This may result in replicated contents, where the
            same element is given more than once in the target, producing violations of
            ID-uniqueness constraints. For profiles that call controls from more than one import
            pathway, the <q>no merge</q> combination may be most useful for debugging.</p>
          <p>Under the <q>use first</q> rule (with <src>merge/combine[@method='use-first']</src>),
            only the first <src>citation</src> with a given ID is kept from the set of citations
            (gathered from all sources). Likewise only the first <src>resource</src> with a given ID
            is kept from the set of resources. Note that uncontrolled identifiers may still clash –
            for example, this will not prevent a <tgt>citation</tgt> and <tgt>resource</tgt> from
            appearing in the result with the same ID (perhaps sourced from two different catalogs).
            Maintenance and possibly revision of upstream data sets is necessary to prevent such
            ambiguities.</p>
          <p><revisit>Examples</revisit></p>
          <p><revisit>How does the <src>merge/combine[@method='merge']</src> (<q>merge controls</q>)
              rule apply to back matter? Maybe the same as use-first. Or maybe use an approach
              similar to controls.</revisit></p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="structuring-result">
        <head>Structuring the target</head>
        <p>The overall organization of the target document at the top level has been described <xref rid="target-structure"/>. This section describes how a profile may dictate the body of
          the target <tgt>catalog</tgt>, apart from its <tgt>metadata</tgt> or
            <tgt>back-matter</tgt>.</p>
        <p>The <src>merge</src> element, in addition to proposing a strategy by which to
          disambiguate clashing controls, also includes directives that can be used to organize the
          target catalog into a structure or hierarchy of groups. Two <src>merge</src> directives
          are used to introduce structure into the target catalog, <src>as-is</src> and
            <src>custom</src>. If neither is given, no structure is provided: parameters and
          controls in the target appear in sequence, with no structure or grouping apart from what
          is internal to the controls</p>
        <section id="merge-flat">
          <head>Unstructured catalog output</head>
          <p>Profiles that have neither of these directives are resolved as unstructured catalogs,
            with no groupings of controls.</p>
          <p>Unstructured catalog output is produced by emitting the contents of the sequence of
            control selections produced in the selection phase, seeing to it that (for validity in
            XML) they are sorted so that all loose <tgt>param</tgt> elements (that is, that do not
            appear inside controls) appear before all <tgt>control</tgt> elements.</p>
          <mapping>
            <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0"
    id="merge-keep_profile">
    &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
    &lt;selection id="…">
      &lt;param id="p1"> … &lt;/param>
      &lt;control id="a1">
        &lt;param id="p3"> … &lt;/param>
         … &lt;/control>
      &lt;control id="c1"> … &lt;/control>
    &lt;/selection>
    &lt;selection id="…">
      &lt;param id="p2"> … &lt;/param>
      &lt;control id="b1"> … &lt;/control>
    &lt;/selection>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
            <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;catalog xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0"
    id="<hi>{ catalog-id }</hi>">
    &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
    &lt;param id="p1"> … &lt;/param>
    &lt;param id="p2"> … &lt;/param>
    &lt;control id="a1">
      &lt;param id="p3"> … &lt;/param>
       … &lt;/control>
    &lt;control id="c1"> … &lt;/control>
    &lt;control id="b1"> … &lt;/control>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
          </mapping>
        </section>
        <section id="merge-as-is">
          <head>Merging <q>as is</q></head>
          <p>An <src>as-is</src>directive is used to reproduce the structure of a source catalog in
            the target catalog. When more than one catalog is referenced by a profile, the
              <src>as-is</src> directive produces a catalog that combines the grouping structures of
            all the source catalogs.</p>
          <p><revisit>(consider case of multiple imports of single resource – we need to track
              catalog identity here)</revisit></p>
          <section id="as-is-implicit">
            <head>Implicit inclusions under <src>as-is</src></head>
            <p>Under <term>as is</term>, a resolved profile’s structure is expected to replicate the
              structure of source catalogs.</p>
            <p>This is achieved by propagating, with all controls that are included, all groups that
              they appear within, along with the groups’ IDs, titles and other contents, including
              any parameters to be referenced in the target (<xref rid="loose-params"/> ) or
                <src>part</src> element children; but not including any controls not included in one
              or another control selection, directly or indirectly. Controls may be included into a
              group indirectly when merging <term>as is</term>, by virtue of containing controls
              that have been included <xref rid="merge-as-is"/></p>
            <p>Groups that do not include controls that have been included (either directly or as
              descendants of contained groups), are not propagated to the target.</p>
            <p>This is slightly different from groups, which may in valid inputs have other contents
              – besides titles, controls, or groups – that profile authors wish to see copied into
              the customized catalog.</p>
            <p>Example:</p>
            <tagging whose="source_catalog">&lt;control id="xyz-1">
  &lt;title>Basic Household&lt;/title>
  &lt;control id="xyz-1.1">&lt;!-- bedtime routine -->...&lt;/control>
  &lt;control id="xyz-1.2">
    &lt;title>Kitchen cleanup&lt;/title>
	&lt;control id="xyz-1.2.1">&lt;!-- kitchen trashcan -->...&lt;/control>
  &lt;/control>
  &lt;control id="xyz-1.3">&lt;!-- newspaper delivery -->...&lt;/control>
&lt;/control>

</tagging>
            <p>In this case the profile does not designate either control <code>xyz-1</code> or
              control <code>xyz-1.2</code> for inclusion</p>
            <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;import href="#XYZ-catalog">
  &lt;include>
    &lt;call control-id='xyz-1.1'/>&lt;!-- bedtime routine -->
    &lt;call control-id='xyz-1.2.1'/>&lt;!-- kitchen trashcan -->
  &lt;/include>
&lt;/import>
</tagging>
            <p>The unmentioned elements are included, however, with their titles, because controls
              that they contain are included. But control <code>xyz-1.3</code> does not appear in
              the target.</p>
            <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;control id="xyz-1">
  &lt;title>Basic Hygiene&lt;/title>
  &lt;control id="xyz-1.1">&lt;!-- bedtime routine -->...&lt;/control>
  &lt;control id="xyz-1.2">
    &lt;title>Kitchen cleanup&lt;/title>
	&lt;control id="xyz-1.2.1">&lt;!-- kitchen trashcan -->...&lt;/control>
  &lt;/control>
&lt;/control>

</tagging>
            <p>Note that this means there may be controls that are selected implicitly by
                <tgt>as-is</tgt> merging, over and above controls actually designated in import
              statements. Thus the control set, considered strictly, of the target of an
                <tgt>as-is</tgt> process, will be different from the control set delivered by a
                <q>no merge</q> process.</p>
            <p>Processors may optionally provide services for detection of nesting and structural
              issues related to the importing and merging of controls, including but not limited to
              validation / detection utilities (for imports regarded as incorrect, incomplete or
              otherwise subject to improvement); runtime warnings; or user interfaces.</p>
          </section>
          <section id="as-is-group-contents">
            <head>Group contents under merging as-is</head>
            <p>One title only. Other contents? Elements and controls are subject to the merge
              combination rules. <revisit>Other kinds of contents of groups … </revisit></p>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section id="merge-custom">
          <head>Merging into a new structure: <src>custom</src></head>
          <p>The <src>merge/custom</src> directive provides a way to provide a target catalog with a
            custom structure. It combines <src>call</src> or <src>match</src> directives, which work
            as they do in selection, into groups, which provide the target with its structure.</p>
          <p>The controls to be included must be selected in the profile's import. A call or match
            appearing inside <src>custom</src>, if it refers to controls not selected, is
            inoperative.</p>
          <p>The structures given inside the <src>custom</src> assembly indicate the structure of
            the  target catalog. They produce this structure by mapping one for one. Unlike
              <q>as-is</q> merging, there is no implicit inclusion of controls by virtue of
            including descendant controls. Instead, all controls are included in the target in the
            locations indicated by the custom structure.</p>
          <section id="custom-groups">
            <head>Grouping controls inside a custom structure</head>
            <p>A <src>group</src> element given in a custom structure results in an analogous
                <tgt>group</tgt>. Its attributes (flags) are copied to the target catalog to appear
              on the <tgt>group</tgt> in the target. All element contents inside the group,
              including <src>title</src>, <src>param</src>, <src>prop</src> and <src>part</src>
              elements are likewise copied into the target, appearing in the same order as in the
              source.</p>
            <p>Within <src>custom</src>, <src>call</src> and <src>match</src> elements reference
              controls in much the same way as they do when given in import/include directives - a
              control is either selected by <src>@id</src> (<src>call.@control-id</src>) or matched
              using a pattern on its <src>@id</src> (<src>match/@pattern</src>).</p>
            <p>A <src>call</src> results in including, at that point inside the new grouping, all
              controls with the <src>@id</src> given by the <src>call/@control-id</src>. They should
              be given in the same order as they appear in the control selection(s). Merge
              combination rules apply. <xref rid="merge-combine"/></p>
            <p>A <src>match</src> results in including, at that point inside the new grouping, all
              controls whose <src>@id</src> matching, as an XPath regular expression, the pattern
              given in the <src>match/@pattern</src>. This may result in several or many controls;
              again they are given in the same order as they have in the control selection(s).
              Again, among clashing controls (that have the same ID), merge combination rules apply.
                <xref rid="merge-combine"/></p>
            <mapping>
              <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0"
    id="merge-custom_profile">
    &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
    &lt;import href="abc-simple_catalog.xml">
        &lt;include>
            &lt;call control-id="a1"/>
            &lt;call control-id="a2"/>
            &lt;call control-id="b1"/>
            &lt;call control-id="b2"/>
            &lt;call control-id="c1"/>
            &lt;call control-id="c2"/>
        &lt;/include>
    &lt;/import>
    &lt;merge>
        &lt;custom>
            &lt;group>
                &lt;title>New Group I&lt;/title>
                &lt;call control-id="a1"/>
                &lt;call control-id="b1"/>
                &lt;call control-id="c1"/>
            &lt;/group>
            &lt;group>
                &lt;title>New Group II&lt;/title>
                &lt;call control-id="b2"/>
                &lt;call control-id="c2"/>
            &lt;/group>
    &lt;/merge>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
              <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;catalog xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0"
    id="<hi>{ new-catalog-identifier }</hi>">
    &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
    &lt;group>
        &lt;title>New Group I&lt;/title>
        &lt;control id="a1"> … &lt;/control>
        &lt;control id="b1"> … &lt;/control>
        &lt;control id="c1"> … &lt;/control>
    &lt;/group>
    &lt;group>
        &lt;title>New Group II&lt;/title>
        &lt;control id="b2"> … &lt;/control>
        &lt;control id="c2"> … &lt;/control>
    &lt;/group>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
              <p>In this example, control <code>a2</code> does <em>not</em> appear in the target
                catalog, as a custom structure was indicated (by the presence of the source profile
                  <src>merge/custom</src>), but the control never referenced by a <src>call</src>
                (or <src>match</src>) directive inside the custom structure.</p>
              <p>When a custom structure references a control that is not included in any control
                selection (in the import phase), the reference is inoperative. A processor may
                signal a warning in this case.</p>
              <p>Similarly, no error occurs if a control is selected (appears in a control selection
                or even more than one), but it is never referenced from the <src>custom</src>
                structure given. The control does not appear in the target catalog. Again, a
                processor may optionally signal a warning if this occurs.</p>
            </mapping>
            <mapping>
              <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0"
    id="merge-custom_profile">
    &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
    &lt;import href="abc-simple_catalog.xml">
        &lt;include>
            &lt;call control-id="a1"/>
            &lt;call control-id="a2"/>
            &lt;call control-id="b1"/>
            &lt;call control-id="b2"/>
            &lt;call control-id="c1"/>
            &lt;call control-id="c2"/>
        &lt;/include>
    &lt;/import>
    &lt;merge>
        &lt;custom>
            &lt;call control-id="b2"/>
            &lt;call control-id="c2"/>
            &lt;group id="group1">
                &lt;title>New Grouping&lt;/title>
                &lt;call control-id="a1"/>
                &lt;call control-id="b1"/>
                &lt;group  id="group2">
                  &lt;call control-id="c1"/>
                &lt;/group>
            &lt;/group>
    &lt;/merge>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
              <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;catalog xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0"
    id="<hi>{ new-catalog-identifier }</hi>">
    &lt;metadata> … &lt;/metadata>
    &lt;control id="b2"> … &lt;/control>
    &lt;control id="c2"> … &lt;/control>
    &lt;group id="group1">
        &lt;title>New Grouping&lt;/title>
        &lt;control id="a1"> … &lt;/control>
        &lt;control id="b1"> … &lt;/control>
        &lt;group id="group2">
          &lt;control id="c1"> … &lt;/control>
        &lt;/group>
    &lt;/group>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
              <p>In this case, no <tgt>group</tgt> container appears in the target for the controls
                  <code>b2</code> and <code>c2</code>;  because they appear unwrapped before the
                  <src>group</src> in the profile source, they appear the same way in the target
                catalog. Control <code>c2</code>, however, appears in a subgroup <code>group2</code>
                inside the group with ID <code>group1</code> , again reflecting the source
                organization. Note also that <src>id</src> flags are copied.</p>
              <p>Again, no provision is made to prevent duplicate or colliding controls from
                appearing. Optionally, a processor may signal warnings when it determines that
                controls from selections are designated to appear in the results more than once, due
                to multiple colliding occurrences of <src>call</src> or <src>match</src> inside
                  <src>custom</src>.</p>
            </mapping>
          </section>
          <section id="custom-with-child-controls">
            <head><src>with-child-controls</src> inside a custom catalog structure</head>
            <p><src>@with-child-controls</src> works also: if child controls are selected, they can
              be included implicitly by virtue of including their parents.)</p>
            <p><revisit>How do we arrange for deeper nesting of controls in a custom
                structure?</revisit></p>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="modify-phase">
      <head>Modification phase</head>
      <p>(Aka <term>patching</term>) Explicit modification of control content</p>
      <p>There are two ways a control may need to be modified. Commonly, controls might be amended –
        new material might be added. (For example, the priority marker properties P1-P3 in the
        SP800-53 LOW MODERATE and HIGH baselines.) Less commonly, materials might be removed or
        edited.</p>
      <p>OSCAL does not provide for <q>changing</q> a control, but editing can be achieved by
        removing contents and adding (edited) contents back. This can be achieved at the control
        level, or, when constituent elements inside a control have distinct IDs, at more granular
        levels as well. Features make it easy both to trim (filter) and to supplement catalogs.   </p>
      <p>In addition to any modification or adjustment to controls, this section of a profile is
        used to set parameter values or other properties of parameters declared in catalogs and
        referenced from their text. Parameters are propagated with the profile's setting into the
        target catalog for its use.</p>
      <section id="param-setting">
        <head>Setting Parameters</head>
        <p>Modification of parameter settings is indicated using <src>set</src>.</p>
        <p>Parameters are not always given within controls. A profile resolution target must include
          copies (with or without modifications or settings) of all parameters defined within the
          source catalog, which are referenced from <src>insert</src> directives anywhere inside
          included controls.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, any parameter referenced by an <src>insert</src> in any source catalog is
          copied from catalog source to target <revisit>parameter propagation rules for merge/as-is,
            merge/custom</revisit> without any configuration required in the profile.</p>
        <p>However, a profile should not reproduce parameters from source catalogs, which are not
          referenced from <src>insert</src> directives.</p>
        <p>When parameters are propagated, they may be modified by <src>set</src> directives given
          in the profile.</p>
        <p>If more than one <src>set</src> directive is given for the same parameter, all are
          applied, in the sequence given in the profile. <revisit>[XXX even when
            merge/combine/@method='use-first'?]</revisit></p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p>A <src>set/label</src> replaces the <src>param/label</src> on the affected
              parameter</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>A <src>set/value</src>
              <em>or</em> a <src>set/select</src> replaces <em>any</em>
              <src>param/value</src> or <src>param/select</src> on the affected parameter</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>Other elements given in a parameter <src>set</src> are added to the affected
              parameter, after elements of the same name</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>The prescribed order of elements in the affected parameter is retained:
                <tgt>label</tgt>; <tgt>usage</tgt>; <tgt>constraint</tgt>; <tgt>guideline</tgt>;
                <tgt>value</tgt> or <tgt>select</tgt> (a choice); and <tgt>link</tgt>.</p>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>[example]</p>
        <tagging whose="source_catalog">&lt;param id="p1">
  &lt;title>Password length&lt;/title>
  &lt;value>10&lt;/value>
&lt;/param>
</tagging>
        <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;set param-id="p1">
  &lt;select>
    &lt;choice>10&lt;/choice>
    &lt;choice>11&lt;/choice>
  &lt;/select>
&lt;/set>
</tagging>
        <p>Note that <tgt>select</tgt> replaces <src>value</src>:</p>
        <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;param id="p1">
  &lt;title>Password length&lt;/title>
  &lt;select>
    &lt;choice>10&lt;/choice>
    &lt;choice>11&lt;/choice>
  &lt;/select>
&lt;/param>
</tagging>
        <section>
          <head>Setting a missing parameter</head>
          <p>A <src>set</src> directive whose <src>@control-id</src> does not correspond to any
            control in the resolved catalog, is inoperative.</p>
          <p>Optionally, a processor may issue a warning where such directives are found.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="control-altering">
        <head>Altering controls</head>
        <p>A control can be altered by an <src>alter</src> directive on a control. The
            <src>@control-id</src> flag on the <src>alter</src> indicates the control to which the
          alteration is applied.</p>
        <section id="add-directive">
          <head>Adding contents to controls</head>
          <p>Contents may be added to controls using an add directive inside an alter directive.
            There are two forms of alteration: with implicit and explicit bindings.</p>
          <section id="add-to-control">
            <head>Implicit binding</head>
            <p>An <src>add</src> directive with no <src>id-ref</src> flag is taken to apply to the
              control as a whole. Its <src>position</src> flag may be either of two values:
                <code>starting</code> and <code>ending</code>.</p>
            <p>The contents of the add directive are then added to the control contents in the
              target, either after its <tgt>title</tgt> when <src>position</src> is
                <code>starting</code>, or at the end if its position is <code>ending</code>, or not
              given.</p>
            <p>However, control contents in catalogs must appear in the order <code>title, param,
                prop, link, part, control</code>. Subsequent to adding new elements, the control
              contents are sorted to appear in the required order. As a consequence, a new
                <tgt>prop</tgt> appears after any <src>prop</src> already in the control, when
                <src>position</src> is <code>ending</code>, or not given,, or before any
                <src>prop</src> in the control when <src>position</src> is
              <code>starting</code>.</p>
            <p>When add has no <src>@ref-id</src> (has an implicit binding), the <src>position</src>
              values <code>before</code> and <code>after</code> are treated like
                <code>starting</code> and <code>ending</code>, respectively. <revisit>The schema
                permits these values.</revisit></p>
            <mapping>
              <p>An addition operating on a control with implicit binding and position
                  <code>starting</code></p>
              <tagging whose="source_catalog">&lt;control id="a1">
  &lt;title>Basic precautions&lt;/title>
  &lt;prop name="status">ready&lt;/prop>
&lt;/control></tagging>
              <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;alter control-id="a1">
  &lt;add position="starting">
    &lt;prop name="basis">enumerated&lt;/prop>
    &lt;part name="caution">&lt;p>Only for adult use.&lt;/p>&lt;/part>
  &lt;/add>
&lt;/alter></tagging>
              <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;control id="a1">
  &lt;title>Basic precautions&lt;/title>
  &lt;prop name="basis">enumerated&lt;/prop>
  &lt;prop name="status">ready&lt;/prop>
  &lt;part name="caution">&lt;p>Only for adult use.&lt;/p>&lt;/part>
&lt;/control></tagging>
              <p>Position is <code>starting</code> but the new <tgt>part</tgt> is added after the
                existing <tgt>prop</tgt>, because <tgt>prop</tgt> elements must always occur
                first.</p>
            </mapping>
            <mapping>
              <p>An addition operating on a control with implicit binding and position
                  <code>ending</code></p>
              <tagging whose="source_catalog">&lt;control id="a1">
  &lt;title>Basic precautions&lt;/title>
  &lt;prop name="status">ready&lt;/prop>
&lt;/control></tagging>
              <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;alter control-id="a1">
  &lt;add position="ending">
    &lt;prop name="basis">enumerated&lt;/prop>
    &lt;part name="caution">&lt;p>Only for adult use.&lt;/p>&lt;/part>
  &lt;/add>
&lt;/alter></tagging>
              <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;control id="a1">
  &lt;title>Basic precautions&lt;/title>
  &lt;prop name="status">ready&lt;/prop>
  &lt;prop name="basis">enumerated&lt;/prop>
  &lt;part name="caution">&lt;p>Only for adult use.&lt;/p>&lt;/part>
&lt;/control></tagging>
              <p>The <src>add/@position</src> is <code>ending</code> so the new <tgt>prop</tgt>
                appears after the existing <tgt>prop</tgt>.</p>
            </mapping>
          </section>
          <section id="add-to-element">
            <head>Explicit binding</head>
            <p>An explicit binding on an addition permits inserting new contents anywhere in a
              control, not only at the top level. It is given by a <src>@ref-id</src> flag on the
                <src>add</src> directive. The value of the <src>@ref-id</src> must correspond to the
              value of an <src>@id</src> flag on an element inside the control, and not the control
              itself. If <src>ref-id</src> does not correspond to such a value, the <src>add</src>
              directive is inoperative. Optionally, a warning may be issued in such a case.</p>
            <p>The element with <src>@id</src> equal to the <src>@ref-id</src> is considered the
                <term>target</term> of the addition.</p>
            <p>Additionally, with an explicit binding given by a <src>@ref-id</src>,
                <src>@position</src> may have any of the values <code>starting</code>,
                <code>ending</code>, <code>before</code> and <code>after</code>.</p>
            <p>When <src>position</src> is <code>starting</code> or <code>ending</code>, the new
              contents are added at the beginning or ending of the target element, inside that
              element, as are additions into controls (using implicit bindings).</p>
            <p>Additionally, a <src>position</src> given as <code>before</code> indicates the
              addition should be made directly before the target element, while <code>after</code>
              indicates the addition should appear directly after the target element.</p>
            <p><revisit>Unlike additions with implicit bindings, an explicit binding does not
                provide for sorting of newly added elements to ensure correct ordering.
                Consequently, profile authors must take care that additions they make into control
                contents using explicit bindings will produce results valid to the catalog
                schema.</revisit></p>
            <mapping>
              <p>An addition operating on a control with explicit binding and position
                  <code>after</code></p>
              <tagging whose="source_catalog">&lt;control id="a1">
  &lt;title>Basic precautions&lt;/title>
  &lt;prop name="status">ready&lt;/prop>
  &lt;part id="a1.b" name="recommendations">
    &lt;part id="a1.b1">&lt;p>Collect recycling for pickup.&lt;/p>&lt;/part>
    &lt;part id="a1.b2">&lt;p>Sweep surfaces free of dust.&lt;/p>&lt;/part>
  &lt;/part>
&lt;/control></tagging>
              <p>Note that the <src>add</src> directive identifies the element with <src>@id</src>
                <code>a1.b1</code> as its target.</p>
              <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;alter control-id="a1">
  &lt;add position="after" ref-id="a1.b1">
    &lt;prop name="basis">allocated&lt;/prop>
    &lt;part name="caution">&lt;p>Unavailable on weekends.&lt;/p>&lt;/part>
  &lt;/add>
&lt;/alter></tagging>
              <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;control id="a1">
  &lt;title>Basic precautions&lt;/title>
  &lt;prop name="status">ready&lt;/prop>
  &lt;part id="a1.b" name="recommendations">
    &lt;part id="a1.b1">&lt;p>Collect recycling for pickup.&lt;/p>&lt;/part>
    &lt;prop name="basis">allocated&lt;/prop>
    &lt;part name="caution">&lt;p>Unavailable on weekends.&lt;/p>&lt;/part>
    &lt;part id="a1.b2">&lt;p>Sweep surfaces free of dust.&lt;/p>&lt;/part>
  &lt;/part>
&lt;/control></tagging>
              <p>The <src>position</src> is <code>after</code> so both elements inside
                  <src>add</src> are added after (not inside) the target element. Since the target
                element is inside another <tgt>part</tgt> in the control, the new additions appear
                there as well.</p>
              <p>Note that the result in this case will be schema-invalid since a <tgt>prop</tgt>
                may not occur directly following a <tgt>part</tgt>. A better result can be obtained
                (a better target may be defined) by using two <src>add</src> directives, to insert
                the new <tgt>prop</tgt> separately
                before any <tgt>part</tgt> elements in the target.</p>
            </mapping>
          </section>
          <section>
            <head>Usage of <src>add</src> directives modifying controls inside controls</head>
            <p>OSCAL supports control extensions inside controls in the form of <src>control</src>
              elements inside <src>control</src> elements. Because the semantics of the
                <src>add</src> directive target any (element) contents of controls, they can be used
              to target these control extensions for modification as well as other contents.</p>
            <p>Because such a control can already be modified using implicit bindings, it is
              recommended that they not be targeted with explicit bindings. Using an implicit
              binding supports more robust alteration since contents in the target can be ordered
              properly by the resolution processor. <revisit>XXX can we guarantee valid results here
                and do we have to specify a sort/order?</revisit> However, it is not an error to
              target control elements in this way, manipulating them in the same way as other
              targets may be manipulated.</p>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section id="remove-directive">
          <head>Removing contents from controls</head>
          <p>Contents inside controls can be removed from them in catalog targets. In combination
            with adding new contents, this feature can be used to edit controls as well as amend
            them.</p>
          <p>A <src>remove</src> directive inside an <src>alter</src> directive identifies an
            element or set of elements inside a control to be removed. It does this using any of
            four flags:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>
              <p><src>@id-ref</src>, like <src>add/@id-ref</src>, matches an element by its
                  <src>@id</src> value.</p>
              <p>Because <src>@id</src> values are unique, the remove directive will remove only a
                single element.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p><src>@name-ref</src> keys to the <src>@name</src> attribute on any element inside
                the control.</p>
              <p>Any element inside the control with the assigned <src>name</src>, is removed.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p><src>@class-ref</src> keys to the <src>@class</src> attribute on any element inside
                the control. All elements with matching <src>class</src> are removed.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p><src>@item-name</src> keys to the element or property name; for example,
                  <code>&lt;remove item-name='prop'/></code> has the effect of removing all
                  <src>prop</src> elements from inside the control. <revisit>(NB: what about in JSON
                  where names are often group names? Can we support removal by item
                name?)</revisit></p>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <p>These are examined in the order given here; the first one that appears is used. Thus a
            remove directive with both a <src>name-ref</src> and a <src>class-ref</src>, uses only
            the <src>name-ref</src>. <revisit>(Or should the effect be cumulative?)</revisit></p>
          <p>Unlike an <src>add</src> directive, a <src>remove</src> may not be bound implicitly to
            the control; its binding, to contents inside the control, must be explicit.</p>
          <p>To remove an control, simply avoid selecting it into the profile, or exclude it
            specifically using <src>import/exclude</src>.</p>
          <p>As with <src>add</src>, a remove that targets any element outside the control, is
            inoperative. Similarly, a remove directive that indicates that all <tgt>prop</tgt>
            elements should be removed from the target catalog, applies only to <src>prop</src></p>
        </section>
        <section>
          <head>Implicit alterations</head>
          <p>Finally some alterations are made automatically.</p>
          <p>For example, <src>link</src> elements in source data representing cross-references in a
            catalog, may no longer be effective in catalogs produced from profiles, which have not
            included the elements (controls or other) to which the links refer.</p>
          <p><revisit>Either: expand the links to refer back to the source catalogs; or remove the
              links.</revisit></p>
          <p><revisit>Note: we could also expand links to point back to the (resolved) source,
              particularly if it is described in back-matter as a resource...</revisit></p>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="anyphase">
      <head>Operations irrespective of phase</head>
      <p>In addition to selecting, merging and modifying, certainl operations
        are conducted in profile resolution that occur irrespective of phases,
        that is in any profile resolution. These include rewriting the profile
        metadata into the resolved baseline (catalog), and filtering and
        rewriting back matter.</p>
      <section id="metadata-rewrite">
        <head>Metadata in the resolved (baseline) catalog</head>
      </section>
      <section id="back-matter-rewrite">
        <head>Back matter in the resolved (baseline) catalog</head>
        <p><tgt>back-matter</tgt> in the result is produced by combining all
          elements within <src>back-matter</src> in all source catalogs, with
          the <src>back-matter</src> in the input profile. Since catalog
          resolution is defined to operate recursively, when profiles import
          profiles, the back matter to be merged is defined by the resolution of
          the imported profile. These elements are combined in order and
          filtered according to the following:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p><src>resource</src> elements copied from imported baseline into a
              resolved catalog (result baseline) are preserved as is, with no
              modification. New resources can be added in a profile by including
              them in its <src>back-matter</src>, but resources cannot be
              targeted for modification. Resources either propagated from source
              catalogs, or included in the importing catalog, are treated the
              same for these purposes.</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>In the result catalog, <tgt>resource</tgt> data objects are given
              in the order they occur in the imported baselines, with the
              baselines given in imported order, and the importing profiles
              .</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>Where <term>node identity</term> can be established between
                <src>resource</src> elements, only the <em>last</em> of the
              duplicate resources is included, within the given total order of
              baselines and resources within those baselines, or if a
                <xpath>prop[@name='keep']</xpath> with value <code>always</code>
              is given on any such <src>resource</src>, the last of these, as
              noted below. That is, each imported catalog or baseline overrides
              any imported before it, while a profile's own resources are
              preferred (as coming last).</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>However, resources are discarded if they are not designated as
              the target of any link (<term>link</term> or <term>a</term>
              element) somewhere in the metadata or body of the resulting
              resolved catalog, by means of an ID reference taking the form of
              the reference's <tgt>id</tgt> value prepended with <code>#</code>,
              with the following exception:</p>
            <ul>
              <li>
                <p>Any <src>resource</src> given in either an imported catalog
                  (baseline), or in the <src>back-matter </src>of the soruce
                  profile, is kept (appears in the result) if it is marked in
                  source with a <src>prop</src> element whose <src>@name</src>
                  is given as <code>keep</code> and whose value is
                    <code>always</code>.</p>
                <p>Within a group of <src>resource</src> objects considered to
                  be identical, this property (<src>prop</src> element) given on
                  any member has the effect of excluding from the group, any
                  that do not. In other words, only the resources marked as
                    <q>always keep</q> with that identity, are selected from,
                  and the last of these (only) is propagated.</p>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>Marking a resource as <code>name='keep'</code> and value
                <code>always</code> thus has a couple of uses:</p>
            <ul>
              <li>
                <p>Placing such a property on a resource in a catalog, has the
                  effect of ensuring it will always appear in the baseline
                  produced by any profile importing that catalog, even if
                  nothing links to the resource. This version of the resource
                  will also be the one copied, unless a later-imported catalog
                  or importing profile offers its own version marked to
                    <q>always keep</q>.</p>
              </li>
              <li>
                <p>Placing such a property on a resource in a profile, ensures
                  both that the resource appears (even if not cross-referenced)
                  in the resulting baseline catalog, and that its version is
                  used, unless when imported into another profile, in which case
                  it may be overridden by another one (also marked as always
                  keep).</p>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <tagging whose="target_catalog">&lt;resource id="fedramp-1">
   &lt;title>FedRAMP Applicable Laws and Regulations&lt;/title>
   &lt;prop name="keep">always&lt;/prop>
   &lt;prop name="conformity" ns="https://fedramp.gov/ns/oscal">fedramp-citations&lt;/prop>
   &lt;rlink href="https://www.fedramp.gov/assets/resources/templates/SSP-A12-FedRAMP-Laws-and-Regulations-Template.xlsx"/>
/resource> </tagging>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="null-profile">
    <head>Null profile</head>
    <p>A <term>null profile</term> is a profile that imports a catalog and selects all its controls
      without modification. A truly <q>null</q> profile – that is, with only an import and nothing
      else – does not return its imported catalog unchanged. But the changes it makes can be useful.
      This makes a null profile or its <term>near-null</term> variants, as described in this
      section, potentially useful for catalog management, design and use, as described in this
      section.</p>
    <section id="all-null">
      <head>Importing and nothing else</head>
      <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile>
  &lt;metadata>...&lt;/metadata>
  &lt;import href="catalog.xml"/>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
      <p>In the target, the catalog group structure and all hierarchy is removed; its controls are
        all returned in sequence. Any loose parameters in the catalog not referenced in a control,
        are dropped.</p>
      <p>This is the same as</p>
      <tagging whose="source_profile">&lt;profile>
  &lt;metadata>...&lt;/metadata>
  &lt;import href="catalog.xml">
    &lt;include>
      &lt;all/>
    &lt;/include>
  &lt;/import>
  &lt;merge>
    &lt;combine method="keep"/>
  &lt;/merge>
&lt;/profile></tagging>
    </section>
    <section>
      <head>all/with-child-controls='no'</head>
      <p>The same, except that only top-level controls are included, not descendants.</p>
      <p><revisit>unit test this</revisit></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <head>including merge directives</head>
      <p>Using merge <src>as-is='true'</src>, the grouping hierarchy of a source catalog can be
        reflected in the target.</p>
      <p>This enables a near-null profile to define a normalization or cleanup pass on a catalog, as
        it will have the result of removing dangling references and orphan parameters, without
        otherwise affecting controls.</p>
      <p><revisit>unit test this too, especially with more than two levels of control hierarchy as
          well as groups</revisit></p>
      <p><revisit>unit test this</revisit></p>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <head>Options</head>
    <p>For conformance, an OSCAL processor must deliver results of profile processing, in a basic
      configuration, exactly as described in these specifications with no elaboration.</p>
    <p>Conformance does not preclude providing additional features, however, including elaborated
      outputs, in an optional mode. Such features could include offering warning or process
      exception handling (appropriate to workflow) not described here; outputs provided with
      comments or extra structure to support tracing or analytics; or <q>gateway</q> or
        <q>Draconian</q> modes that would provide user assistance or refuse to deliver results for
      inputs considered erroneous in a workflow.</p>
  </section>
    <section id="tools-utlities">
    <head>Profile tools and utilities</head>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>rendering - showing both unresolved (raw) and resolved profiles</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>editing / integrity checking</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>rewriting/normalization</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>diffing</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>deriving a profile as the delta of two catalogs (<q>base</q> and <q>tailored</q>)</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </section>
  </SPECIFICATION>