<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Layers and Models Reference on OSCAL</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/documentation/schema/</link><description>Recent content in Layers and Models Reference on OSCAL</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/documentation/schema/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>OSCAL Model Overview</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/documentation/schema/overview/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/documentation/schema/overview/</guid><description>OSCAL is organized in a series of layers that each provide a set of models.
A model represents a information structure supporting a specific operational purpose or concept.
Each model is comprised of information structures that form an information model for each OSCAL model. This information model is then bound to multiple serialization formats (i.e., XML, JSON, YAML), which represent a concrete data model. Thus, a data model that defines how to represent an OSCAL information model in a serialized format.</description></item><item><title>OSCAL Data Types</title><link>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/documentation/schema/datatypes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/documentation/schema/datatypes/</guid><description>The OSCAL models share a set of data type primitives. These data types are documented in the following sections.
Simple Data types empty This data type indicates that the model information element contains no value content, but may contain other structured information elements.
In XML, this may represent an element without text content.
In JSON, this may represent an object with labels corresponding to other child information elements, but no label corresponding to a text value.</description></item></channel></rss>