<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../build/metaschema-xslt/src/validate/metaschema-composition-check.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- OSCAL CATALOG METASCHEMA -->
<!-- validate with XSD and Schematron (linked) -->
<!DOCTYPE METASCHEMA [
   <!ENTITY allowed-values-control-group-property-name SYSTEM "./shared-constraints/allowed-values-control-group-property-name.ent">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="metaschema-author.css"?>
<METASCHEMA
        xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/metaschema/1.0" abstract="yes">
        <schema-name>OSCAL Control Catalog Format -- Common Models</schema-name>
        <schema-version>1.2.0</schema-version>
        <short-name>oscal-control-common</short-name>
        <namespace>http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0</namespace>
        <json-base-uri>http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal</json-base-uri>
        <import href="oscal_metadata_metaschema.xml"/>
        <!-- ######################################## -->
        <!-- # Part Assembly and related constructs # -->
        <!-- ######################################## -->
        <define-assembly name="part">
                <formal-name>Part</formal-name>
                <description>An annotated, markup-based textual element of a control's or catalog group's definition, or a child of another part.</description>
                <define-flag name="id" as-type="token">
                        <!-- This is an id because the identifier is intended to be human-readable. -->
                        <formal-name>Part Identifier</formal-name>
                        <!-- Identifier Declaration -->
                        <description>A unique identifier for the part.</description>
                        <prop name="value-type" value="identifier"/>
                        <prop name="identifier-type" value="human-oriented"/>
                        <prop name="identifier-uniqueness" value="instance"/>
                        <prop name="identifier-scope" value="cross-instance"/>
                        <prop name="identifier-persistence" value="per-subject"/>
                        <remarks>
                                <p>While a part is not required to have an id, it is often desirable for an identifier to be provided, which allows the part to be referenced elsewhere in OSCAL document instances. For this reason, it is RECOMMENDED to provide a part identifier.</p>
                        </remarks>
                </define-flag>
                <define-flag name="name" as-type="token" required="yes">
                        <formal-name>Part Name</formal-name>
                        <description>A textual label that uniquely identifies the part's semantic type, which exists in a value space qualified by the <code>ns</code>.</description>
                </define-flag>
                <define-flag name="ns" as-type="uri" default="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal">
                        <formal-name>Part Namespace</formal-name>
                        <description>An optional namespace qualifying the part's <code>name</code>. This allows different organizations to associate distinct semantics with the same name.</description>
                        <remarks>
                                <p>This value must be an <a href="https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/concepts/uri-use/#absolute-uri">absolute URI</a> that serves as a <a href="https://pages.nist.gov/OSCAL/concepts/uri-use/#use-as-a-naming-system-identifier">naming system identifier</a>.</p>
                                <p>When a <code>ns</code> is not provided, its value should be assumed to be <code>http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal</code> and the name should be a name defined by the associated OSCAL model.</p>
                        </remarks>
                </define-flag>
                <define-flag name="class" as-type="token">
                        <formal-name>Part Class</formal-name>
                        <description>An optional textual providing a sub-type or characterization of the part's <code>name</code>, or a category to which the part belongs.</description>
                        <remarks>
                                <p>One use of this flag is to distinguish or discriminate between the semantics of multiple parts of the same control with the same <code>name</code> and <code>ns</code> (since even within a given namespace it can be useful to overload a name).</p>
                                <p>A <code>class</code> can be used in validation rules to express extra constraints over named items of a specific <code>class</code> value.</p>
                                <p>A <code>class</code> can also be used in an OSCAL profile as a means to target an alteration to control content.</p>
                        </remarks>
                </define-flag>
                <model>
                        <define-field name="title" as-type="markup-line">
                                <formal-name>Part Title</formal-name>
                                <description>An optional name given to the part, which may be used by a tool for display and navigation.</description>
                        </define-field>
                        <assembly ref="property" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                <group-as name="props" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        </assembly>
                        <define-field name="prose" as-type="markup-multiline" in-xml="UNWRAPPED">
                                <formal-name>Part Text</formal-name>
                                <description>Permits multiple paragraphs, lists, tables etc.</description>
                        </define-field>
                        <assembly ref="part" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                <group-as name="parts" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        </assembly>
                        <assembly ref="link" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                <group-as name="links" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        </assembly>
                        <!-- <any/> -->
                </model>
                <constraint>
                        <allowed-values id="oscal-part-prop-name" target="prop[has-oscal-namespace('http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal')]/@name">
            &allowed-values-control-group-property-name;
                        </allowed-values>
                </constraint>
                <remarks>
                        <p>A <code>part</code> provides for logical partitioning of prose, and can be thought of as a grouping structure (e.g., section). A <code>part</code> can have child parts allowing for arbitrary nesting of prose content (e.g., statement hierarchy). A <code>part</code> can contain <code>prop</code> objects that allow for enriching prose text with structured name/value information.</p>
                        <p>A <code>part</code> can be assigned an optional <code>id</code>, which allows references to this part from within a catalog, or within an instance of another OSCAL model that has a need to reference the part. Examples of where part referencing is used in OSCAL include:</p>
                        <ul>
                                    <li>Referencing a part by id to tailor (make modifications to) a control statement in a profile.</li>
                                    <li>Referencing a control statement represented by a part in a system security plan implemented-requirement where a statement-level response is desired.</li>
                        </ul>
                        <p>Use of <code>part</code> and <code>prop</code> provides for a wide degree of extensibility within the OSCAL catalog model. The optional <code>ns</code> provides a means to qualify a part's <code>name</code>, allowing for organization-specific vocabularies to be defined with clear semantics. Any organization that extends OSCAL in this way should consistently assign a <code>ns</code> value that represents the organization, making a given namespace qualified <code>name</code> unique to that organization. This allows the combination of <code>ns</code> and <code>name</code> to always be unique and unambiguous, even when mixed with extensions from other organizations. Each organization is responsible for governance of their own extensions, and is strongly encouraged to publish their extensions as standards to their user community. If no <code>ns</code> is provided, the name is expected to be in the "OSCAL" namespace.</p>
                        <p>To ensure a <code>ns</code> is unique to an organization and naming conflicts are avoided, a URI containing a DNS or other globally defined organization name should be used. For example, if FedRAMP and DoD both extend OSCAL, FedRAMP will use the <code>ns</code> <code>http://fedramp.gov/ns/oscal</code>, while DoD might use the <code>ns</code> <code>https://defense.gov</code> for any organization specific <code>name</code>.</p>
                        <p>Tools that process OSCAL content are not required to interpret unrecognized OSCAL extensions; however, OSCAL compliant tools should not modify or remove unrecognized extensions, unless there is a compelling reason to do so, such as data sensitivity.</p>
                </remarks>
                <example>
                        <description>Multiple Parts with Different Organization-Specific Names.</description>
                        <part xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0" name="statement" id="statement-A">
                                <part ns="http://fedramp.gov/ns/oscal" name="status" id="statement-A-FedRAMP">A requirement specific to FedRAMP stakeholders.</part>
                                <part ns="https://defense.gov" name="status" id="statement-A-DoD">A requirement specific to the Department of Defense stakeholders.</part>
                        </part>
                </example>
        </define-assembly>

        <!-- ############################################# -->
        <!-- # Parameter Assembly and related constructs # -->
        <!-- ############################################# -->
        <!-- continue here -->
        <define-assembly name="parameter">
                <formal-name>Parameter</formal-name>
                <description>Parameters provide a mechanism for the dynamic assignment of value(s) in a control.</description>
                <use-name>param</use-name>
                <define-flag name="id" as-type="token" required="yes">
                        <!-- This is an id because the identifier is intended to be human-readable. -->
                        <formal-name>Parameter Identifier</formal-name>
                        <description>A unique identifier for the parameter.</description>
                        <prop name="value-type" value="identifier"/>
                        <prop name="identifier-type" value="human-oriented"/>
                        <prop name="identifier-uniqueness" value="instance"/>
                        <prop name="identifier-scope" value="cross-instance"/>
                        <prop name="identifier-persistence" value="per-subject"/>
                </define-flag>
                <!-- TODO: What is the semantics of class here? -->
                <define-flag name="class" as-type="token">
                        <formal-name>Parameter Class</formal-name>
                        <description>A textual label that provides a characterization of the type,
                                purpose, use or scope of the parameter.</description>
                        <remarks>
                                <p>A <code>class</code> can be used in validation rules to express extra constraints over named items of a specific <code>class</code> value.</p>
                        </remarks>
                </define-flag>
                <define-flag name="depends-on" as-type="token" deprecated="1.0.1">
                        <formal-name>Depends on</formal-name>
                        <description><strong>(deprecated)</strong> Another parameter invoking this one. This construct has been deprecated and should not be used.</description>
                </define-flag>
                <model>
                        <assembly ref="property" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                <group-as name="props" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        </assembly>
                        <!-- CHANGE: relative order in sequence -->
                        <assembly ref="link" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                <group-as name="links" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        </assembly>
                        <define-field name="label" as-type="markup-line">
                                <formal-name>Parameter Label</formal-name>
                                <description>A short, placeholder name for the parameter, which can be used as a substitute for a <code>value</code> if no value is assigned.</description>
                                <remarks>
                                       <p>The label value is intended use when rendering a parameter in generated documentation or a user interface when a parameter is referenced. Note that labels are not required to be distinctive, which means that parameters within the same control may have the same label.</p>
                                </remarks>
                        </define-field>
                        <define-field name="usage" as-type="markup-multiline" in-xml="WITH_WRAPPER">
                                <formal-name>Parameter Usage Description</formal-name>
                                <description>Describes the purpose and use of a
                                        parameter.</description>
                        </define-field>
                        <assembly ref="parameter-constraint" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                <use-name>constraint</use-name>
                                <group-as name="constraints" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        </assembly>
                        <assembly ref="parameter-guideline" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                <use-name>guideline</use-name>
                                <group-as name="guidelines" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        </assembly>
                        <choice>
                                <field ref="parameter-value" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                        <use-name>value</use-name>
                                        <group-as name="values" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                                        <remarks>
                                                <p>A set of values provided in a catalog can be redefined in OSCAL's <code>profile</code> or <code>system-security-plan</code> models.</p>
                                        </remarks>
                                </field>
                                <assembly ref="parameter-selection">
                                        <use-name>select</use-name>
                                        <remarks>
                                                <p>The OSCAL parameter <code>value</code> construct can be used to prescribe a specific parameter value in a catalog or profile. In cases where a prescriptive value is not possible in a catalog or profile, it may be possible to constrain the set of possible values to a few options. Use of <code>select</code> in a parameter instead of <code>value</code> is a way of defining value options that <strong>may</strong> be set.</p>
                                                <p>A set of allowed parameter values expressed as a set of options which may be selected. These options constrain the permissible values that may be selected for the containing parameter. When the value assignment is made, such as in an OSCAL profile or system security plan, the actual selected value can be examined to determine if it matches one of the permissible choices for the parameter value.</p>
                                                <p>When the value of <code>how-many</code> is set to "one-or-more", multiple values may be assigned reflecting more than one choice.</p>
                                        </remarks>
                                </assembly>
                        </choice>
                        <field ref="remarks" in-xml="WITH_WRAPPER"/>
                </model>
                <constraint>
                        <allowed-values id="oscal-parameter-prop-name" target="prop[has-oscal-namespace('http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal')]/@name">
                                &allowed-values-control-group-property-name;
                                <enum value="alt-label">An alternate to the value provided by the parameter's label. This will typically be qualified by a class.</enum>
                        </allowed-values>
                        <allowed-values id="oscal-rmf-parameter-prop-name" target="prop[has-oscal-namespace('http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/rmf')]/@name">
                                <enum value="aggregates">The parent parameter provides an
                                        aggregation of two or more other parameters, each described
                                        by this property.</enum>
                        </allowed-values>
                        <expect id="oscal-parameter-depends-on-deprecated" target="." test="not(exists(@depends-on))">
                                <message>depends-on is deprecated</message>
                        </expect>
                </constraint>
                <remarks>
                        <p>In a catalog, a parameter is typically used as a placeholder for the future assignment of a parameter value, although the OSCAL model allows for the direct assignment of a value if desired by the control author. The <code>value</code> may be optionally used to specify one or more values. If no value is provided, then it is expected that the value will be provided at the Profile or Implementation layer.</p>
                        <p>A parameter can include a variety of metadata options that support the future solicitation of one or more values. A <code>label</code> provides a textual placeholder that can be used in a tool to solicit parameter value input, or to display in catalog documentation. The <code>desc</code> provides a short description of what the parameter is used for, which can be used in tooling to help a user understand how to use the parameter. A <code>constraint</code> can be used to provide criteria for the allowed values. A <code>guideline</code> provides a recommendation for the use of a parameter.</p>
                </remarks>
        </define-assembly>

        <define-assembly name="parameter-constraint">
                <formal-name>Constraint</formal-name>
                <description>A formal or informal expression of a constraint or test.</description>
                <model>
                        <define-field name="description" as-type="markup-multiline" in-xml="WITH_WRAPPER">
                                <formal-name>Constraint Description</formal-name>
                                <description>A textual summary of the constraint to be applied.</description>
                        </define-field>
                        <define-assembly name="test" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                <formal-name>Constraint Test</formal-name>
                                <description>A test expression which is expected to be evaluated by a tool.</description>
                                <group-as name="tests" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                                <model>
                                        <define-field name="expression" as-type="string" min-occurs="1">
                                                <formal-name>Constraint test</formal-name>
                                                <description>A formal (executable) expression of a
                                                  constraint.</description>
                                        </define-field>
                                        <field ref="remarks" in-xml="WITH_WRAPPER"/>
                                </model>
                        </define-assembly>
                </model>
        </define-assembly>
        <define-assembly name="parameter-guideline">
                <formal-name>Guideline</formal-name>
                <description>A prose statement that provides a recommendation for the use of a parameter.</description>
                <model>
                        <define-field name="prose" as-type="markup-multiline" in-xml="UNWRAPPED" min-occurs="1">
                                <formal-name>Guideline Text</formal-name>
                                <description>Prose permits multiple paragraphs, lists, tables etc.</description>
                        </define-field>
                </model>
        </define-assembly>

        <define-field name="parameter-value">
                <formal-name>Parameter Value</formal-name>
                <description>A parameter value or set of values.</description>
        </define-field>

        <define-assembly name="parameter-selection">
                <formal-name>Selection</formal-name>
                <description>Presenting a choice among alternatives.</description>
                <define-flag name="how-many" as-type="token">
                        <formal-name>Parameter Cardinality</formal-name>
                        <description>Describes the number of selections that must occur. Without this setting, only one value should be assumed to be permitted.</description>
                        <constraint>
                                <allowed-values id="oscal-parameter-how-many-type">
                                        <enum value="one">Only one value is permitted.</enum>
                                        <enum value="one-or-more">One or more values are permitted.</enum>
                                </allowed-values>
                        </constraint>
                </define-flag>
                <model>
                        <define-field name="choice" as-type="markup-line" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                <formal-name>Choice</formal-name>
                                <description>A value selection among several such
                                        options.</description>
                                <json-value-key>value</json-value-key>
                                <group-as name="choice" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        </define-field>
                </model>
                <remarks>
                        <p>A set of parameter value choices, that may be picked from to set the parameter value.</p>
                </remarks>
        </define-assembly>
        <!-- ############################## -->
        <!-- # Control-related constructs # -->
        <!-- ############################## -->
        <define-flag name="control-id" as-type="token">
                <formal-name>Control Identifier Reference</formal-name>
                <!-- Identifier Reference -->
                <description>A reference to a control with a corresponding <code>id</code> value. When referencing an externally defined <code>control</code>, the <code>Control Identifier Reference</code> must be used in the context of the external / imported OSCAL instance (e.g., uri-reference).</description>
                <prop name="value-type" value="identifier-reference"/>
                <prop name="identifier-type" value="human-oriented"/>
                <prop name="identifier-scope" value="cross-instance"/>
        </define-flag>
        <define-assembly name="include-all">
                <formal-name>Include All</formal-name>
                <description>Include all controls from the imported catalog or profile resources.</description>
                <remarks>
                        <p>This element provides an alternative to calling controls individually from a catalog.</p>
                </remarks>
        </define-assembly>
</METASCHEMA>
