<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../build/metaschema/toolchains/xslt-M4/validate/metaschema-composition-check.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE METASCHEMA [
   <!ENTITY allowed-values-control-group-property-name SYSTEM "./shared-constraints/allowed-values-control-group-property-name.ent">
]>
<METASCHEMA xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/metaschema/1.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/metaschema/1.0 ../../build/metaschema/toolchains/xslt-M4/validate/metaschema.xsd">
      <schema-name>OSCAL Profile Model</schema-name>
      <schema-version>1.0.0</schema-version>
      <short-name>oscal-profile</short-name>
      <namespace>http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/1.0</namespace>
      <json-base-uri>http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal</json-base-uri>
      <remarks>
            <p>A profile designates a selection and configuration of controls from one or more catalogs, along with a series of operations over them. The topmost element in the OSCAL profile XML schema is <code>profile</code>.</p>
      </remarks>

      <import href="oscal_metadata_metaschema.xml"/>
      <import href="oscal_control-common_metaschema.xml"/>

      <define-assembly name="profile">
            <formal-name>Profile</formal-name>
            <description>Each OSCAL profile is defined by a Profile element</description>
            <root-name>profile</root-name>
            <define-flag name="uuid" as-type="uuid" required="yes">
                  <formal-name>Profile Universally Unique Identifier</formal-name>
                  <!-- Identifier Declaration -->
                  <description>A <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#machine-oriented">machine-oriented</a>, <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#globally-unique">globally unique</a> identifier with <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#cross-instance">cross-instance</a> scope that can be used to reference this profile elsewhere in <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#profile-identifiers">this or other OSCAL instances</a>. The locally defined <em>UUID</em> of the <code>profile</code> can be used to reference the data item locally or globally (e.g., in an imported OSCAL instance).This identifier should be assigned <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#consistency">per-subject</a>, which means it should be consistently used to identify the same profile across revisions of the document.</description>
            </define-flag>
            <model>
                  <assembly ref="metadata" min-occurs="1"/>
                  <assembly ref="import" min-occurs="1" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <group-as name="imports" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </assembly>
                  <assembly ref="merge"/>
                  <assembly ref="modify"/>
                  <assembly ref="back-matter"/>
            </model>
            <remarks>
                  <p>An OSCAL document that describes a tailoring of controls from one or more catalogs, with possible modification of multiple controls. It provides mechanisms by which controls may be selected (<code>import</code>), merged or (re)structured (<code>merge</code>), and amended (<code>modify</code>). OSCAL profiles may select subsets of controls, set parameter values for them in application, and even adjust the representation of controls as given in and by a catalog. They may also serve as sources for further modification in and by other profiles, that import them.</p>
                  <p>See the <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/">Concepts - Identifier Use</a> page for additional information regarding this identifier's uniqueness and scope.</p>
            </remarks>
      </define-assembly>
      <define-assembly name="import">
            <formal-name>Import resource</formal-name>
            <description>The <code>import</code> designates a catalog, profile, or other resource to be included (referenced and potentially modified) by this profile. The import also identifies which controls to select using the <code>include-all</code>, <code>include-controls</code>, and <code>exclude-controls</code> directives.</description>
            <define-flag name="href" as-type="uri-reference" required="yes">
                  <formal-name>Catalog or Profile Reference</formal-name>
                  <description>A resolvable URL reference to the base catalog or profile that this profile is tailoring.</description>
                  <remarks>
                        <p>The value of the <code>href</code> can be an internet resource, or a local reference using a fragment e.g. #fragment that points to a <code>back-matter</code>
                              <code>resource</code> in the same document.</p>
                        <!-- TODO: Add a link to "within the scope of the containing OSCAL document" to point to documentation of identification scopes" -->
                        <p>If a local reference using a fragment is used, this will be indicated by a fragment "#" followed by an identifier which references an identified <code>resource</code> in the document's <code>back-matter</code> or another object that is within the scope of the containing OSCAL document.</p>
                        <p>If an internet resource is used, the <code>href</code> value will be an absolute or relative URL pointing to the location of the referenced resource. A relative URL will be resolved relative to the location of the document containing the link.</p>
                  </remarks>
            </define-flag>
            <model>
                  <choice>
                        <assembly ref="include-all" min-occurs="1">
                              <remarks>
                                    <p>Identifies that all controls are to be included from the imported catalog or profile.</p>
                              </remarks>
                        </assembly>
                        <assembly ref="select-control-by-id" min-occurs="1" max-occurs="unbounded">
                              <use-name>include-controls</use-name>
                              <group-as name="include-controls" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                              <remarks>
                                    <p>Identifies a subset of controls to import from the referenced catalog or profile by control identifier or match pattern.</p>
                              </remarks>
                        </assembly>
                  </choice>
                  <assembly ref="select-control-by-id" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <use-name>exclude-controls</use-name>
                        <group-as name="exclude-controls" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        <remarks>
                              <p>Identifies which controls to exclude, or eliminate, from the set of included controls by control identifier or match pattern.</p>
                        </remarks>
                  </assembly>
            </model>
            <remarks>
                  <p>A profile must be based on an existing OSCAL catalog or another OSCAL profile. An <code>import</code> indicates such a source whose controls are to be included (referenced and modified) in a profile. This source will either be a catalog whose controls are given (<q>by value</q>), or a profile with its own control imports.</p>
                  <p>The contents of the <code>import</code> element indicate which controls from the source will be included. Controls from the source catalog or profile may be either selected, using the <code>include-all</code> or <code>include-controls</code> directives, or de-selected (using an <code>exclude-controls</code> directive).</p>
            </remarks>
            <example>
                  <import xmlns="http://csrc.nist.gov/ns/oscal/example" href="catalog.xml">
                        <include-all/>
                  </import>
            </example>
      </define-assembly>
      <define-assembly name="merge">
            <formal-name>Merge controls</formal-name>
            <description>A Merge element provides structuring directives that drive how controls are organized after resolution.</description>
            <model>
                  <define-assembly name="combine">
                        <formal-name>Combination rule</formal-name>
                        <description>A Combine element defines whether and how to combine multiple (competing) versions of the same control</description>
                        <define-flag name="method" as-type="string">
                              <formal-name>Combination method</formal-name>
                              <description>How clashing controls should be handled</description>
                              <constraint>
                                    <allowed-values>
                                          <enum value="use-first">Use the first definition - the first control with a given ID is used; subsequent ones are discarded</enum>
                                          <enum value="merge">**(deprecated)** **(unspecified)** Merge - controls with the same ID are combined</enum>
                                          <enum value="keep">Keep - controls with the same ID are kept, retaining the clash</enum>
                                    </allowed-values>
                              </constraint>
                        </define-flag>
                        <constraint>
                              <expect id="expect-profile-combine-method-merge-unused" target="." test="not(exists(combine[@method='merge']))"/>
                        </constraint>
                        <remarks>
                              <p>Whenever combining controls from multiple (import) pathways, an issue arises of what to do with clashing invocations (multiple competing versions of a control). </p>
                              <p>This setting permits a profile designer to apply a rule for the resolution of such cases. In a well-designed profile, such collisions would ordinarily be avoided, but this setting can be useful for defining what to do when it occurs.</p>
                        </remarks>
                  </define-assembly>
                  <choice>
                        <define-assembly name="flat" min-occurs="1">
                              <formal-name>Flat</formal-name>
                              <description>Use the flat structuring method.</description>
                        </define-assembly>
                        <define-field name="as-is" as-type="boolean" min-occurs="1">
                              <formal-name>As-Is Structuring Directive</formal-name>
                              <description>An As-is element indicates that the controls should be structured in resolution as they are structured in their source catalogs. It does not contain any elements or attributes.</description>
                        </define-field>
                        <define-assembly name="custom">
                              <formal-name>Custom grouping</formal-name>
                              <description>A Custom element frames a structure for embedding represented controls in resolution.</description>
                              <model>
                                    <assembly ref="group" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                          <group-as name="groups" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                                    </assembly>
                                    <assembly ref="insert-controls" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                          <group-as name="insert-controls" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                                    </assembly>
                              </model>
                              <remarks>
                                    <p>The <code>custom</code> element represents a custom arrangement or organization of controls in the resolution of a catalog.</p>
                                    <p>While the <code>as-is</code> element provides for a restitution of a control set's organization (in one or more source catalogs), this element permits the definition of an entirely different structure.</p>
                              </remarks>
                        </define-assembly>
                  </choice>
            </model>
            <remarks>
                  <p>The contents of the <code>merge</code> element may be used to <q>reorder</q> or <q>restructure</q> controls by indicating an order and/or structure in resolution.</p>
                  <p>Implicitly, a <code>merge</code> element is also a filter: controls that are included in a profile, but not included (implicitly or explicitly) in the scope of a <code>merge</code> element, will not be merged into (will be dropped) in the resulting resolution.</p>
            </remarks>
      </define-assembly>
      <define-assembly name="group">
            <formal-name>Control group</formal-name>
            <description>A group of (selected) controls or of groups of controls</description>
            <define-flag name="id" as-type="token">
                  <!-- This is an id because the idenfier is assigned and managed externally by humans. -->
                  <formal-name>Group Identifier</formal-name>
                  <!-- Identifier Declaration -->
                  <description>A <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#human-oriented">human-oriented</a>, <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#locally-unique">locally unique</a> identifier with <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#cross-instance">cross-instance</a> scope that can be used to reference this defined group elsewhere in <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#profile-identifiers">this or other OSCAL instances</a>. When referenced from another OSCAL instance, this identifier must be referenced in the context of the containing resource (e.g., import-profile). This id should be assigned <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#consistency">per-subject</a>, which means it should be consistently used to identify the same group across revisions of the document.</description>
            </define-flag>
            <define-flag name="class" as-type="token">
                  <formal-name>Group Class</formal-name>
                  <description>A textual label that provides a sub-type or characterization of the group.</description>
                  <remarks>
                        <p>A <code>class</code> can be used in validation rules to express extra constraints over named items of a specific <code>class</code> value.</p>
                        <p>A <code>class</code> can also be used in an OSCAL profile as a means to target an alteration to control content.</p>
                  </remarks>
            </define-flag>
            <model>
                  <define-field name="title" as-type="markup-line" min-occurs="1">
                        <formal-name>Group Title</formal-name>
                        <description>A name given to the group, which may be used by a tool for display and navigation.</description>
                  </define-field>
                  <assembly ref="parameter" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <group-as name="params" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </assembly>
                  <assembly ref="property" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <group-as name="props" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </assembly>
                  <assembly ref="link" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <group-as name="links" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </assembly>
                  <assembly ref="part" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <group-as name="parts" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </assembly>
                  <choice>
                        <assembly ref="group" max-occurs="unbounded">
                              <group-as name="groups" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        </assembly>
                        <assembly ref="insert-controls" max-occurs="unbounded">
                              <group-as name="insert-controls" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        </assembly>
                  </choice>
            </model>
            <remarks>
                  <p>This construct mirrors the same construct that exists in an OSCAL catalog.</p>
            </remarks>
      </define-assembly>
      <define-assembly name="modify">
            <formal-name>Modify controls</formal-name>
            <description>Set parameters or amend controls in resolution</description>
            <model>
                  <define-assembly name="set-parameter" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <formal-name>Parameter Setting</formal-name>
                        <description>A parameter setting, to be propagated to points of insertion</description>
                        <group-as name="set-parameters" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        <define-flag required="yes" name="param-id" as-type="token">
                              <!-- This is an id because the idenfier is assigned and managed by humans. -->
                              <formal-name>Parameter ID</formal-name>
                              <!-- Identifier Declaration -->
                              <description>A <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#human-oriented">human-oriented</a>, <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#locally-unique">locally unique</a> identifier with <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#cross-instance">cross-instance</a> scope that can be used to reference this defined parameter elsewhere in <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#profile-identifiers">this or other OSCAL instances</a>. When referenced from another OSCAL instance, this identifier must be referenced in the context of the containing resource (e.g., import-profile). This id should be assigned <a href="/concepts/identifier-use/#consistency">per-subject</a>, which means it should be consistently used to identify the same subject across revisions of the document.</description>
                        </define-flag>
                        <define-flag name="class" as-type="token">
                              <formal-name>Parameter Class</formal-name>
                              <description>A textual label that provides a characterization of the parameter.</description>
                              <remarks>
                                    <p>A <code>class</code> can be used in validation rules to express extra constraints over named items of a specific <code>class</code> value.</p>
                              </remarks>
                        </define-flag>
                        <flag ref="depends-on"/>
                        <model>
                              <assembly ref="property" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                    <group-as name="props" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                              </assembly>
                              <assembly ref="link" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                    <group-as name="links" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                              </assembly>
                              <define-field name="label" as-type="markup-line">
                                    <formal-name>Parameter Label</formal-name>
                                    <description>A short, placeholder name for the parameter, which can be used as a substitute for a <code>value</code> if no value is assigned.</description>
                                    <remarks>
                                          <p>The label value should be suitable for inline display in a rendered catalog.</p>
                                    </remarks>
                              </define-field>
                              <define-field name="usage" as-type="markup-multiline" in-xml="WITH_WRAPPER">
                                    <formal-name>Parameter Usage Description</formal-name>
                                    <description>Describes the purpose and use of a parameter</description>
                              </define-field>
                              <assembly ref="parameter-constraint" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                    <use-name>constraint</use-name>
                                    <group-as name="constraints" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                              </assembly>
                              <assembly ref="parameter-guideline" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                    <use-name>guideline</use-name>
                                    <group-as name="guidelines" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                              </assembly>
                              <choice>
                                    <field ref="parameter-value" max-occurs="unbounded">
                                          <use-name>value</use-name>
                                          <group-as name="values" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                                          <remarks>
                                                <p>Used to (re)define a parameter value.</p>
                                          </remarks>
                                    </field>
                                    <assembly ref="parameter-selection">
                                          <use-name>select</use-name>
                                    </assembly>
                              </choice>
                        </model>
                  </define-assembly>
                  <assembly ref="alter" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <group-as name="alters" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </assembly>
            </model>
            <constraint>
                  <is-unique id="unique-profile-modify-set-parameter" target="set-parameter">
                        <key-field target="@param-id"/>
                        <remarks>
                              <p>Since multiple <code>set-parameter</code> entries can be provided, each parameter must be set only once.</p>
                        </remarks>
                  </is-unique>
            </constraint>
            
      </define-assembly>
      <define-assembly name="insert-controls">
            <formal-name>Select controls</formal-name>
            <description>Specifies which controls to use in the containing context.</description>
            <define-flag as-type="token" name="order">
                  <formal-name>Order</formal-name>
                  <description>A designation of how a selection of controls in a profile is to be ordered.</description>
                  <constraint>
                        <allowed-values>
                              <enum value="keep"/>
                              <enum value="ascending"/>
                              <enum value="descending"/>
                        </allowed-values>
                  </constraint>
            </define-flag>
            <model>
                  <choice>
                        <assembly ref="include-all" min-occurs="1"/>
                        <assembly ref="select-control-by-id" min-occurs="1" max-occurs="unbounded">
                              <use-name>include-controls</use-name>
                              <group-as name="include-controls" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        </assembly>
                  </choice>
                  <assembly ref="select-control-by-id" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <use-name>exclude-controls</use-name>
                        <group-as name="exclude-controls" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        <remarks>
                              <p>Identifies which controls to exclude, or eliminate, from the set of matching includes.</p>
                        </remarks>
                  </assembly>
            </model>
            <remarks>
                  <p>To be schema-valid, this element must contain either (but not both) a single <code>include-all</code> directive, or a sequence of <code>include-controls</code> directives.</p>
                  <p>If this directive is not provided, then no controls are to be inserted; i.e., all controls are included explicitly.</p>
            </remarks>
      </define-assembly>

      <define-assembly name="include-all">
            <formal-name>Insert All</formal-name>
            <description>Insert all controls from the imported catalog or profile resources identified in the <code>import</code> directive.</description>
            <remarks>
                  <p>This element provides an alternative to calling controls individually from a catalog.</p>
            </remarks>
      </define-assembly>
      <define-assembly name="select-control-by-id" scope="local">
            <formal-name>Call</formal-name>
            <description>Call a control by its ID</description>
            <flag ref="with-child-controls"/>
            <model>
                  <define-field name="with-id" as-type="token" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <formal-name>Match Controls by Identifier</formal-name>
                        <description></description>
                        <group-as name="with-ids" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </define-field>
                  <define-assembly name="matching" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <formal-name>Match Controls by Pattern</formal-name>
                        <description>Select controls by (regular expression) match on ID</description>
                        <group-as name="matching" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                        <flag ref="pattern"/>
                  </define-assembly>
            </model>
            <remarks>
                  <p>If <code>with-child-controls</code> is <q>yes</q> on the call to a control, no sibling <code>call</code>elements need to be used to call any controls appearing within it. Since generally, this is how control enhancements are represented (as controls within controls), this provides a way to include controls with all their dependent controls (enhancements) without having to call them individually.</p>
            </remarks>
      </define-assembly>
      <define-assembly name="alter">
            <formal-name>Alteration</formal-name>
            <description>An Alter element specifies changes to be made to an included control when a profile is resolved.</description>
            <flag ref="control-id"/>
            <model>
                  <assembly ref="remove" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <group-as name="removes" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </assembly>
                  <assembly ref="add" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <group-as name="adds" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </assembly>
            </model>
            <remarks>
                  <p>Use <code>@control-id</code> to indicate the scope of alteration.</p>
                  <p>It is an error for two <code>alter</code> elements to apply to the same control. In practice, multiple alterations can be applied (together), but it creates confusion.</p>
                  <p>At present, no provision is made for altering many controls at once (for example, to systematically remove properties or add global properties); extending this element to match multiple control IDs could provide for this.</p>
            </remarks>
      </define-assembly>
      <define-assembly name="remove">
            <formal-name>Removal</formal-name>
            <description>Specifies objects to be removed from a control based on specific aspects of the object that must all match.</description>
            <define-flag name="by-name" as-type="token">
                  <formal-name>Reference by (assigned) name</formal-name>
                  <description>Identify items to remove by matching their assigned name</description>
            </define-flag>
            <define-flag name="by-class" as-type="token">
                  <formal-name>Reference by class</formal-name>
                  <description>Identify items to remove by matching their <code>class</code>.</description>
            </define-flag>
            <define-flag name="by-id" as-type="token">
                  <formal-name>Reference by ID</formal-name>
                  <description>Identify items to remove indicated by their <code>id</code>.</description>
            </define-flag>
            <define-flag name="by-item-name" as-type="token">
                  <formal-name>Item Name Reference</formal-name>
                  <description>Identify items to remove by the name of the item's information element name, e.g. <code>title</code> or <code>prop</code></description>
            </define-flag>
            <define-flag name="by-ns" as-type="token">
                  <formal-name>Item Namespace Reference</formal-name>
                  <description>Identify items to remove by the item's <code>ns</code>, which is the namespace associated with a <code>part</code>, or <code>prop</code>.</description>
            </define-flag>
            <remarks>
                  <p>Use <code>name-ref</code>, <code>class-ref</code>, <code>id-ref</code> or <code>generic-identifier</code> to indicate class tokens or ID reference, or the formal name, of the component to be removed or erased from a control, when a catalog is resolved. The control affected is indicated by the pointer on the removal's parent (containing) <code>alter</code> element.</p>
                  <p>To change an element, use <code>remove</code> to remove the element, then <code>add</code> to add it back again with changes.</p>
            </remarks>
      </define-assembly>
      <define-assembly name="add">
            <formal-name>Addition</formal-name>
            <description>Specifies contents to be added into controls, in resolution</description>
            <define-flag name="position" as-type="token">
                  <formal-name>Position</formal-name>
                  <description>Where to add the new content with respect to the targeted element (beside it or inside it)</description>
                  <constraint>
                        <allowed-values>
                              <enum value="before">Preceding the id-ref target</enum>
                              <enum value="after">Following the id-ref target</enum>
                              <enum value="starting">Inside the control or id-ref target, at the start</enum>
                              <enum value="ending">Inside the control or id-ref target, at the end</enum>
                        </allowed-values>
                  </constraint>
            </define-flag>
            <define-flag name="by-id" as-type="token">
                  <formal-name>Reference by ID</formal-name>
                  <description>Target location of the addition.</description>
            </define-flag>
            <model>
                  <define-field name="title" as-type="markup-line">
                        <formal-name>Title Change</formal-name>
                        <description>A name given to the control, which may be used by a tool for display and navigation.</description>
                  </define-field>
                  <assembly ref="parameter" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <!-- CHANGED: "parameters" to "params" -->
                        <group-as name="params" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </assembly>
                  <assembly ref="property" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <group-as name="props" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </assembly>
                  <assembly ref="link" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <group-as name="links" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </assembly>
                  <assembly ref="part" max-occurs="unbounded">
                        <group-as name="parts" in-json="ARRAY"/>
                  </assembly>
            </model>
            <constraint>
                  <!-- CHANGE: added allowed values for a property/@name -->
                  <allowed-values target="prop/@name" allow-other="yes">
            &allowed-values-control-group-property-name;
                  </allowed-values>
            </constraint>
            <remarks>
                  <p>When no <code>id-ref</code> is given, the addition is inserted into the control targeted by the alteration at the start or end as indicated by <code>position</code>. Only <code>position</code> values of "starting" or "ending" are permitted when there is no <code>id-ref</code>.</p>
                  <p><code>id-ref</code>, when given, should indicate, by its ID, an element inside the control to serve as the anchor point for the addition. In this case, <code>position</code> value may be any of the permitted values.</p>
            </remarks>
      </define-assembly>
      <define-flag as-type="token" name="with-child-controls">
            <formal-name>Include contained controls with control</formal-name>
            <description>When a control is included, whether its child (dependent) controls are also included.</description>
            <constraint>
                  <allowed-values>
                        <enum value="yes">Include child controls with an included control.</enum>
                        <enum value="no">When importing a control, only include child controls that are also explicitly called.</enum>
                  </allowed-values>
            </constraint>
      </define-flag>
      <define-flag as-type="string" name="pattern">
            <formal-name>Pattern</formal-name>
            <description>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glob_(programming)">glob expression</a> matching the IDs of one or more controls to be selected.</description>
      </define-flag>
</METASCHEMA>
