<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<catalog xmlns="http://scap.nist.gov/schema/catalog"
    xmlns:xh11d="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/datatypes/"
    xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"    
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://scap.nist.gov/schema/catalog 
        file:../../../../xsd/nist/oscal/2.0/OSCAL.xsd">
    <id>SP800-53</id>
    <name>SP 800-53 rev 4</name>
    <version>4</version>
    <summary>TBD</summary>
    <meta>
        <property name="family" type="xsd:string"/>
        <property name="supplemental-guidance">
            <property name="description" type="xsd:string" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1"/>
            <property name="related" type="xsd:token" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
        </property>
        <property name="withdrawn">
            <property name="incorporated-into" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded" />
        </property>      
        <item>
            <property name="family" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1" />
            <property name="priority" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1" />
            <property name="supplemental-guidance" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1" />
            <property name="withdrawn" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1" />
            <!-- <property name="parameter" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded" /> -->
        </item>
    </meta>

    <items>
        <item>
            <type>control</type>
            <id>AC-1</id>
            <title>ACCESS CONTROL POLICY AND PROCEDURES</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The organization:</description>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-1a.</number>
                    <description>Develops, documents, and disseminates to [Assignment: organization-defined personnel or roles]:</description>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-1a.1.</number>
                        <description>An access control policy that addresses purpose, scope, roles, responsibilities, management commitment, coordination among organizational entities, and compliance; and</description>
                    </statement>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-1a.2.</number>
                        <description>Procedures to facilitate the implementation of the access control policy and associated access controls; and</description>
                    </statement>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-1b.</number>
                    <description>Reviews and updates the current:</description>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-1b.1.</number>
                        <description>Access control policy [Assignment: organization-defined frequency]; and</description>
                    </statement>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-1b.2.</number>
                        <description>Access control procedures [Assignment: organization-defined frequency].</description>
                    </statement>
                </statement>
            </statement>
            <link rel="reference" xml:lang="en-US" href="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#800-12">NIST Special Publication 800-12</link>
            <link rel="reference" xml:lang="en-US" href="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html#800-100">NIST Special Publication 800-100</link>
            <properties>
                <family>ACCESS CONTROL</family>
                <priority>P1</priority>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>This control addresses the establishment of policy and procedures for the effective implementation of selected security controls and control enhancements in the AC family. Policy and procedures reflect applicable federal laws, Executive Orders, directives, regulations, policies, standards, and guidance. Security program policies and procedures at the organization level may make the need for system-specific policies and procedures unnecessary. The policy can be included as part of the general information security policy for organizations or conversely, can be represented by multiple policies reflecting the complex nature of certain organizations. The procedures can be established for the security program in general and for particular information systems, if needed. The organizational risk management strategy is a key factor in establishing policy and procedures.</description>
                    <link rel="related" href="#PM-9"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2</id>
            <title>ACCOUNT MANAGEMENT</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The organization:</description>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2a.</number>
                    <description>Identifies and selects the following types of information system accounts to support organizational missions/business functions: [Assignment: organization-defined information system account types];</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2b.</number>
                    <description>Assigns account managers for information system accounts;</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2c.</number>
                    <description>Establishes conditions for group and role membership;</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2d.</number>
                    <description>Specifies authorized users of the information system, group and role membership, and access authorizations (i.e., privileges) and other attributes (as required) for each account;</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2e.</number>
                    <description>Requires approvals by [Assignment: organization-defined personnel or roles] for requests to create information system accounts;</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2f.</number>
                    <description>Creates, enables, modifies, disables, and removes information system accounts in accordance with [Assignment: organization-defined procedures or conditions];</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2g.</number>
                    <description>Monitors the use of information system accounts;</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2h.</number>
                    <description>Notifies account managers:</description>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-2h.1.</number>
                        <description>When accounts are no longer required;</description>
                    </statement>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-2h.2.</number>
                        <description>When users are terminated or transferred; and</description>
                    </statement>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-2h.3.</number>
                        <description>When individual information system usage or need-to-know changes;</description>
                    </statement>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2i.</number>
                    <description>Authorizes access to the information system based on:</description>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-2i.1.</number>
                        <description>A valid access authorization;</description>
                    </statement>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-2i.2.</number>
                        <description>Intended system usage; and</description>
                    </statement>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-2i.3.</number>
                        <description>Other attributes as required by the organization or associated missions/business functions;</description>
                    </statement>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2j.</number>
                    <description>Reviews accounts for compliance with account management requirements [Assignment: organization-defined frequency]; and</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2k.</number>
                    <description>Establishes a process for reissuing shared/group account credentials (if deployed) when individuals are removed from the group.</description>
                </statement>
            </statement>
            <properties>
                <family>ACCESS CONTROL</family>
                <priority>P1</priority>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Information system account types include, for example, individual, shared, group, system, guest/anonymous, emergency, developer/manufacturer/vendor, temporary, and service. Some of the account management requirements listed above can be implemented by organizational information systems. The identification of authorized users of the information system and the specification of access privileges reflects the requirements in other security controls in the security plan. Users requiring administrative privileges on information system accounts receive additional scrutiny by appropriate organizational personnel (e.g., system owner, mission/business owner, or chief information security officer) responsible for approving such accounts and privileged access. Organizations may choose to define access privileges or other attributes by account, by type of account, or a combination of both. Other attributes required for authorizing access include, for example, restrictions on time-of-day, day-of-week, and point-of-origin. In defining other account attributes, organizations consider system-related requirements (e.g., scheduled maintenance, system upgrades) and mission/business requirements, (e.g., time zone differences, customer requirements, remote access to support travel requirements). Failure to consider these factors could affect information system availability. Temporary and emergency accounts are accounts intended for short-term use. Organizations establish temporary accounts as a part of normal account activation procedures when there is a need for short-term accounts without the demand for immediacy in account activation. Organizations establish emergency accounts in response to crisis situations and with the need for rapid account activation. Therefore, emergency account activation may bypass normal account authorization processes. Emergency and temporary accounts are not to be confused with infrequently used accounts (e.g., local logon accounts used for special tasks defined by organizations or when network resources are unavailable). Such accounts remain available and are not subject to automatic disabling or removal dates. Conditions for disabling or deactivating accounts include, for example: (i) when shared/group, emergency, or temporary accounts are no longer required; or (ii) when individuals are transferred or terminated. Some types of information system accounts may require specialized training.</description>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-3"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-4"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-5"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-6"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-10"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-17"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-19"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-20"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AU-9"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#IA-2"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#IA-4"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#IA-5"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#IA-8"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CM-5"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CM-6"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CM-11"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#MA-3"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#MA-4"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#MA-5"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#PL-4"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#SC-13"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(1)</id>
            <title>AUTOMATED SYSTEM ACCOUNT MANAGEMENT</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The organization employs automated mechanisms to support the management of information system accounts.</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>The use of automated mechanisms can include, for example: using email or text messaging to automatically notify account managers when users are terminated or transferred; using the information system to monitor account usage; and using telephonic notification to report atypical system account usage.</description>
                </supplemental-guidance>                
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(2)</id>
            <title>REMOVAL OF TEMPORARY / EMERGENCY ACCOUNTS</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system automatically [Selection: removes; disables] temporary and emergency accounts after [Assignment: organization-defined time period for each type of account].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>This control enhancement requires the removal of both temporary and emergency accounts automatically after a predefined period of time has elapsed, rather than at the convenience of the systems administrator.</description>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(3)</id>
            <title>DISABLE INACTIVE ACCOUNTS</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system automatically disables inactive accounts after [Assignment: organization-defined time period].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(4)</id>
            <title>AUTOMATED AUDIT ACTIONS</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system automatically audits account creation, modification, enabling, disabling, and removal actions, and notifies [Assignment: organization-defined personnel or roles].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AU-2"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AU-12"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(5)</id>
            <title>INACTIVITY LOGOUT</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The organization requires that users log out when [Assignment: organization-defined time-period of expected inactivity or description of when to log out].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <link rel="related" href="#SC-23"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(6)</id>
            <title>DYNAMIC PRIVILEGE MANAGEMENT</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system implements the following dynamic privilege management capabilities: [Assignment: organization-defined list of dynamic privilege management capabilities].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>In contrast to conventional access control approaches which employ static information system accounts and predefined sets of user privileges, dynamic access control approaches (e.g., service-oriented architectures) rely on run time access control decisions facilitated by dynamic privilege management. While user identities may remain relatively constant over time, user privileges may change more frequently based on ongoing mission/business requirements and operational needs of organizations. Dynamic privilege management can include, for example, the immediate revocation of privileges from users, as opposed to requiring that users terminate and restart their sessions to reflect any changes in privileges. Dynamic privilege management can also refer to mechanisms that change the privileges of users based on dynamic rules as opposed to editing specific user profiles. This type of privilege management includes, for example, automatic adjustments of privileges if users are operating out of their normal work times, or if information systems are under duress or in emergency maintenance situations. This control enhancement also includes the ancillary effects of privilege changes, for example, the potential changes to encryption keys used for communications. Dynamic privilege management can support requirements for information system resiliency.</description>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-16"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(7)</id>
            <title>ROLE-BASED SCHEMES</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The organization:</description>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2(7)(a)</number>
                    <description>Establishes and administers privileged user accounts in accordance with a role-based access scheme that organizes allowed information system access and privileges into roles;</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2(7)(b)</number>
                    <description>Monitors privileged role assignments; and</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2(7)(c)</number>
                    <description>Takes [Assignment: organization-defined actions] when privileged role assignments are no longer appropriate.</description>
                </statement>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Privileged roles are organization-defined roles assigned to individuals that allow those individuals to perform certain security-relevant functions that ordinary users are not authorized to perform. These privileged roles include, for example, key management, account management, network and system administration, database administration, and web administration.</description>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(8)</id>
            <title>DYNAMIC ACCOUNT CREATION</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system creates [Assignment: organization-defined information system accounts] dynamically.</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Dynamic approaches for creating information system accounts (e.g., as implemented within service-oriented architectures) rely on establishing accounts (identities) at run time for entities that were previously unknown. Organizations plan for dynamic creation of information system accounts by establishing trust relationships and mechanisms with the appropriate authorities to validate related authorizations and privileges.</description>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-16"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(9)</id>
            <title>RESTRICTIONS ON USE OF SHARED / GROUP ACCOUNTS</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The organization only permits the use of shared/group accounts that meet [Assignment: organization-defined conditions for establishing shared/group accounts].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(10)</id>
            <title>SHARED / GROUP ACCOUNT CREDENTIAL TERMINATION</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system terminates shared/group account credentials when members leave the group.</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(11)</id>
            <title>USAGE CONDITIONS</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system enforces [Assignment: organization-defined circumstances and/or usage conditions] for [Assignment: organization-defined information system accounts].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Organizations can describe the specific conditions or circumstances under which information system accounts can be used, for example, by restricting usage to certain days of the week, time of day, or specific durations of time.</description>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(12)</id>
            <title>ACCOUNT MONITORING / ATYPICAL USAGE</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The organization:</description>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2(12)(a)</number>
                    <description>Monitors information system accounts for [Assignment: organization-defined atypical usage]; and</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-2(12)(b)</number>
                    <description>Reports atypical usage of information system accounts to [Assignment: organization-defined personnel or roles].</description>
                </statement>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Atypical usage includes, for example, accessing information systems at certain times of the day and from locations that are not consistent with the normal usage patterns of individuals working in organizations.</description>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CA-7"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-2(13)</id>
            <title>DISABLE ACCOUNTS FOR HIGH-RISK INDIVIDUALS</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The organization disables accounts of users posing a significant risk within [Assignment: organization-defined time period] of discovery of the risk.</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-2"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Users posing a significant risk to organizations include individuals for whom reliable evidence or intelligence indicates either the intention to use authorized access to information systems to cause harm or through whom adversaries will cause harm. Harm includes potential adverse impacts to organizational operations and assets, individuals, other organizations, or the Nation. Close coordination between authorizing officials, information system administrators, and human resource managers is essential in order for timely execution of this control enhancement.</description>
                    <link rel="related" href="#PS-4"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control</type>
            <id>AC-3</id>
            <title>ACCESS ENFORCEMENT</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system enforces approved authorizations for logical access to information           and system resources in accordance with applicable access control policies.</description>
            </statement>
            <properties>
                <type>control</type>
                <family>ACCESS CONTROL</family>
                <priority>P1</priority>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Access control policies (e.g., identity-based policies, role-based policies, control matrices, cryptography) control access between active entities or subjects (i.e., users or processes acting on behalf of users) and passive entities or objects (e.g., devices, files, records, domains) in information systems. In addition to enforcing authorized access at the information system level and recognizing that information systems can host many applications and services in support of organizational missions and business operations, access enforcement mechanisms can also be employed at the application and service level to provide increased information security.</description>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-2"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-4"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-5"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-6"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-16"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-17"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-18"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-19"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-20"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-21"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-22"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AU-9"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CM-5"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CM-6"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CM-11"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#MA-3"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#MA-4"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#MA-5"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#PE-3"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-3(1)</id>
            <title>RESTRICTED ACCESS TO PRIVILEGED FUNCTIONS</title>
            <statement>
                <description>[Withdrawn: Incorporated into AC-6].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-3"/>
            <properties>            
                <withdrawn>
                    <incorporated-into>AC-6</incorporated-into>
                </withdrawn>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-3(2)</id>
            <title>DUAL AUTHORIZATION</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system enforces dual authorization for [Assignment: organization-defined privileged commands and/or other organization-defined actions].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-3"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Dual authorization mechanisms require the approval of two authorized individuals in order to execute. Organizations do not require dual authorization mechanisms when immediate responses are necessary to ensure public and environmental safety. Dual authorization may also be known as two-person control.</description>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CP-9"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#MP-6"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-3(3)</id>
            <title>MANDATORY ACCESS CONTROL</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system enforces [Assignment: organization-defined mandatory access control policy] over all subjects and objects where the policy:</description>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-3 (3)(a)</number>
                    <description>Is uniformly enforced across all subjects and objects within the boundary of the information system;</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-3 (3)(b)</number>
                    <description>Specifies that a subject that has been granted access to information is constrained from doing any of the following;</description>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-3 (3)(b)(1)</number>
                        <description>Passing the information to unauthorized subjects or objects;</description>
                    </statement>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-3 (3)(b)(2)</number>
                        <description>Granting its privileges to other subjects;</description>
                    </statement>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-3 (3)(b)(3)</number>
                        <description>Changing one or more security attributes on subjects, objects, the information system, or information system components;</description>
                    </statement>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-3 (3)(b)(4)</number>
                        <description>Choosing the security attributes and attribute values to be associated with newly created or modified objects; or</description>
                    </statement>
                    <statement>
                        <number>AC-3 (3)(b)(5)</number>
                        <description>Changing the rules governing access control; and</description>
                    </statement>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-3 (3)(c)</number>
                    <description>Specifies that [Assignment: organization-defined subjects] may explicitly be granted [Assignment: organization-defined privileges (i.e., they are trusted subjects)] such that they are not limited by some or all of the above constraints.</description>
                </statement>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-3"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Mandatory access control as defined in this control enhancement is synonymous with nondiscretionary access control, and is not constrained only to certain historical uses (e.g., implementations using the Bell-LaPadula Model). The above class of mandatory access control policies constrains what actions subjects can take with information obtained from data objects for which they have already been granted access, thus preventing the subjects from passing the information to unauthorized subjects and objects. This class of mandatory access control policies also constrains what actions subjects can take with respect to the propagation of access control privileges; that is, a subject with a privilege cannot pass that privilege to other subjects. The policy is uniformly enforced over all subjects and objects to which the information system has control. Otherwise, the access control policy can be circumvented. This enforcement typically is provided via an implementation that meets the reference monitor concept (see AC-25). The policy is bounded by the information system boundary (i.e., once the information is passed outside of the control of the system, additional means may be required to ensure that the constraints on the information remain in effect). The trusted subjects described above are granted privileges consistent with the concept of least privilege (see AC-6). Trusted subjects are only given the minimum privileges relative to the above policy necessary for satisfying organizational mission/business needs. The control is most applicable when there is some policy mandate (e.g., law, Executive Order, directive, or regulation) that establishes a policy regarding access to sensitive/classified information and some users of the information system are not authorized access to all sensitive/classified information resident in the information system. This control can operate in conjunction with AC-3 (4). A subject that is constrained in its operation by policies governed by this control is still able to operate under the less rigorous constraints of AC-3 (4), but policies governed by this control take precedence over the less rigorous constraints of AC-3 (4). For example, while a mandatory access control policy imposes a constraint preventing a subject from passing information to another subject operating at a different sensitivity label, AC-3 (4) permits the subject to pass the information to any subject with the same sensitivity label as the subject.</description>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-25"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#SC-11"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-3(4)</id>
            <title>DISCRETIONARY ACCESS CONTROL</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system enforces [Assignment: organization-defined discretionary access control policy] over defined subjects and objects where the policy specifies that a subject that has been granted access to information can do one or more of the following:</description>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-3 (4)(a)</number>
                    <description>Pass the  information to any other subjects or objects;</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-3 (4)(b)</number>
                    <description>Grant its privileges to other subjects;</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-3 (4)(c)</number>
                    <description>Change security attributes on subjects, objects, the information system, or the information system�s components;</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-3 (4)(d)</number>
                    <description>Choose the security attributes to be associated with newly created or revised objects; or</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-3 (4)(e)</number>
                    <description>Change the rules governing access control.</description>
                </statement>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-3"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>When discretionary access control policies are implemented, subjects are not constrained with regard to what actions they can take with information for which they have already been granted access. Thus, subjects that have been granted access to information are not prevented from passing (i.e., the subjects have the discretion to pass) the information to other subjects or objects. This control enhancement can operate in conjunction with AC-3 (3). A subject that is constrained in its operation by policies governed by AC-3 (3) is still able to operate under the less rigorous constraints of this control enhancement. Thus, while AC-3 (3) imposes constraints preventing a subject from passing information to another subject operating at a different sensitivity level, AC-3 (4) permits the subject to pass the information to any subject at the same sensitivity level. The policy is bounded by the information system boundary. Once the information is passed outside of the control of the information system, additional means may be required to ensure that the constraints remain in effect. While the older, more traditional definitions of discretionary access control require identity-based access control, that limitation is not required for this use of discretionary access control.</description>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-3(5)</id>
            <title>SECURITY-RELEVANT INFORMATION</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system prevents access to [Assignment: organization-defined security-relevant information] except during secure, non-operable system states.</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-3"/>
            <properties>
                <type>control-enhancement</type>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Security-relevant information is any information within information systems that can potentially impact the operation of security functions or the provision of security services in a manner that could result in failure to enforce system security policies or maintain the isolation of code and data. Security-relevant information includes, for example, filtering rules for routers/firewalls, cryptographic key management information, configuration parameters for security services, and access control lists. Secure, non-operable system states include the times in which information systems are not performing mission/business-related processing (e.g., the system is off-line for maintenance, troubleshooting, boot-up, shut down).</description>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CM-3"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-3(6)</id>
            <title>PROTECTION OF USER AND SYSTEM INFORMATION</title>
            <statement>
                <description>[Withdrawn: Incorporated into MP-4 and SC-28].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-3"/>
            <properties>
                <withdrawn>
                    <incorporated-into>MP-4</incorporated-into>
                    <incorporated-into>SC-28</incorporated-into>
                </withdrawn>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-3(7)</id>
            <title>ROLE-BASED ACCESS CONTROL</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system enforces a role-based access control policy over defined subjects and objects and controls access based upon [Assignment: organization-defined roles and users authorized to assume such roles].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-3"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Role-based access control (RBAC) is an access control policy that restricts information system access to authorized users. Organizations can create specific roles based on job functions and the authorizations (i.e., privileges) to perform needed operations on organizational information systems associated with the organization-defined roles. When users are assigned to the organizational roles, they inherit the authorizations or privileges defined for those roles. RBAC simplifies privilege administration for organizations because privileges are not assigned directly to every user (which can be a significant number of individuals for mid- to large-size organizations) but are instead acquired through role assignments. RBAC can be implemented either as a mandatory or discretionary form of access control. For organizations implementing RBAC with mandatory access controls, the requirements in AC-3 (3) define the scope of the subjects and objects covered by the policy.</description>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-3(8)</id>
            <title>REVOCATION OF ACCESS AUTHORIZATIONS</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system enforces the revocation of access authorizations resulting from changes to the security attributes of subjects and objects based on [Assignment: organization-defined rules governing the timing of revocations of access authorizations].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-3"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Revocation of access rules may differ based on the types of access revoked. For example, if a subject (i.e., user or process) is removed from a group, access may not be revoked until the next time the object (e.g., file) is opened or until the next time the subject attempts a new access to the object. Revocation based on changes to security labels may take effect immediately. Organizations can provide alternative approaches on how to make revocations immediate if information systems cannot provide such capability and immediate revocation is necessary.</description>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-3(9)</id>
            <title>CONTROLLED RELEASE</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system does not release information outside of the established system boundary unless:</description>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-3 (9)(a)</number>
                    <description>The receiving [Assignment: organization-defined information system or system component] provides [Assignment: organization-defined security safeguards]; and</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>AC-3 (9)(b)</number>
                    <description>[Assignment: organization-defined security safeguards] are used to validate the appropriateness of the information designated for release.</description>
                </statement>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-3"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Information systems can only protect organizational information within the confines of established system boundaries. Additional security safeguards may be needed to ensure that such information is adequately protected once it is passed beyond the established information system boundaries. Examples of information leaving the system boundary include transmitting information to an external information system or printing the information on one of its printers. In cases where the information system is unable to make a determination of the adequacy of the protections provided by entities outside its boundary, as a mitigating control, organizations determine procedurally whether the external information systems are providing adequate security. The means used to determine the adequacy of the security provided by external information systems include, for example, conducting inspections or periodic testing, establishing agreements between the organization and its counterpart organizations, or some other process. The means used by external entities to protect the information received need not be the same as those used by the organization, but the means employed are sufficient to provide consistent adjudication of the security policy to protect the information. This control enhancement requires information systems to employ technical or procedural means to validate the information prior to releasing it to external systems. For example, if the information system passes information to another system controlled by another organization, technical means are employed to validate that the security attributes associated with the exported information are appropriate for the receiving system. Alternatively, if the information system passes information to a printer in organization-controlled space, procedural means can be employed to ensure that only appropriately authorized individuals gain access to the printer. This control enhancement is most applicable when there is some policy mandate (e.g., law, Executive Order, directive, or regulation) that establishes policy regarding access to the information, and that policy applies beyond the realm of a particular information system or organization.</description>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>AC-3(10)</id>
            <title>AUDITED OVERRIDE OF ACCESS CONTROL MECHANISMS</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The organization employs an audited override of automated access control mechanisms under [Assignment: organization-defined conditions].</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#AC-3"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AU-2"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AU-6"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>
            </properties>
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control</type>
            <id>AC-4</id>
            <title>INFORMATION FLOW ENFORCEMENT</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The information system enforces approved authorizations for controlling the flow of information within the system and between interconnected systems based on [Assignment: organization-defined information flow control policies].</description>
            </statement>
            <properties>
                <family>ACCESS CONTROL</family>
                <priority>P1</priority>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Information flow control regulates where information is allowed to travel within an information system and between information systems (as opposed to who is allowed to access the information) and without explicit regard to subsequent accesses to that information. Flow control restrictions include, for example, keeping export-controlled information from being transmitted in the clear to the Internet, blocking outside traffic that claims to be from within the organization, restricting web requests to the Internet that are not from the internal web proxy server, and limiting information transfers between organizations based on data structures and content. Transferring information between information systems representing different security domains with different security policies introduces risk that such transfers violate one or more domain security policies. In such situations, information owners/stewards provide guidance at designated policy enforcement points between interconnected systems. Organizations consider mandating specific architectural solutions when required to enforce specific security policies. Enforcement includes, for example: (i) prohibiting information transfers between interconnected systems (i.e., allowing access only); (ii) employing hardware mechanisms to enforce one-way information flows; and (iii) implementing trustworthy regrading mechanisms to reassign security attributes and security labels.
                        Organizations commonly employ information flow control policies and enforcement mechanisms to control the flow of information between designated sources and destinations (e.g., networks, individuals, and devices) within information systems and between interconnected systems. Flow control is based on the characteristics of the information and/or the information path. Enforcement occurs, for example, in boundary protection devices (e.g., gateways, routers, guards, encrypted tunnels, firewalls) that employ rule sets or establish configuration settings that restrict information system services, provide a packet-filtering capability based on header information, or message-filtering capability based on message content (e.g., implementing key word searches or using document characteristics). Organizations also consider the trustworthiness of filtering/inspection mechanisms (i.e., hardware, firmware, and software components) that are critical to information flow enforcement. Control enhancements 3 through 22 primarily address cross-domain solution needs which focus on more advanced filtering techniques, in-depth analysis, and stronger flow enforcement mechanisms implemented in cross-domain products, for example, high-assurance guards. Such capabilities are generally not available in commercial off-the-shelf information technology products.</description>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-3"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-17"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-19"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#AC-21"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CM-6"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CM-7"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#SA-8"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#SC-2"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#SC-5"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#SC-7"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#SC-18"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>                
            </properties>          
        </item>
        <!-- add enhancements for AC-4 -->
        
        <!-- SECURITY ASSESSMENT AND AUTHORIZATION -->
        <item>
            <type>control</type>
            <id>CA-2</id>
            <title>SECURITY ASSESSMENTS</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The organization:</description>
                <statement>
                    <number>CA-2a.</number>
                    <description>Develops a security assessment plan that describes the scope of the assessment including:</description>
                    <statement>
                        <number>CA-2a.1.</number>
                        <description>Security controls and control enhancements under assessment;</description>
                    </statement>
                    <statement>
                        <number>CA-2a.2.</number>
                        <description>Assessment procedures to be used to determine security control effectiveness; and</description>
                    </statement>
                    <statement>
                        <number>CA-2a.3.</number>
                        <description>Assessment environment, assessment team, and assessment roles and responsibilities;</description>
                    </statement>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>CA-2b.</number>
                    <description>Assesses the security controls in the information system and its environment of operation [Assignment: organization-defined frequency] to determine the extent to which the controls are implemented correctly, operating as intended, and producing the desired outcome with respect to meeting established security requirements;</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>CA-2c.</number>
                    <description>Produces a security assessment report that documents the results of the assessment; and</description>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                    <number>CA-2d.</number>
                    <description>Provides the results of the security control assessment to [Assignment: organization-defined individuals or roles].</description>
                </statement>
            </statement>
            <properties>
                <family>SECURITY ASSESSMENT AND AUTHORIZATION</family>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Organizations assess security controls in organizational information systems and the environments in which those systems operate as part of: (i) initial and ongoing security authorizations; (ii) FISMA annual assessments; (iii) continuous monitoring; and (iv) system development life cycle activities. Security assessments: (i) ensure that information security is built into organizational information systems; (ii) identify weaknesses and deficiencies early in the development process; (iii) provide essential information needed to make risk-based decisions as part of security authorization processes; and (iv) ensure compliance to vulnerability mitigation procedures. Assessments are conducted on the implemented security controls from Appendix F (main catalog) and Appendix G (Program Management controls) as documented in System Security Plans and Information Security Program Plans. Organizations can use other types of assessment activities such as vulnerability scanning and system monitoring to maintain the security posture of information systems during the entire life cycle. Security assessment reports document assessment results in sufficient detail as deemed necessary by organizations, to determine the accuracy and completeness of the reports and whether the security controls are implemented correctly, operating as intended, and producing the desired outcome with respect to meeting security requirements. The FISMA requirement for assessing security controls at least annually does not require additional assessment activities to those activities already in place in organizational security authorization processes. Security assessment results are provided to the individuals or roles appropriate for the types of assessments being conducted. For example, assessments conducted in support of security authorization decisions are provided to authorizing officials or authorizing official designated representatives.
                        To satisfy annual assessment requirements, organizations can use assessment results from the following sources: (i) initial or ongoing information system authorizations; (ii) continuous monitoring; or (iii)   system development life cycle activities. Organizations ensure that security assessment results are current, relevant to the determination of security control effectiveness, and obtained with the appropriate level of assessor independence. Existing security control assessment results can be reused to the extent that the results are still valid and can also be supplemented with additional assessments as needed. Subsequent to initial authorizations and in accordance with OMB policy, organizations assess security controls during continuous monitoring. Organizations establish the frequency for ongoing security control assessments in accordance with organizational continuous monitoring strategies. Information Assurance Vulnerability Alerts provide useful examples of vulnerability mitigation procedures. External audits (e.g., audits by external entities such as regulatory agencies) are outside the scope of this control.</description>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CA-5"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CA-6"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#CA-7"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#PM-9"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#RA-5"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#SA-11"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#SA-12"/>
                    <link rel="related" href="#SI-4"/>
                </supplemental-guidance>                
            </properties>            
        </item>
        <item>
            <type>control-enhancement</type>
            <id>CA-2(1)</id>
            <title>INDEPENDENT ASSESSORS</title>
            <statement>
                <description>The organization employs assessors or assessment teams with [Assignment: organization-defined level of independence] to conduct security control assessments.</description>
            </statement>
            <link rel="parent" href="#CA-2"/>
            <properties>
                <supplemental-guidance>
                    <description>Independent assessors or assessment teams are individuals or groups who conduct impartial assessments of organizational information systems. Impartiality implies that assessors are free from any perceived or actual conflicts of interest with regard to the development, operation, or management of the organizational information systems under assessment or to the determination of security control effectiveness. To achieve impartiality, assessors should not: (i) create a mutual or conflicting interest with the organizations where the assessments are being conducted; (ii) assess their own work; (iii) act as management or employees of the organizations they are serving; or (iv) place themselves in positions of advocacy for the organizations acquiring their services. Independent assessments can be obtained from elements within organizations or can be contracted to public or private sector entities outside of organizations. Authorizing officials determine the required level of independence based on the security categories of information systems and/or the ultimate risk to organizational operations, organizational assets, or individuals. Authorizing officials also determine if the level of assessor independence provides sufficient assurance that the results are sound and can be used to make credible, risk-based decisions. This includes determining whether contracted security assessment services have sufficient independence, for example, when information system owners are not directly involved in contracting processes or cannot unduly influence the impartiality of assessors conducting assessments. In special situations, for example, when organizations that own the information systems are small or organizational structures require that assessments are conducted by individuals that are in the developmental, operational, or management chain of system owners, independence in assessment processes can be achieved by ensuring that assessment results are carefully reviewed and analyzed by independent teams of experts to validate the completeness, accuracy, integrity, and reliability of the results. Organizations recognize that assessments performed for purposes other than direct support to authorization decisions are, when performed by assessors with sufficient independence, more likely to be useable for such decisions, thereby reducing the need to repeat assessments.</description>
                </supplemental-guidance>                
            </properties>
        </item>
        <!-- add the other enhancements to CA-2 -->
        
        <!-- add the rest of the controls and enhancements -->
    </items>
</catalog>